<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ44">
  <title>Protecting Your Directories and Files</title>

  <para>This chapter explains how to protect AFS files and directories by defining permissions on an access control list.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ45">
    <title>Access Control Lists</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>protection</primary>

      <secondary>for files and directories</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

      <secondary>granting and denying to users</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>directories</primary>

      <secondary>setting access control list</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>described</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>access control list</primary>

      <see>ACL</see>
    </indexterm>

    <para>AFS augments and refines the standard UNIX scheme for controlling access to files and directories. Instead of using mode
    bits to define access permissions for individual files, as UNIX does, AFS stores an <emphasis>access control list</emphasis>
    (<emphasis>ACL</emphasis>) with each directory. It defines which users and groups can access the directory and the files it
    contains, and in what manner. An ACL can store up to about 20 entries, each of which pairs a user or group and a set of
    permissions. AFS defines seven permissions rather than the three that UNIX uses.</para>

    <para>Another refinement to the standard UNIX protection scheme is that users can define their own protection
    <emphasis>groups</emphasis> and then place the groups on ACLs as though they were individual users. A group can include both
    users and machines. Each user who belongs to a group inherits all of the permissions granted to the group on the ACL. Similarly,
    all users who are logged into a machine that belongs to a group inherits all of the permissions granted to the group. You can
    create groups to place on ACLs and also use groups that other users have created. To learn more about group creation, see <link
    linkend="HDRWQ60">Using Groups</link>.</para>

    <para>In addition, AFS defines two system groups called <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis>. By placing them on ACLs, you can grant access to large numbers of users at once. See
    <link linkend="HDRWQ50">Using the System Groups on ACLs</link>.</para>

    <para>Although AFS uses ACLs to protect files and directories, it also uses the UNIX mode bits to a limited extent. See <link
    linkend="HDRWQ59">How AFS Uses the UNIX Mode Bits</link>.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_81">
      <title>Directory Level Access Control</title>

      <para>As noted, AFS associates an ACL with each directory, and it applies to all of the files stored in the directory. Files
      do not have separate ACLs. Defining access at the directory level has several consequences: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The permissions on a directory's ACL apply to all of the files in the directory. When you move a file to a
            different directory, you effectively change its permissions to those on its new directory's ACL. Changing a directory's
            ACL changes the protection on all the files in it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you create a subdirectory, it inherits the current ACL of its parent directory. You can then set the
            subdirectory's ACL to be different from its parent's. However, do not make the ACL on the parent directory more
            restrictive than on a subdirectory, because that can prevent users from accessing the subdirectory even when they have
            the necessary permissions on its ACL. Specifically, a user must have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis
            role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission (defined in <link linkend="HDRWQ46">The AFS ACL Permissions</link>) on the
            parent directory to reach its subdirectories. <indexterm>
                <primary>subdirectories, accessing</primary>
              </indexterm> <indexterm>
                <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

                <secondary>controlling at directory level</secondary>
              </indexterm></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>As a general rule, it makes sense to grant fairly liberal access to your home directory. If you need to protect certain
      files more closely, place them in subdirectories that have more restrictive ACLs.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ46">
    <title>The AFS ACL Permissions</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>access permissions on ACL</primary>

      <seealso>permissions on ACL</seealso>

      <seealso>ACL</seealso>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

      <secondary>defined</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>permissions defined</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>There are seven standard AFS ACL permissions. Functionally, they fall into two groups: one that applies to the directory
    itself and one that applies to the files.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ47">
      <title>The Four Directory Permissions</title>

      <para>The four permissions in this group are meaningful with respect to the directory itself. For example, the <emphasis
      role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>) permission does not control addition of data to a file, but
      rather creation of a new file or subdirectory. <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The l (lookup) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission functions as something of a gate keeper for access to the directory and its files, because a
              user must have it in order to exercise any other permissions. In particular, a user must have this permission to
              access anything in the directory's subdirectories. <indexterm>
                  <primary>lookup ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>l ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>

              <para>This permission enables a user to issue the following commands: <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis> command to list the names of the files and subdirectories in the
                    directory</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> command to obtain complete status information for the
                    directory element itself</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command to examine the directory's ACL</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>

              <para>This permission does not enable a user to read the contents of a file in the directory or to issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> commands with a filename as the argument.
              Those operations require the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission,
              which is described in <link linkend="HDRWQ48">The Three File Permissions</link>.</para>

              <para>Similarly, this permission does not enable a user to issue the <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">ls -l</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
              commands against a subdirectory of the directory. Those operations require the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis>
              permission on the ACL of the subdirectory itself.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The i (insert) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to add new files to the directory, either by creating or copying, and to create
              new subdirectories. It does not extend into any subdirectories, which are protected by their own ACLs. <indexterm>
                  <primary>insert ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>i ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The d (delete) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to remove files and subdirectories from the directory or move them into other
              directories (assuming that the user has the <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> permission on the ACL of the other
              directories). <indexterm>
                  <primary>delete ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>d ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The a (administer) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to change the directory's ACL. Members of the <emphasis
              role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group implicitly have this permission on every directory (that is, even
              if that group does not appear on the ACL). Similarly, the owner of a directory implicitly has this permission on its
              ACL and those of all directories below it. <indexterm>
                  <primary>administer ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>a ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ48">
      <title>The Three File Permissions</title>

      <para>The three permissions in this group are meaningful with respect to files in a directory, rather than the directory
      itself or its subdirectories. <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The r (read) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to read the contents of files in the directory and to issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command to stat the file elements. <indexterm>
                  <primary>read ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>r ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The w (write) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to modify the contents of files in the directory and to issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">chmod</emphasis> command to change their UNIX mode bits. <indexterm>
                  <primary>write ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>w ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">The k (lock) permission</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This permission enables a user to run programs that issue system calls to lock files in the directory.
              <indexterm>
                  <primary>k ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm> <indexterm>
                  <primary>lock ACL permission</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_85">
      <title>The Eight Auxiliary Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>auxiliary ACL permissions</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>auxiliary permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>AFS provides eight additional permissions that do not have a defined meaning. They are denoted by the uppercase letters
      <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">D</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">G</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">H</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Your system administrator can choose to write application programs that assign a meaning to one or more of the
      permissions, and then place them on ACLs to control file access by those programs. Use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      listacl</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> commands to display and set the auxiliary permissions on
      ACLs just like the standard seven.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_86">
      <title>Shorthand Notation for Sets of Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>shorthand notation for grouping sets of permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>shorthand notation for ACL permissions</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

        <secondary>shorthand for</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>You can combine the seven permissions in any way in an ACL entry, but certain combinations are more useful than others.
      Four of the more common combinations have corresponding shorthand forms. When using the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      setacl</emphasis> command to define ACL entries, you can provide either one or more of the individual letters that represent
      the permissions, or one of the following shorthand forms: <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Represents all seven standard permissions (<emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>) <indexterm>
                  <primary>all shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Removes the entry from the ACL, leaving the user or group with no permission <indexterm>
                  <primary>none shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Represents the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) and <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permissions <indexterm>
                  <primary>read shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Represents all permissions except <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis
              role="bold">administer</emphasis>): <emphasis role="bold">rlidwk</emphasis> <indexterm>
                  <primary>write shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ49">
      <title>About Normal and Negative Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>normal vs. negative permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>normal permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>negative permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

        <secondary>normal vs. negative</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>normal ACL permissions</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>normal ACL permissions</primary>

        <secondary>setting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>negative ACL permissions</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>ACLs enable you both to grant and to deny access to a directory and the files in it. To grant access, use the <emphasis
      role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to create an ACL entry that associates a set of permissions with a user or group, as
      described in <link linkend="HDRWQ54">Changing an ACL</link>. When you use the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
      command to display an ACL (as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ52">Displaying an ACL</link>), such entries appear underneath
      the following header, which uses the term <emphasis>rights</emphasis> to refer to permissions:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Normal rights
</programlisting>

      <para>There are two ways to deny access: <indexterm>
          <primary>negative ACL permissions</primary>

          <secondary>setting</secondary>
        </indexterm> <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The recommended method is simply to omit an entry for the user or group from the ACL, or to omit the appropriate
            permissions from an entry. Use the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to remove or edit an existing
            entry. In most cases, this method is enough to prevent access of certain kinds or by certain users. You must take care,
            however, not to grant the undesired permissions to any groups to which such users belong.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The more explicit method for denying access is to place an entry on the <emphasis>negative permissions</emphasis>
            section of an ACL, by including the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis role="bold">fs
            setacl</emphasis> command. For instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ56">To Add, Remove, or Edit Negative ACL
            Permissions</link>. The <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command displays the negative permissions section of
            an ACL underneath the following header: <programlisting>
   Negative rights
</programlisting></para>

            <para>When determining what type of access to grant to a user, AFS first examines all of the entries in the normal
            permissions section of the ACL. It then subtracts any permissions associated with the user (or with groups to which the
            user belongs) on the negative permissions section of the ACL. Therefore, negative permissions always cancel out normal
            permissions.</para>

            <para>Negative permissions can be confusing, because they reverse the usual meaning of the <emphasis role="bold">fs
            setacl</emphasis> command. In particular, combining the <emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand and the
            <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag is a double negative: by removing an entry from the negative permissions
            section of the ACL, you enable a user once again to obtain permissions via entries in the normal permissions section.
            Combining the <emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> shorthand with the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag
            explicitly denies all permissions.</para>

            <para>It is useless to create an entry in the negative permissions section if an entry in the normal permissions section
            grants the denied permissions to the <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group. In this case, users can
            obtain the permissions simply by using the <emphasis role="bold">unlog</emphasis> command to discard their tokens. When
            they do so, AFS recognizes them as the <emphasis role="bold">anonymous</emphasis> user, who belongs to the <emphasis
            role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group but does not match the entries on the negative permissions section of the
            ACL.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_88">
      <title>Setting DFS ACLs</title>

      <para>If your machine is configured to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit, then you can use
      the AFS <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> commands to display and set
      the ACLs on DFS directories and files that you own. However, DFS uses a slightly different set of permissions and a different
      syntax for ACL entries. See the DFS documentation or ask your system administrator.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ50">
    <title>Using the System Groups on ACLs</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>system groups</primary>

        <secondary>using on ACLs</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>system:anyuser group</primary>

        <secondary>using on ACLs</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>system:authuser group</primary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>system:administrators group</primary>
      </indexterm> AFS defines two <emphasis>system groups</emphasis> that grant access to a large number of users at once when
    placed on an ACL. However, you cannot control the membership of these groups, so consider carefully what kind of permissions you
    wish to give them. (You do control the membership of the groups you own; see <link linkend="HDRWQ60">Using Groups</link>.)
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Includes anyone who can access the cell's file tree, including users who have tokens in the local cell, users who
            have logged in on a local AFS client machine but have not obtained tokens (such as the local superuser <emphasis
            role="bold">root</emphasis>), and users who have connected to a local machine from outside the cell. Creating an ACL
            entry for this group is the only way to extend access to AFS users from foreign cells, unless your system administrator
            creates local authentication accounts for them. <indexterm>
                <primary>ACL</primary>

                <secondary>foreign users on</secondary>
              </indexterm></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Includes all users who have a valid AFS token obtained from the local cell's AFS authentication service.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para>The third system group, <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis>, includes a small group of administrators
    who have extensive permissions in the cell. You do not generally need to put this group on your ACLs, because its members always
    have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission on every ACL, even if the
    group does not appear on it.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_90">
      <title>Enabling Access to Subdirectories</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>subdirectories, accessing</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

        <secondary>controlling for subdirectories</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>A user must have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission on a directory to access its subdirectories in any
      way. Even if users have extensive permissions on a subdirectory, they cannot access it if the parent directory's ACL does not
      grant the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission.</para>

      <para>You can grant the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission in one of three ways: grant it to a system group
      (<emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis>), grant it to individual
      users, or grant it to one or more groups of users defined by you or other users (see <link linkend="HDRWQ60">Using
      Groups</link>). Granting the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission to the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group is the easiest option and is generally secure because the permission only enables
      users to list the contents of the directory, not to read the files in it. If you want to enable only locally authenticated
      users to list a directory's contents, substitute the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group for the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group. Your system administrator has possibly already created an entry on your home
      directory's ACL that grants the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions to the
      <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_91">
      <title>Extending Access to Service Processes</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

        <secondary>enabling for service processes</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>It is sometimes necessary to grant more extensive permissions to the <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis>
      group so that processes that provide printing and mail delivery service can work correctly. For example, printing processes
      sometimes need the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> permission in addition to the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis>
      permission. A mail delivery process possibly needs the <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> permission to place new messages in
      your mail directory. Your system administrator has probably already created the necessary ACL entries. If you notice an ACL
      entry for which the purpose is unclear, check with your system administrator before removing it.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ51">
      <title>Extending Access to Users from Foreign Cells</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

          <secondary>enabling for users from foreign cells</secondary>
        </indexterm> The only way to grant access to users from foreign cells who do not have an account in your cell is to put the
      <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group on an ACL. Remember, however, that such an entry extends access to
      everyone who can reach your cell, not just the AFS users from foreign cells that you have in mind.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ52">
    <title>Displaying an ACL</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>displaying</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>displaying</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

      <secondary>displaying</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To display the ACL associated with a file or directory, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
    command.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine on which you issue the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command is configured to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit,
    you can use the command to display the ACL on DFS files and directories. To display a DFS directory's Initial Container or
    Initial Object ACL instead of the regular one, include the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command's <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flag. For more information, ask your system administrator.
    The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter ignores the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when displaying an AFS ACL.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ53">
      <title>To display an ACL</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command. <indexterm>
              <primary>fs commands</primary>

              <secondary>listacl</secondary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>fs listacl</secondary>
            </indexterm> <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">la</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">listacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis
                role="bold">lista</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold"><replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable></emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names one or more files or directories for which to display the ACL. For a file, the output displays the ACL
                on its directory. If you omit this argument, the output is for the current working directory. Partial pathnames are
                interpreted relative to the current working directory. You can also use the following notation on its own or as part
                of a pathname: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(A single period). Specifies the current working directory.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">..</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(Two periods). Specifies the current working directory's parent directory.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(The asterisk). Specifies each file and subdirectory in the current working directory. The ACL
                        displayed for a file is always the same as for its directory, but the ACL for each subdirectory can
                        differ.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                  </variablelist></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The output for each file or directory specified as <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> begins with the following
      header to identify it:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Access list for  <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> is
</programlisting>

      <para>The <computeroutput>Normal rights</computeroutput> header appears on the next line, followed by lines that each pair a
      user or group name and a set of permissions. The permissions appear as the single letters defined in <link
      linkend="HDRWQ46">The AFS ACL Permissions</link>, and always in the order <emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>. If there
      are any negative permissions, the <computeroutput>Negative rights</computeroutput> header appears next, followed by pairs of
      negative permissions.</para>

      <para>If the following error message appears instead of an ACL, you do not have the permissions needed to display an ACL. To
      specify a directory name as the <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> argument, you must have the <emphasis
      role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on the ACL. To specify a filename, you must also
      have the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission on its directory's ACL.</para>

      <programlisting>
   fs: You don't have the required access permissions on '<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>'
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_95">
      <title>Example: Displaying the ACL on One Directory</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>displaying ACL for single directory</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following example displays the ACL on user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory in the ABC
      Corporation cell:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs la /afs/abc.com/usr/terry</emphasis>
   Access list for /afs/abc.com/usr/terry is
   Normal rights:
      system:authuser rl
      pat rlw
      terry rlidwka
   Negative rights:
      terry:other-dept rl
      jones rl
</programlisting>

      <para>where <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>, and <emphasis
      role="bold">jones</emphasis> are individual users, <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> is a system group, and
      <emphasis role="bold">terry:other-dept</emphasis> is a group that <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> owns. The list of
      normal permissions grants all permissions to <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">rlw</emphasis>
      permissions to <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis>, and the <emphasis role="bold">rl</emphasis> permissions to the members of
      the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group.</para>

      <para>The list of negative permissions denies the <emphasis role="bold">rl</emphasis> permissions to <emphasis
      role="bold">jones</emphasis> and the members of the <emphasis role="bold">terry:other-dept</emphasis> group. These entries
      effectively prevent them from accessing <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory in any way; they cancel out
      the <emphasis role="bold">rl</emphasis> permissions extended to the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group,
      which is the only entry on the normal permissions section of the ACL that possibly applies to them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_96">
      <title>Example: Displaying the ACLs on Multiple Directories</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>displaying ACLs for multiple directories</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following example illustrates how you can specify pathnames in different ways, and the appearance of the output for
      multiple directories. It displays the ACL for three directories: the current working directory (which is a subdirectory of
      user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory), the home directory for user <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis>, and another subdirectory of <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory called
      <emphasis role="bold">plans</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl  .  /afs/abc.com/usr/pat  ../plans</emphasis>
   Access list for . is
   Normal rights:
      system:anyuser rl
      pat:dept rliw
   Access list for /afs/abc.com/usr/pat is
   Normal rights:
      system:anyuser rl
      pat rlidwka
      terry rliw 
   Access list for ../plans is
   Normal rights:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rlidw
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ54">
    <title>Changing an ACL</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>changing</primary>

      <secondary>ACLs</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>setting permissions on ACL</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>setting</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

      <secondary>setting</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To add, remove, or edit ACL entries, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command. By default, the command
    manipulates entries on the normal permissions section of the ACL. To manipulate entries on the negative permissions section,
    include the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag as instructed in <link linkend="HDRWQ56">To Add, Remove, or Edit
    Negative ACL Permissions</link>.</para>

    <para>You can change any ACL on which you already have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> permission. You always have the
    <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> permission on the ACL of every directory that you own, even if you accidentally remove that
    permission from the ACL. (The <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> command reports a directory's owner.) Your system
    administrator normally designates you as the owner of your home directory and its subdirectories, and you possibly own other
    directories also.</para>

    <para>If an ACL entry already exists for the user or group you specify, then the new permissions completely replace the existing
    permissions rather than being added to them. In other words, when issuing the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis>
    command, you must include all permissions that you want to grant to a user or group.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine on which you issue the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command is configured to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit,
    you can use the command to set the ACL on DFS files and directories. To set a DFS directory's Initial Container or Initial
    Object ACL instead of the regular one, include the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command's <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flag. For more information, ask your system administrator.
    The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter ignores the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when setting an AFS ACL.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ55">
      <title>To Add, Remove, or Edit Normal ACL Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>creating</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry in normal permissions section</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>creating normal entry</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>adding</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry to normal permissions section</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>granting access to AFS filespace</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>access to AFS filespace</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entries control</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>directories</primary>

        <secondary>granting access</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>files</primary>

        <secondary>granting access</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to edit entries in the normal permissions section of the
      ACL. To remove an entry, specify the <emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand as the permissions. If an ACL entry
      already exists for a user or group, the permissions you specify completely replace those in the existing entry. <indexterm>
          <primary>commands</primary>

          <secondary>fs setacl</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>fs commands</primary>

          <secondary>setacl</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl  -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript> <emphasis
          role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>
</programlisting>

      <para>where <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis> is
              the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
              role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the current working directory. You
              can also use the following notation on its own or as part of a pathname: <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(A single period). If used by itself, sets the ACL on the current working directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">..</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(Two periods). If used by itself, sets the ACL on the current working directory's parent
                      directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(The asterisk). Sets the ACL on each of the subdirectories in the current working directory. You must
                      precede it with the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> switch, since it potentially designates multiple
                      directories. The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter generates the following error message
                      for each file in the directory: <programlisting>
   fs: '<replaceable>filename</replaceable>': Not a directory
</programlisting></para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>

              <para>If you specify only one directory (or file) name, you can omit the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> switches. For more on omitting switches, see <link linkend="HDRWQ86">Appendix B,
              AFS Command Syntax and Online Help</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
              the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces.</para>

              <para>To define the permissions, provide either:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>One or more of the letters that represent the standard or auxiliary permissions (<emphasis
                  role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">ABCDEFGH</emphasis>), in any order</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>One of the four shorthand notations: <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>)</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> (removes the entry)</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rl</emphasis>)</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rlidwk</emphasis>)</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para>On a single command line, you can combine user and group entries. Also, you can both combine individual letters
              and use the shorthand notations, but not within a single pair.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_99">
      <title>Example: Adding a Single ACL Entry</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>adding a user to an ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Either of the following example commands grants user <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> the <emphasis
      role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the <emphasis
      role="bold">notes</emphasis> subdirectory of the current working directory. They illustrate how it is possible to omit the
      <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> switches when you name only one
      directory.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa notes pat rl</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa pat read</emphasis>
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_100">
      <title>Example: Setting Several ACL Entries on One Directory</title>

      <para>The following example edits the ACL for the current working directory. It removes the entry for the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group, and adds two entries: one grants all permissions except <emphasis
      role="bold">a</emphasis> to the members of the <emphasis role="bold">terry:colleagues</emphasis> group and the other grants
      the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions to the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa  -dir . -acl  system:anyuser none  terry:colleagues write</emphasis>  \
            <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser rl</emphasis>
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ56">
      <title>To Add, Remove, or Edit Negative ACL Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>creating</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry in negative permissions section</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>creating negative entry</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>adding</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry to negative permissions section</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>denying access with negative ACL entry</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>directories</primary>

        <secondary>denying access</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>files</primary>

        <secondary>denying access</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag to
      edit entries in the negative permissions section of the ACL. To remove an entry, specify the <emphasis
      role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand as the permissions. If an ACL entry already exists for a user or group, the permissions
      you specify completely replace those in the existing entry. <indexterm>
          <primary>fs commands</primary>

          <secondary>setacl</secondary>

          <tertiary>with -negative flag</tertiary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>commands</primary>

          <secondary>fs setacl</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl  -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript> <emphasis
          role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>  <emphasis
          role="bold">-negative</emphasis> 
</programlisting>

      <para>where <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis> is
              the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the negative ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
              role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link linkend="HDRWQ55">To
              Add, Remove, or Edit Normal ACL Permissions</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
              the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces. For a detailed description of acceptable values,
              see <link linkend="HDRWQ55">To Add, Remove, or Edit Normal ACL Permissions</link>. Keep in mind that the usual meaning
              of each permission is reversed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Places the entries defined by the <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument on the negative permissions
              section of the ACL for each directory named by the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> argument.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_102">
      <title>Example: Setting an Entry in the Negative Permissions Section</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>creating entry on negative permissions section of ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>User <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> has granted all access permissions except <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis>
      to the group <emphasis role="bold">terry:team</emphasis> on her <emphasis role="bold">plans</emphasis> subdirectory.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">cd /afs/abc.com/usr/terry</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl plans</emphasis>
   Access control list for plans is
   Normal rights:
      system:anyuser rl
      terry:team rlidwk
      terry  rlidwka
</programlisting>

      <para>However, <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> notices that one of the members of the group, user <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis>, has been making inappropriate changes to files. To prevent this without removing <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis> from the group or changing the permissions for the <emphasis role="bold">terry:team</emphasis>
      group, <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> creates an entry on the negative permissions section of the ACL that denies the
      <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> permissions to <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis>:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl plans pat wd -negative</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl plans</emphasis>
   Access control list for plans is
   Normal rights:
      system:anyuser rl
      terry:team rlidwk
      terry: rlidwka
   Negative rights:
      pat wd
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_103">
      <title>Example: Restoring Access by Removing an Entry from the Negative Permissions Section</title>

      <para>In the previous example, user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> put <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> on the
      negative permissions section of ACL for the <emphasis role="bold">plans</emphasis> subdirectory. But the result has been
      inconvenient and <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> has promised not to change files any more. To enable <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis> to exercise all permissions granted to the members of the <emphasis
      role="bold">terry:team</emphasis> group, <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> removes the entry for <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis> from the negative permissions section of the ACL.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl plans pat  none -negative</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl plans</emphasis>
   Access control list for plans is
   Normal rights:
      system:anyuser rl
      terry:team rlidwk
      terry  rlidwka
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ57">
    <title>Completely Replacing an ACL</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>replacing all entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>clearing</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>replacing</primary>

      <secondary>all entries on ACL</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>erasing all ACL entries</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>clearing all ACL entries</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>removing</primary>

      <secondary>all ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>directories</primary>

      <secondary>replacing ACL</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>It is sometimes simplest to clear an ACL completely before defining new permissions on it, for instance if the mix of
    normal and negative permissions makes it difficult to understand how their interaction affects access to the directory. To clear
    an ACL completely while you define new entries, include the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag on the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command. When you include this flag, you can create entries on either the normal permissions or
    the negative permissions section of the ACL, but not on both at once.</para>

    <para>Remember to create an entry for yourself. As the owner of the directory, you always have the <emphasis
    role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission required to replace a deleted entry, but the
    effects the effects of a missing ACL entry can be confusing enough to make it difficult to realize that the problem is a missing
    entry. In particular, the lack of the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission
    prevents you from using any shorthand notation in pathnames (such as a period for the current working directory or two periods
    for the parent directory).</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_105">
      <title>To Replace an ACL Completely</title>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag to
      clear the ACL completely before setting either normal or negative permissions. Because you need to grant the owner of the
      directory all permissions, it is better in most cases to set normal permissions at this point. <indexterm>
          <primary>fs commands</primary>

          <secondary>setacl</secondary>

          <tertiary>completely replacing ACL</tertiary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl  -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript> <emphasis
          role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript> <emphasis
          role="bold">-clear</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis> is
              the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
              role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link linkend="HDRWQ55">To
              Add, Remove, or Edit Normal ACL Permissions</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
              the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces. Remember to grant all permissions to the owner of
              the directory. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link linkend="HDRWQ55">To Add, Remove, or Edit
              Normal ACL Permissions</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Removes all entries from each ACL before creating the entries indicated by the <emphasis
              role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Places the entries defined by the <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument on the negative permissions
              section of each ACL.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_106">
      <title>Example: Replacing an ACL</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>replacing an ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following example clears the ACL on the current working directory and creates entries that grant all permissions to
      user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> and all permissions except <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> to user <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl . terry all pat write -clear</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl .</emphasis>
   Access control list for . is
   Normal rights:
     terry rlidwka
     pat rlidwk
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ58">
    <title>Copying ACLs Between Directories</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>copying between directories</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>ACL as copy of another</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>copying</primary>

      <secondary>ACL between directories</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>directories</primary>

      <secondary>copying ACLs between</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis> command copies a source directory's ACL to one or more destination
    directories. It does not affect the source ACL at all, but changes each destination ACL as follows: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry on the source ACL does not exist on the destination ACL, the command copies it to the destination
          ACL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry on the destination ACL does not also exist on the source ACL, the command does not remove it unless you
          include the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag, which overwrites the destination ACL completely.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry is on both ACLs, the command changes the destination ACL entry to match the source ACL entry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>To copy an ACL, you must have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission on the source ACL and the <emphasis
    role="bold">a</emphasis> permission on each destination ACL. If you identify the source directory by naming a file in it, you
    must also have the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> permission on the source ACL. To display the permissions you have on the
    two directories, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ52">Displaying
    an ACL</link>.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine on which you issue the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis> command is configured for access to a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration
    Toolkit, you can use the command to copy ACLs between DFS files and directories also. The command includes <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags for altering a DFS directory's Initial Container and
    Initial Object ACLs as well as its regular ACL; for details, ask your system administrator. You cannot copy ACLs between AFS and
    DFS directories, because they use different ACL formats. The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter ignores the
    <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when copying AFS
    ACLs.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_108">
      <title>To Copy an ACL Between Directories</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs copyacl</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>copyacl</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis> command to copy a source ACL to the ACL on one or more destination
      directories.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl -fromdir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>source directory</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-todir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>destination directory</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">co</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">copyacl</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-fromdir</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Names the source directory from which to copy the ACL. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the current
              working directory. If this argument names a file, the ACL is copied from its directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-todir</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Names each destination directory to which to copy the source ACL. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to
              the current working directory. Filenames are not acceptable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Completely overwrites each destination directory's ACL with the source ACL.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_109">
      <title>Example: Copying an ACL from One Directory to Another</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>copying ACL between directories</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>In this example, user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> copies the ACL from her home directory (the current working
      directory) to its <emphasis role="bold">plans</emphasis> subdirectory. She begins by displaying both ACLs.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl . plans</emphasis>
   Access list for . is
   Normal rights:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rlidwk
      jones rl
   Access list for plans is
   Normal rights:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rl
      smith rl   
     
  % <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl -from . -to plans</emphasis>
   
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl . plans</emphasis>
   Access list for . is
   Normal rights:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rlidwk
      jones rl
   Access list for plans is
   Normal rights:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rlidwk
      jones rl
      smith rl   
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ59">
    <title>How AFS Uses the UNIX Mode Bits</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary>

      <secondary>mode bits, interpretation</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>mode bits (UNIX)</primary>

      <secondary>interpretation in AFS</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Although AFS protects data primarily with ACLs rather than mode bits, it does not ignore the mode bits entirely. An
    explanation of how mode bits work in the UNIX file system is outside the scope of this document, and the following discussion
    assumes you understand them; if necessary, see your UNIX documentation. Also, the following discussion does not cover the
    setuid, setgid or sticky bits. If you need to understand how those bits work on AFS files, see the <emphasis>IBM AFS
    Administration Guide</emphasis> or ask your system administrator.</para>

    <para>AFS uses the UNIX mode bits in the following way:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It uses the initial bit to distinguish files and directories. This is the bit that appears first in the output from
        the <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command and shows the hyphen (<computeroutput>-</computeroutput>) for a file or
        the letter <computeroutput>d</computeroutput> for a directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It does not use any of the mode bits on a directory. The AFS ACL alone controls directory access.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For a file, the owner (first) set of bits interacts with the ACL entries that apply to the file in the following way.
        AFS does not use the group or world (second and third sets) of mode bits at all. <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the first <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> mode bit is not set, no one (including the owner) can read the
              file, no matter what permissions they have on the ACL. If the bit is set, users also need the <emphasis
              role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the file's directory to read
              the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the first <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> mode bit is not set, no one (including the owner) can modify the
              file. If the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> bit is set, users also need the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the file's directory to modify the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>There is no ACL permission directly corresponding to the <emphasis role="bold">x</emphasis> mode bit, but to
              execute a file stored in AFS, the user must also have the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the file's directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When you issue the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">chmod</emphasis> command on an AFS file or directory, AFS changes the bits
    appropriately. To change a file's mode bits, you must have the AFS <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> permission on the ACL of
    the file's directory. To change a directory's mode bits, you must have the <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">i</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on its ACL. <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>chmod</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>chmod command</primary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_111">
      <title>Example: Disabling Write Access for a File</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>examples</primary>

          <secondary>using chmod</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <para>Suppose <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> is chairing a committee that is writing a proposal. As each section is
      approved, she turns off write access to that file to prevent further changes. For example, the following <emphasis
      role="bold">chmod</emphasis> command turns off the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> mode bits on the file <emphasis
      role="bold">proposal.chap2</emphasis>. This makes it impossible for anyone to change the file, no matter what permissions are
      granted on the directory ACL.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">chmod -w proposal.chap2</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis>
   -rw-r--r--  1 terry     573 Nov 10 09:57 conclusion
   -r--r--r--  1 terry     573 Nov 15 10:34 intro
   -r--r--r--  1 terry     573 Dec  1 15:07 proposal.chap2
   -rw-r--r--  1 terry     573 Nov 10 09:57 proposal.chap3
   -rw-r--r--  1 terry     573 Nov 10 09:57 proposal.chap4
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>