<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="HDRWQ90">
  <title>Glossary</title>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>A</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">a (administer) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that allows the possessor to change the entries on the ACL .</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">a Privacy Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The fourth privacy flag on a group, which enables the possessor to add members to it.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Access Control List (ACL)</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A list associated with an AFS directory that specifies what actions a user or group can perform on the directory and
        the files in it. There are seven access permissions: <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis
        role="bold">administer</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>), <emphasis
        role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> (<emphasis
        role="bold">lock</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>), <emphasis
        role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>), and <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis
        role="bold">write</emphasis>).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">ACL Entry</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An entry on an ACL that pairs a user or group with specific access permissions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Alias</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An alternative name for an AFS command.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">all ACL Shorthand</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A shorthand notation used with the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to represent all seven
        permissions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Anonymous</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The identity assigned to a user who does not have a valid token for the local cell.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Argument</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The portion of a command that names an entity to be affected by the command. Arguments consist of two parts: a
        <emphasis>switch</emphasis> and one or more <emphasis>instances</emphasis>. Some AFS commands take one or more
        arguments.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Authenticate</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>To become recognized as a valid AFS user by providing the correct password. Authenticate by logging onto a machine
        that uses an AFS-modified login utility or by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command. Only authenticated
        users can perform most AFS actions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>B</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Byte, kilobyte</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A unit of measure used to measure usage of space in a volume or on a partition. A kilobyte block is equal to 1024
        bytes.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>C</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Cache Manager</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of modifications to the operating system on a client machine which enables users on the machine to access files
        stored in AFS. The Cache Manager requests files from the File Server and stores (<emphasis>caches</emphasis>) a copy of each
        file on the client machine's local disk. Application programs then use the cached copy, which eliminates repeated network
        requests to file server machines.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Cached File</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A copy of a file that the Cache Manager stores on a workstation's local disk.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Callback</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A promise from the File Server to contact the Cache Manager if the centrally stored copy of the file changes while the
        Cache Manager has a cached copy. If the file is altered, the File Server <emphasis>breaks</emphasis> the callback. The next
        time an application program asks for data from the file, the Cache Manager notices the broken callback and retrieves an
        updated copy of the file from the File Server. Callbacks ensure the user is working with the most recent copy of a
        file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Cell</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An independently administered site running AFS, consisting of a collection of file server machines and client machines
        defined to belong to the cell. A machine can belong to only one cell at a time.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Client Machines</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Computers that perform computations for users. Users normally work on a client machine, accessing files stored on a
        file server machine.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Client/Server Computing</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A computing system in which two types of computers (client machines and server machines) perform different specialized
        functions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Command</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A string of characters indicating an action for an AFS server to perform. For a description of AFS command syntax, see
        <link linkend="HDRWQ86">Appendix B, AFS Command Syntax and Online Help</link>.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Command Suite</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A group of AFS commands with related functions. The command suite name is the first word in many AFS commands.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Complete Pathname</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A full specification of a file's location in AFS, starting at the root of the filespace (by convention mounted at the
        <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis> directory) and specifying all the directories the Cache Manager must pass through to
        access the file. The names of the directories are separated by slashes.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>D</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">d (delete) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that enables the possessor to remove elements from a directory.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Directory</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A logical structure containing a collection of files and other directories.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Distributed File System</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A file system that joins the file systems of individual machines. Files are stored on different machines in the
        network but are accessible from all machines.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A collection of information stored and retrieved as a unit.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">File Server Machine</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A type of machine that stores files and transfers them to client machines on request.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Part of a command that determines how the command executes, or the type of output it produces.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Foreign Cell</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A cell other than the cell to which the client machine belongs. If the client machine is appropriately configured,
        users can access the AFS filespace in foreign cells as well as the local cell, and can authenticate in foreign cells in
        which they have AFS accounts.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A defined list of users, which can be placed on a directory's ACL to extend a set of permissions to all of its members
        at once.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Group-owned Group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A group owned by another group. All members of the owning group can administer the owned group; the members of the
        owned group do not have administer permissions themselves.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>H</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Hierarchical File Structure</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A method of storing data in directories that are organized in a tree structure.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Home Directory</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A directory owned by a user and dedicated to storage of the user's personal files.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>I</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">i (insert) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that enables the possessor to add files or subdirectories to a directory.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Instance</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The part of a command string that defines the entity to affect.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>K</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">k (lock) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See the k (lock) Permission entry. The ACL permission that enables programs to place advisory locks on a file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Kilobyte</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A unit of measure used to measure usage of space in a volume or on a partition. A kilobyte is equal to 1024 bytes. The
        term <emphasis>kilobyte block</emphasis> is sometimes used when referring to disk space.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>L</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">l (lookup) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that enables the possessor to list the contents of a directory and display its ACL.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Local Cell</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The cell to which the user's account and client machine belong.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">lock Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See the <emphasis role="bold">k (lock) Permission</emphasis> entry.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Login</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The process of establishing a connection to a client machine's local file system as a specific user.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Logout</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The process of ending a connection to the local file system.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>M</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">m Privacy Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The third privacy flag on a group, which enables the possessor to list the members of a group or the groups to which a
        user belongs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Mode Bits</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of permissions that the UNIX file system associates with a file or directory to control access to it. They
        appear in the first field of the output from the <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Mount Point</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A special type of directory that associates a location in the AFS file space with a volume. It acts like a standard
        UNIX directory in that users can change directory to it and list its contents with the UNIX <emphasis
        role="bold">cd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis> commands.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Mutual Authentication</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A procedure through which two parties prove their identities to one another. AFS server and client processes normally
        mutually authenticate as they establish a connection.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>N</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">NFS/AFS Translator</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A program that enables users on NFS client machines to access files in the AFS filespace.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">none ACL Shorthand</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A shorthand notation used with the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to delete an entry from an
        ACL.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>O</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">o Privacy Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The second privacy flag on a group, which enables the possessor to list groups owned by the user or group.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Operation Code</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The second word in an AFS command that belongs to a suite. It indicates the command's function.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Owner of a Group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The person or group who can administer a group.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>P</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Parent Directory</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The directory in which a directory or file resides.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Partition</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A logical section of a disk in a computer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Password</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A unique, user-defined string of characters validating the user's system identity. The user must correctly enter the
        password in order to be authenticated.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A certain type of access granted on an ACL. Anyone who possesses the permission can perform the action.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>Q</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Quota</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The size limit of a volume, assigned by the system administrator and measured in kilobyte blocks.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>R</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">r (read) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that enables the possessor to examine the contents of a file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">r Privacy Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The fifth privacy flag on a group, which enables the possessor to remove members from it.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">read ACL Shorthand</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A shorthand notation used with the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to represent the <emphasis
        role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Relative Pathname</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A pathname that does not begin at the root of the AFS or local filespace and so represents a file or directory's
        location with respect to the current working directory.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Remote Commands</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Commands used to run programs on a remote machine without establishing a persistent connection to it.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>S</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">s Privacy Flag</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The first privacy flag on a group, which enables the possessor to list general information about it.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Self-owned Group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A group that owns itself, enabling all of its members to administer it.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A program or machine that provides a specialized service to its clients, such as storing and transferring files or
        performing authentication.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Subdirectory</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A directory that resides in another directory in the file system hierarchy.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Switch</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The part of a command string defining the type of an argument. It is preceded by a hyphen.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Syntax Statement</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A specification of the options available on a command and their ordering.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">System Administrator</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A user who is authorized to administer an AFS cell.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">System Groups</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Groups that AFS defines automatically to represent users who share certain characteristics. See the following three
        entries.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">System:administrators group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A system group that includes users authorized to administer AFS.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">System:anyuser group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A system group that includes everyone who can gain access the cell's AFS filespace. It includes unauthenticated users,
        who are assigned the identity <emphasis role="bold">anonymous</emphasis>.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">System:authuser group</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A system group that includes all users who currently have valid AFS tokens for the local cell.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>T</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Token</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A collection of data that the AFS server processes accept as evidence that the possessor has successfully proved his
        or her identity to the cell's AFS authentication service. AFS assigns the identity <emphasis
        role="bold">anonymous</emphasis> to users who do not have a token.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>U</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">UNIX Mode Bits</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See the <emphasis role="bold">Mode Bits</emphasis> entry.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Username</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A character string entered at login that uniquely identifies a person in the local cell.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>V</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">Volume</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A structure that AFS uses to group a set of files and directories into a single unit for administrative purposes. The
        contents of a volume reside on a single disk partition and must be mounted in the AFS filespace to be accessible.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>W</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">w (write) Permission</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The ACL permission that enables the possessor to modify the contents of a file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm><emphasis role="bold">write ACL Shorthand</emphasis></glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A shorthand notation used with the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to represent all permissions
        except the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> permission.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>
