<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="HDRWQ1">
  <title>About This Guide</title>

  <para>This section describes the purpose, organization, and conventions of this document.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRPREFAUDPUR">
    <title>Audience and Purpose</title>

    <para>This guide describes concepts and procedures for accessing information stored in the AFS filespace. It is intended for AFS
    users who are familiar with UNIX but not necessarily AFS.</para>

    <para>The first chapter describes basic AFS concepts and guidelines for using it, and summarizes some of the differences between
    the UNIX file system and AFS. The remaining chapters explain how to perform basic AFS functions, including logging in, changing
    a password, listing information, protecting files, creating groups, and troubleshooting. Concepts important to a specific task
    or group of related tasks are presented in context, just prior to the procedures. Many examples are provided.</para>

    <para>Instructions generally include only the commands and command options necessary for a specific task. For a complete list of
    AFS commands and description of all options available on every command, see the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
    Reference</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRPREFORGAN">
    <title>Document Organization</title>

    <para>This document is divided into the following chapters.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ2">An Introduction to AFS</link> introduces the basic concepts and functions of AFS. To use AFS
    successfully, it is important to be familiar with the terms and concepts described in this chapter.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ20">Using AFS</link> describes how to use AFS's basic features: how to log in and authenticate, unlog,
    log out, access AFS files and directories in AFS, and change your password.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ38">Displaying Information about AFS</link> describes how to display information about AFS volume
    quota and location, file server machine status, and the foreign cells you can access.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ44">Protecting Your Directories and Files</link> describes how to protect your data using AFS access
    control lists (ACLs).</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ60">Using Groups</link> describes how to create and manage groups.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ76">Troubleshooting</link> outlines step-by-step diagnostic and corrective steps for specific
    problems.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ80">Appendix A, Using the NFS/AFS Translator</link> describes how to use the NFS/AFS Translator to
    access the AFS filespace from an NFS client machine.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ86">Appendix B, AFS Command Syntax and Online Help</link> describes AFS command syntax and how to
    obtain online information about commands.</para>

    <para><link linkend="HDRWQ90">Appendix C, Glossary</link> defines terms used in the <emphasis>IBM AFS User
    Guide</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRUSERFRONTHOWTO">
    <title>How To Use This Document</title>

    <para>Before you begin using AFS, read <link linkend="HDRWQ2">An Introduction to AFS</link>. Next, follow the procedures
    outlined in <link linkend="HDRWQ20">Using AFS</link> to get started using AFS as an authenticated user. It describes how to
    access files in the AFS filespace and how to end an AFS session. Consult the other chapters as you need to perform the tasks
    they describe.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRPREFRELATE">
    <title>Related Documents</title>

    <para>The AFS Documentation Kit also includes the following documents:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Reference</emphasis> details the syntax of each AFS command and is intended for
        the experienced AFS administrator, programmer, or user. For each AFS command, the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
        Reference</emphasis> lists the command syntax, aliases and abbreviations, description, arguments, warnings, output,
        examples, and related topics. Commands are organized alphabetically.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis> describes concepts and procedures necessary for administering an
        AFS cell, as well as more extensive coverage of the topics in the <emphasis>IBM AFS User Guide</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis> provides instructions for installing AFS server and client
        machines.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRTYPO_CONV">
    <title>Typographical Conventions</title>

    <para>This document uses the following typographical conventions:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Command and option names appear in <emphasis role="bold">bold type</emphasis> in syntax definitions, examples, and
        running text. Names of directories, files, machines, partitions, volumes, and users also appear in <emphasis
        role="bold">bold type</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Variable information appears in <emphasis>italic type</emphasis>. This includes user-supplied information on command
        lines and the parts of prompts that differ depending on who issues the command. New terms also appear in <emphasis>italic
        type</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Examples of screen output and file contents appear in <computeroutput>monospace type</computeroutput>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

    <para>In addition, the following symbols appear in command syntax definitions, both in the documentation and in AFS online help
    statements. When issuing a command, do not type these symbols.

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Square brackets <emphasis role="bold">[ ]</emphasis> surround optional items.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Angle brackets <emphasis role="bold">&lt; &gt;</emphasis> surround user-supplied values in AFS commands.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A superscripted plus sign <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> follows an argument that accepts more than one
        value.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The percent sign <computeroutput>%</computeroutput> represents the regular command shell prompt. Some operating
        systems possibly use a different character for this prompt.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The number sign <computeroutput>#</computeroutput> represents the command shell prompt for the local superuser
        <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>. Some operating systems possibly use a different character for this prompt.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The pipe symbol <emphasis role="bold">|</emphasis> in a command syntax statement separates mutually exclusive values
        for an argument.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

    <para>For additional information on AFS commands, including a description of command string components, acceptable abbreviations
    and aliases, and how to get online help for commands, see <link linkend="HDRWQ86">Appendix B, AFS Command Syntax and Online
    Help</link>.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>
