<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ38">
  <title>Displaying Information about AFS</title>

  <para>This chapter explains how to display information that can help you use AFS more effectively. It includes the following
  sections.

  <simplelist>
    <member><link linkend="HDRWQ39">Displaying Volume Quota</link></member>

    <member><link linkend="HDRWQ40">Locating Files and Directories</link>.</member>

    <member><link linkend="HDRWQ41">Checking the Status of Server Machines</link></member>

    <member><link linkend="HDRWQ42">Determining Access to Foreign Cells</link></member>

    <member><link linkend="HDRWQ43">Displaying Server Preference Ranks</link></member>
  </simplelist>
</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ39">
    <title>Displaying Volume Quota</title>

    <para>By convention, the files in your home directory are stored together in a single volume. (For information about volumes,
    see <link linkend="HDRWQ6">Volumes and Mount Points</link>.) To allocate your cell's available disk space as fairly as possible,
    your system administrators impose a size limit, or <emphasis>quota</emphasis>, on each volume. You cannot store more data in a
    volume than its quota allows. If a volume is close to its quota, you sometimes cannot save changes you have made to files stored
    in the volume.</para>

    <para>The amount of space available on the partition that houses the volume also limits how large the volume can grow. If the
    disk partition is full, you can become unable to save changes to a file even though the volume is not close to its quota.
    <indexterm><primary>volume quota</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>disk partition</primary><secondary>consequences when full</secondary></indexterm></para>

    <para>Check the quota on your home volume periodically to make sure you have adequate space. Also, if you encounter problems
    saving a file, check the quota of the volume in which the file is stored. Use the following commands to display volume
    quota.

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs quota</emphasis> command lists the percentage of the volume quota used.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Both the <emphasis role="bold">fs listquota</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> commands list
        the volume name, its maximum size (quota), and its current size. They also report the following additional
        information.

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs listquota</emphasis> command lists the percentage used of both the volume and the
            partition.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> command lists the partition's size, the amount of space currently
            used, and any messages associated with the volume.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_63">
      <title>To Display Percentage of Quota Used</title>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>quota</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>volume quota</primary><secondary>displaying percentage used</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs quota</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>percentage of volume quota used</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs quota</emphasis> command to display the percentage of the quota currently used for
      the volume that contains a specified directory or file.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs quota</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> specifies the pathname of a file or directory in each volume for which to
      display quota information. If you do not provide a pathname, the output reports quota information for the volume that contains
      the current working directory.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_64">
      <title>Example: Displaying Percentage of Quota Used</title>

      <para><indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>displaying volume quota percentage used</secondary></indexterm> The following example displays the percentage of quota used for the volumes that contain two user
      home directories in the ABC Corporation cell.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">cd /afs/abc.com/usr</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs quota terry pat</emphasis>
   34% of quota used.
   85% of quota used.
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_65">
      <title>To Display Quota and Other Information about a Volume</title>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>listquota</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>volume quota</primary><secondary>displaying with other information</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs listquota</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>volume quota with other information</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>disk partition percentage space used</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>disk partition</primary><secondary>displaying percentage of space used</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listquota</emphasis> command to display the following information:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the volume that houses each specified file or directory</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The quota, expressed as a number of kilobytes (<computeroutput>1024</computeroutput> indicates one megabyte)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The current size of the volume (the number of kilobytes of currently used)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The percentage of the quota used</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The percentage of space used on the disk partition housing the volume</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>

      <para>The command's syntax is as follows.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listquota</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> specifies the pathname of a file or directory in each volume for which to
      display quota information. If you do not provide a pathname, the output reports quota information for the volume that contains
      the current working directory.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_66">
      <title>Example: Display Quota and Other Information about a Volume</title>

      <indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>displaying volume quota and other information</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>The following example displays quota information about the volume that houses the home directory of user <emphasis
      role="bold">terry</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listquota ~terry</emphasis>
   Volume Name     Quota    Used    % Used   Partition 
   user.terry      10000    3400       34%         86% 
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_67">
      <title>To Display Quota and Other Information about a Volume and Partition</title>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>examine</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs examine</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>volume quota</primary><secondary>displaying with other information</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>volume quota with other information</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>disk partition space available and total size</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>disk partition</primary><secondary>displaying space available and total size</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> command to display the following information about a volume and
      the partition it resides on:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The volume's ID number (abbreviated in the output as <computeroutput>vid</computeroutput>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The volume name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The volume's quota and current size, in kilobytes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The number of kilobyte blocks available on the disk partition housing the volume and the total size of that
          partition</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An <emphasis>off-line message</emphasis> associated with the volume, if any, as set by a system administrator</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>

      <para>The command's syntax is as follows.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> specifies the pathname of a file or directory in each volume for which to
      display quota information. If you do not provide a pathname, the output reports quota information for the volume that contains
      the current working directory.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_68">
      <title>Example: Displaying Quota and Other Information about a Volume and Partition</title>

      <indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>displaying volume information</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>The following example displays quota and other information about the volume that houses the current working
      directory.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis>
   Volume status for vid = 536871122 named user.terry
   Current disk quota is 10000
   Current blocks used are 5745
   The partition has 1593 blocks available out of 99162
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ40">
    <title>Locating Files and Directories</title>

    <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>displaying location</secondary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>directories</primary><secondary>displaying location</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>Normally, you do not need to know which file server machine stores the volume containing a file or directory. Given the
    pathname to a file, the Cache Manager on your client machine automatically accesses the appropriate server machine.</para>

    <para>If you become unable to access a file, however, it can be useful to know which file server machine houses it. You can then
    check whether the File Server process or machine is functioning correctly, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ41">Checking the
    Status of Server Machines</link>. Or, if your system administrators schedule downtime for a machine, you can learn whether the
    outage is likely to prevent you from accessing certain files.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_70">
      <title>To Display a File or Directory's Location</title>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>whereis</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs whereis</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>directory/file location</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>displaying</primary><secondary>file or directory location</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs whereis</emphasis> command to display the file server machine on which a file or
      directory is stored.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs whereis</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;<superscript>+</superscript>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where <replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable> specifies the pathname of each file or directory for which you want
      location information. If you do not provide a pathname, the output reports the machine housing the volume that contains the
      current working directory.</para>

      <para>If the output mentions more than one machine, there is a copy of the volume at each site (the volume is
      <emphasis>replicated</emphasis>). Your system administrators can choose to replicate volumes that contain information many
      people need to use, both for load balancing reasons and to make the information available even if there is an outage on one
      machine that houses the volume.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_71">
      <title>Example: Displaying Directory Location</title>

      <indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>locating multiple files</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>The following example displays the names of the server machines that house the home volumes for users <emphasis
      role="bold">terry</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">cd /afs/abc.com/usr</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs whereis terry pat</emphasis>
   File /afs/abc.com/usr/terry is on host fs2.abc.com
   File /afs/abc.com/usr/pat is on host fs3.abc.com
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ41">
    <title>Checking the Status of Server Machines</title>

    <indexterm><primary>file server machines</primary><secondary>checking status</secondary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>status of file server machines</primary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>saving files</primary><secondary>on inaccessible file server machines</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>Sometimes one or more server machines in your cell become inaccessible due to hardware problems, software problems, or
    routine maintenance. During the outage, you cannot access files stored on those machines or save any changes you have made to
    files that are stored on those machines. (Your Cache Manager possibly has copies of the files stored locally, which you can
    still work with.)</para>

    <para>To check the status of server machines, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs checkservers</emphasis> command. If a server
    machine has more than one network interface address (is <emphasis>multihomed</emphasis>), the Cache Manager sends the
    status-checking message to all of the machine's interfaces. If at least one of the server's interfaces replies, the command's
    output reports the machine as accessible. If there is no reply from any of the interfaces, the output reports the machine as
    inaccessible but displays only one of the interfaces (usually the one with the best preference rank; see <link
    linkend="HDRWQ43">Displaying Server Preference Ranks</link>).</para>

    <para>To check the status of different groups of server machines, combine the <emphasis role="bold">fs checkservers</emphasis>
    command's options as indicated:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To check file server machines in the local cell only, do not include any options</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To check file server machines in a particular foreign cell only, include the <emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis>
        argument</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To check every file server machine that your Cache Manager has contacted in any cell, include the <emphasis
        role="bold">-all</emphasis> flag</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

    <para>It can take several minutes for the command shell prompt to return, because the <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis>
    command interpreter waits a timeout period before concluding that an unresponsive machine is really inaccessible. To have the
    command shell prompt return immediately, add the ampersand (<emphasis role="bold">&amp;</emphasis>), which runs the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs checkservers</emphasis> command in the background.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_73">
      <title>To Check File Server Machine Status</title>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>checkservers</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs checkservers</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs checkservers</emphasis> command to check the status of file server machines.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs checkservers</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>cell to check</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis
          role="bold">-all</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">&amp;</emphasis>]
</programlisting>

      <para>where

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Names each cell for which to check server machine status. Do not combine this argument and the <emphasis
            role="bold">-all</emphasis> flag.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">-all</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Checks the status of all server machines. Do not combine this flag and the <emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis>
            argument.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
</para>

      <para>The following message indicates that all server machines replied to the Cache Manager's status-checking message:</para>

      <programlisting>
   All servers are running.
</programlisting>

      <para>Otherwise, a message like the following lists the inaccessible machines:</para>

      <programlisting>
   These servers unavailable due to network or server problems: <replaceable>list of machines</replaceable>.
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_74">
      <title>Example: Checking Server Machine Status</title>

      <indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>checking status of file servers</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>The following example checks the status of every file server machine the Cache Manager has contacted in any cell. Two
      machines are not responding.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs checkservers -all &amp;</emphasis>
   These servers unavailable due to network or server problems: 
      fs1.abc.com server7.stateu.edu.
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ42">
    <title>Determining Access to Foreign Cells</title>

    <indexterm><primary>foreign cells</primary><secondary>enabling access</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>The Cache Manager maintains a list of foreign cells that it knows how to reach. A cell must appear in the list for you to
    access its AFS filespace. (In addition, the ACL on each directory in the pathname to the file must grant you the necessary
    permissions, and your system administrator must mount the cell in the local AFS filespace--by convention, just under the
    <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis> directory.)</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_76">
      <title>To Display Foreign Cells</title>

      <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs listcells</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>listcells</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listcells</emphasis> command to display the cells you can access from this client
      machine. It can take several minutes for the command shell prompt to return. The Cache Manager stores the machines as IP
      addresses, but has the addresses translated to names before displaying them. To have the command shell prompt return
      immediately, use the ampersand (<emphasis role="bold">&amp;</emphasis>) to run the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      listcells</emphasis> command in the background as in the following example.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listcells &amp;</emphasis>
   Cell abc.com  on hosts 
        db1.abc.com
        db2.abc.com
        db3.abc.com
   Cell test.abc.com on hosts 
        test4.abc.com.
   Cell stateu.edu on hosts 
        sv5.stateu.edu.
        sv2.stateu.edu.
        sv11.stateu.edu.
   Cell def.com on hosts 
        serverA.def.com 
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ43">
    <title>Displaying Server Preference Ranks</title>

    <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>fs getserverprefs</secondary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>fs commands</primary><secondary>getserverprefs</secondary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>Cache Manager</primary><secondary>displaying file server preferences</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>The Cache Manager stores a list of preference ranks for file server machines. When it needs to access a file or directory,
    the Cache Manager compares the ranks of the file server machines that house the relevant volume. It first tries to access the
    volume on the machine with the best rank. (If a file server machine is multihomed--has more than one network interface--the
    Cache Manager actually assigns a separate rank to each interface.)</para>

    <para>The Cache Manager assigns a default rank to a file server machine interface by comparing its own IP address to the
    interface's IP address. It assigns a better rank to interfaces that are on its own subnetwork or network than to interfaces on
    other networks. Therefore, the ranks bias the Cache Manager to fetch files from file server machines that are close in terms of
    network distance, which tends to reduce network traffic and help the Cache Manager deliver data to applications more
    quickly.</para>

    <para>The Cache Manager stores each rank as a pairing of a file server machine interface's IP address and an integer rank from
    the range <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> to <emphasis role="bold">65,534</emphasis>. A lower number is a better rank. To
    display the server preference ranks on the local client machine, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs getserverprefs</emphasis>
    command.</para>

    <para>The Cache Manager stores a separate but similar set of ranks for Volume Location (VL) Servers, which tell the Cache
    Manager the location of volumes that house files and directories. To display those ranks, add the <emphasis
    role="bold">-vlservers</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis role="bold">fs getserverprefs</emphasis> command.</para>

    <para>If the default ranks do not seem to result in the best performance, your system administrator can change them. Ask your
    system administrator about the ranks if appropriate.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_78">
      <title>To Display Server Preference Ranks</title>

      <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs getserverprefs</emphasis> command to display the file server machine preference ranks
      used by the Cache Manager on the local machine. To display VL Server ranks, add the <emphasis
      role="bold">-vlservers</emphasis> flag. By default, the Cache Manager has the IP address of each interface translated into a
      hostname before displaying it. To bypass the translation and display IP addresses, include the <emphasis
      role="bold">-numeric</emphasis> flag. This can significantly speed up the command's output.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs getserverprefs</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-numeric</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-vlservers</emphasis>]
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example displays the file server machine preference ranks for a client machine in the <emphasis
      role="bold">abc.com</emphasis> cell. The ranks of the file server machines in that cell are lower than the ranks of the file
      server machines from the foreign cell, <emphasis role="bold">def.com</emphasis>. Because the <emphasis
      role="bold">-numeric</emphasis> flag is not used, the output displays hostnames. The appearance of an IP address for two
      machines indicates that translating them was not possible.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs getserverprefs</emphasis>
   fs2.abc.com           20007
   fs3.abc.com           30002
   fs1.abc.com           20011
   fs4.abc.com           30010
   server1.def.com       40002
   192.12.105.34         40000
   server6.def.com       40012
   192.12.105.37         40005
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
