<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ2">
  <title>An Introduction to AFS</title>

  <para>This chapter introduces basic AFS concepts and terms. It assumes that you are already familiar with standard UNIX commands,
  file protection, and pathname conventions.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ3">
    <title>AFS Concepts</title>

    <para>AFS makes it easy for people to work together on the same files, no matter where the files are located. AFS users do not
    have to know which machine is storing a file, and administrators can move files from machine to machine without interrupting
    user access. Users always identify a file by the same pathname and AFS finds the correct file automatically, just as happens in
    the local file system on a single machine. While AFS makes file sharing easy, it does not compromise the security of the shared
    files. It provides a sophisticated protection scheme. <indexterm><primary>AFS</primary><secondary>sharing information</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>AFS</primary><secondary>transparent access</secondary></indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_9">
      <title>Client/Server Computing</title>

      <para>AFS uses a <emphasis>client/server computing</emphasis> model. In client/server computing, there are two types of
      machines. <emphasis>Server machines</emphasis> store data and perform services for client machines. <emphasis>Client
      machines</emphasis> perform computations for users and access data and services provided by server machines. Some machines act
      as both clients and servers. In most cases, you work on a client machine, accessing files stored on a file server machine.
      <indexterm><primary>client/server computing</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>client machine</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>server machines defined</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>machines</primary><secondary>server</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>machines</primary><secondary>client</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>communication</primary><secondary>between clients and servers</secondary></indexterm></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_10">
      <title>Distributed File Systems</title>

      <para>AFS is a <emphasis>distributed file system</emphasis> which joins together the file systems of multiple file server
      machines, making it as easy to access files stored on a remote file server machine as files stored on the local disk. A
      distributed file system has two main advantages over a conventional centralized file system: <indexterm><primary>distributed file system</primary></indexterm>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Increased availability: A copy of a popular file, such as the binary for an application program, can be stored on
          many file server machines. An outage on a single machine or even multiple machines does not necessarily make the file
          unavailable. Instead, user requests for the program are routed to accessible machines. With a centralized file system, the
          loss of the central file storage machine effectively shuts down the entire system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Increased efficiency: In a distributed file system, the work load is distributed over many smaller file server
          machines that tend to be more fully utilized than the larger (and usually more expensive) file storage machine of a
          centralized file system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>

      <para>AFS hides its distributed nature, so working with AFS files looks and feels like working with files stored on your local
      machine, except that you can access many more files. And because AFS relies on the power of users' client machines for
      computation, increasing the number of AFS users does not slow AFS performance appreciably, making it a very efficient
      computing environment.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ4">
      <title>AFS Filespace and Local Filespace</title>

      <indexterm><primary>local machine</primary></indexterm>

      <para>AFS acts as an extension of your machine's local UNIX file system. Your system administrator creates a directory on the
      local disk of each AFS client machine to act as a gateway to AFS. By convention, this directory is called <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs</emphasis>, and it functions as the root of the <emphasis>AFS filespace</emphasis>. <indexterm><primary>AFS</primary><secondary>filespace as extension of local filespace</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>afs (/afs) directory</primary><secondary>as root of AFS filespace</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>root of AFS filespace</primary></indexterm></para>

      <para>Just like the UNIX file system, AFS uses a hierarchical file structure (a tree). Under the <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs</emphasis> root directory are subdirectories created by your system administrator, including your home
      directory. Other directories that are at the same level of the local file system as <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis>,
      such as <emphasis role="bold">/usr</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">/etc</emphasis>, or <emphasis
      role="bold">/bin</emphasis>, can either be located on your local disk or be links to AFS directories. Files relevant only to
      the local machine are usually stored on the local machine. All other files can be stored in AFS, enabling many users to share
      them and freeing the local machine's disk space for other uses.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You can use AFS commands only on files in the AFS filespace or the local directories that are links to the AFS
        filespace.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ5">
      <title>Cells and Sites</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>cell</emphasis> is the administrative domain in AFS. Each cell's administrators determine how client
      machines are configured and how much storage space is available to each user. The organization corresponding to a cell can be
      a company, a university department, or any defined group of users. From a hardware perspective, a cell is a grouping of client
      machines and server machines defined to belong to the same cell. <indexterm><primary>cells</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm> An AFS <emphasis>site</emphasis> is a
      grouping of one or more related cells. For example, the cells at the ABC Corporation form a single site. <indexterm><primary>site defined</primary></indexterm></para>

      <para>By convention, the subdirectories of the <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis> directory are cellular filespaces, each
      of which contains subdirectories and files that belong to a single cell. For example, directories and files relevant to the
      ABC Corporation cell are stored in the subdirectory <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>While each cell organizes and maintains its own filespace, it can also connect with the filespace of other AFS cells.
      The result is a huge filespace that enables file sharing within and across cells. <indexterm><primary>communication</primary><secondary>among cells and sites</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>The cell to which your client machine belongs is called your <emphasis>local cell</emphasis>. All other cells in the AFS
      filespace are termed <emphasis>foreign cells</emphasis>. <indexterm><primary>local cell, defined</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>foreign cells</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>cells</primary><secondary>local vs. foreign</secondary></indexterm></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ6">
      <title>Volumes and Mount Points</title>

      <para>The storage disks in a computer are divided into sections called <emphasis>partitions</emphasis>. AFS further divides
      partitions into units called <emphasis>volumes</emphasis>, each of which houses a subtree of related files and directories.
      The volume provides a convenient container for storing related files and directories. Your system administrators can move
      volumes from one file server machine to another without your noticing, because AFS automatically tracks a volume's location.
      <indexterm><primary>volumes</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>disk partition</primary><secondary>use in AFS</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>You access the contents of a volume by accessing its <emphasis>mount point</emphasis> in the AFS filespace. A mount
      point is a special file system element that looks and acts like a regular UNIX directory, but tells AFS the volume's name.
      When you change to a different directory (by using the <emphasis role="bold">cd</emphasis> command, for example) you sometimes
      <emphasis>cross</emphasis> a mount point and start accessing the contents of a different volume than before. You normally do
      not notice the crossing, however, because AFS automatically interprets mount points and retrieves the contents of the new
      directory from the appropriate volume. You do not need to track which volume, partition, or file server machine is housing a
      directory's contents. If you are interested, though, you can learn a volume's location; for instructions, see <link
      linkend="HDRWQ40">Locating Files and Directories</link>. <indexterm><primary>mount points defined</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>volumes</primary><secondary>accessing via mount points</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>If your system administrator has followed the conventional practice, your home directory corresponds to one volume,
      which keeps its contents together on one partition of a file server machine. User volumes are typically named <emphasis
      role="bold">user.</emphasis><replaceable>username</replaceable>. For example, the volume for a user named <emphasis
      role="bold">smith</emphasis> in the cell <emphasis role="bold">abc.com</emphasis> is called <emphasis
      role="bold">user.smith</emphasis> and is mounted at the directory <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr/smith</emphasis>.
      <indexterm><primary>examples</primary><secondary>volume/mount point interaction</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>Because AFS volumes are stored on different file server machines, when a machine becomes unavailable only the volumes on
      that machine are inaccessible. Volumes stored on other machines are still accessible. However, if a volume's mount point
      resides in a volume that is stored on an unavailable machine, the former volume is also inaccessible. For that reason, volumes
      containing frequently used directories (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs/</emphasis><replaceable>cellname</replaceable>) are often copied and distributed to many file server
      machines.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ7">
      <title>Volume Quotas</title>

      <indexterm><primary>volumes</primary><secondary>volume/mount point interaction</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Each volume has a size limit, or <emphasis>quota</emphasis>, assigned by the system administrator. A volume's quota
      determines the maximum amount of disk space the volume can consume. If you attempt to exceed a volume's quota, you receive an
      error message. For instructions on checking volume quota, see <link linkend="HDRWQ39">Displaying Volume Quota</link>.</para>

      <para>Volumes have completely independent quotas. For example, say that the current working directory is <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr/smith</emphasis>, which is the mount point for the <emphasis role="bold">user.smith</emphasis>
      volume with 1000 free blocks. You try to copy a 500 block file from the current working directory to the <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr/pat</emphasis> directory, the mount point for the volume <emphasis
      role="bold">user.pat</emphasis>. However, you get an error message saying there is not enough space. You check the volume
      quota for <emphasis role="bold">user.pat</emphasis>, and find that the volume only has 50 free blocks.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ8">
    <title>Using Files in AFS</title>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ9">
      <title>The Cache Manager</title>

      <para>You can access the AFS filespace only when working on an AFS client machine. The <emphasis>Cache Manager</emphasis> on
      that machine is your agent in accessing information stored in the AFS filespace. When you access a file, the Cache Manager on
      your client machine requests the file from the appropriate file server machine and stores (<emphasis>caches</emphasis>) a copy
      of it on your client machine's local disk. Application programs on your client machine use the local, cached copy of the file.
      This improves performance because it is much faster to use a local file than to send requests for file data across the network
      to the file server machine. <indexterm><primary>caching files</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>Cache Manager</primary><secondary>described</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>client machine</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>caching</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>Because application programs use the cached copy of a file, any changes you make are not necessarily stored permanently
      to the central version stored on the file server machine until the file closes. At that point, the Cache Manager writes your
      changes back to the file server machine, where they replace the corresponding parts of the existing file. Some application
      programs close a file in this way each time you issue their <emphasis role="bold">save</emphasis> command (and then
      immediately reopen the file so that you can continue working). With other programs, issuing the <emphasis
      role="bold">save</emphasis> command writes the changes only to the local cached copy. If you use the latter type of text
      editor, you need to close the file periodically to make sure your changes are stored permanently.</para>

      <para>If a file server machine becomes inaccessible, you can continue working with the local, cached copy of a file fetched
      from that machine, but you cannot save your changes permanently until the server machine is again accessible.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ10">
      <title>Updating Copies of Cached Files</title>

      <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>updating</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>callbacks</primary></indexterm>

      <para>When the central version of a file changes on the file server machine, the AFS <emphasis>File Server</emphasis> process
      running on that machine advises all other Cache Managers with copies of that file that their version is no longer valid. AFS
      has a special mechanism for performing these notifications efficiently. When the File Server sends the Cache Manager a copy of
      a modifiable file, it also sends a <emphasis>callback</emphasis>. A callback functions as a promise from the File Server to
      contact the Cache Manager if the centrally stored copy of the file is changed while it is being used. If that happens, the
      File Server <emphasis>breaks</emphasis> the callback. If you run a program that requests data from the changed file, the Cache
      Manager notices the broken callback and gets an updated copy of the file from the File Server. Callbacks ensure that you are
      working with the most recent copy of a file.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The callback mechanism does not guarantee that you immediately see the changes someone else makes to a file you are
        using. Your Cache Manager does not notice the broken callback until your application program asks it for more data from the
        file.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_18">
      <title>Multiple Users Modifying Files</title>

      <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>denying access</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>sharing</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Like a standard UNIX file system, AFS preserves only the changes to a file that are saved last, regardless of who made
      the changes. When collaborating with someone on the same files, you must coordinate your work to avoid overwriting each
      other's changes. You can use AFS access control lists (ACLs) to limit the ability of other users to access or change your
      files, and so prevent them from accidentally overwriting your files. See <link linkend="HDRWQ44">Protecting Your Directories
      and Files</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ11">
    <title>AFS Security</title>

    <indexterm><primary>AFS</primary><secondary>security</secondary></indexterm>

    <indexterm><primary>security in AFS</primary></indexterm>

    <para>AFS makes it easy for many users to access the same files, but also uses several mechanisms to ensure that only authorized
    users access the AFS filespace. The mechanisms include the following:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Passwords and mutual authentication ensure that only authorized users access AFS filespace</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Access control lists enable users to restrict or permit access to their own directories</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ12">
      <title>Passwords and Mutual Authentication</title>

      <indexterm><primary>mutual authentication</primary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>authentication</primary><secondary>mutual</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>password</primary></indexterm>

      <para>AFS uses two related mechanisms to ensure that only authorized users access the filespace: passwords and mutual
      authentication. Both mechanisms require that a user prove his or her identity.</para>

      <para>When you first identify yourself to AFS, you must provide the password associated with your username, to prove that you
      are who you say you are. When you provide the correct password, you become <emphasis>authenticated</emphasis> and your Cache
      Manager receives a <emphasis>token</emphasis>. A token is a package of information that is scrambled by an AFS authentication
      program using your AFS password as a key. Your Cache Manager can unscramble the token because it knows your password and AFS's
      method of scrambling. <indexterm><primary>tokens</primary><secondary>as proof of authentication</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>authentication</primary><secondary>defined</secondary></indexterm></para>

      <para>The token acts as proof to AFS server programs that you are authenticated as a valid AFS user. It serves as the basis
      for the second means through which AFS creates security, called <emphasis>mutual authentication</emphasis>. Under mutual
      authentication, both parties communicating across the network prove their identities to one another. AFS requires mutual
      authentication whenever a server and client (most often, a Cache Manager) communicate with each other.</para>

      <para>The mutual authentication protocol that AFS uses is designed to make it very difficult for people to authenticate
      fraudulently. When your Cache Manager contacts a File Server on your behalf, it sends the token you obtained when you
      authenticated. The token is encrypted with a key that only an AFS File Server can know. If the File Server can decrypt your
      token, it can communicate with your Cache Manager. In turn, the Cache Manager accepts the File Server as genuine because the
      File Server can decrypt and use the information in the token. <indexterm><primary>tokens</primary><secondary>use in mutual authentication</secondary></indexterm></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_21">
      <title>Access Control Lists</title>

      <indexterm><primary>ACL</primary><secondary>described</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>AFS uses <emphasis>access control lists</emphasis> (<emphasis>ACLs</emphasis>) to determine who can access the
      information in the AFS filespace. Each AFS directory has an ACL to specify what actions different users can perform on that
      directory and its files. An ACL can contain up to about 20 entries for users, groups, or both; each entry lists a user or
      group and the permissions it possesses.</para>

      <para>The owner of a directory and system administrators can always administer an ACL. Users automatically own their home
      directories and subdirectories. Other non-owner users can define a directory's ACL only if specifically granted that
      permission on the ACL. For more information on ACLs, see <link linkend="HDRWQ44">Protecting Your Directories and Files</link>
      .</para>

      <para>A group is composed of one or more users and client machines. If a user belongs to a group that appears on an ACL, the
      user gets all of the permissions granted to that group, just as if the user were listed directly on the ACL. Similarly, if a
      user is logged into a client machine that belongs to a group, the user has all of the permissions granted to that group. For
      instructions on defining and using groups, see <link linkend="HDRWQ60">Using Groups</link>.</para>

      <para>All users who can access your cell's filespace, authenticated or not, are automatically assigned to a group called
      <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis>. For a discussion of placing the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group on ACLs, see <link linkend="HDRWQ51">Extending Access to Users from Foreign
      Cells</link>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You can use the UNIX mode bits to control access on specific files within an AFS directory; however, the effect of
        these mode bits is different under AFS than in the standard UNIX file system. See <link linkend="HDRWQ16">File and Directory
        Protection</link>.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ13">
    <title>Differences Between UNIX and AFS</title>

    <para>AFS is designed to be similar to the UNIX file system. For instance, many of the basic UNIX file manipulation commands
    (<emphasis role="bold">cp</emphasis> for copy, <emphasis role="bold">rm</emphasis> for remove, and so on) are the same in AFS as
    they are as in UNIX. All of your application programs work as they did before. The following sections describe some of the
    differences between a standard UNIX file system and AFS.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ14">
      <title>File Sharing</title>

      <indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>file transfer</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>sharing files</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>files</primary><secondary>sharing</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>AFS enables users to share remote files as easily as local files. To access a file on a remote machine in AFS, you
      simply specify the file's pathname. In contrast, to access a file in a remote machine's UNIX file system, you must log into
      the remote machine or create a mount point on the local machine that points to a directory in the remote machine's UNIX file
      system.</para>

      <para>AFS users can see and share all the files under the <emphasis role="bold">/afs</emphasis> root directory, given the
      appropriate privileges. An AFS user who has the necessary privileges can access a file in any AFS cell, simply by specifying
      the file's pathname. File sharing in AFS is not restricted by geographical distances or operating system differences.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ15">
      <title>Login and Authentication</title>

      <indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>login</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>To become an authenticated AFS user, you need to provide a password to AFS.

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On machines that use an AFS-modified login utility, logging in is a one-step process; your initial login
          automatically authenticates you with AFS.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On machines that do not use an AFS-modified login utility, you must perform two steps.

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Log in to your local machine.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-setpag</emphasis>
              argument to authenticate with AFS and get your token.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>

      <para>Your system administrator can tell you whether your machine uses an AFS-modified login utility or not. Then see the
      login instructions in <link linkend="HDRWQ21">Logging in and Authenticating with AFS</link>.</para>

      <para>AFS authentication passwords are stored in special AFS database, rather than in the local password file (<emphasis
      role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> or equivalent). If your machine uses an AFS-modified login utility, you can change your
      password with a single command. If your machine does not use an AFS-modified login utility, you must issue separate commands
      to change your AFS and local passwords. See <link linkend="HDRWQ36">Changing Your Password</link>. <indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>passwords</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>local password file (/etc/passwd)</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>passwd</primary><secondary>file</secondary></indexterm></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ16">
      <title>File and Directory Protection</title>

      <indexterm><primary>ACL</primary><secondary>compared to UNIX mode bits</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>file access/protection</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>AFS does not rely on the mode bit protections of a standard UNIX system (though its protection system does interact with
      these mode bits). Instead, AFS uses an access control list (ACL) to control access to each directory and its contents. The
      following list summarizes the differences between the two methods:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>UNIX mode bits specify three types of access permissions: <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis
          role="bold">read</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>), and <emphasis
          role="bold">x</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">execute</emphasis>). An AFS ACL uses seven types of permissions: <emphasis
          role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis
          role="bold">lookup</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>), <emphasis
          role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis
          role="bold">write</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lock</emphasis>), and <emphasis
          role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>). For more information, see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ46">The AFS ACL Permissions</link> and <link linkend="HDRWQ59">How AFS Uses the UNIX Mode
          Bits</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The three sets of mode bits on each UNIX file or directory enable you to grant permissions to three users or groups
          of users: the file or directory's owner, the group that owns the file or directory, and all other users. An ACL can
          accommodate up to about 20 entries, each of which extends certain permissions to a user or group. Unlike standard UNIX, a
          user can belong to an unlimited number of groups, and groups can be defined by both users and system administrators. See
          <link linkend="HDRWQ60">Using Groups</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>UNIX mode bits are set individually on each file and directory. An ACL applies to all of the files in a directory.
          While at first glance the AFS method possibly seems less precise, in actuality (given a proper directory structure) there
          are no major disadvantages to directory-level protections and they are easier to establish and maintain.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ17">
      <title>Machine Outages</title>

      <para>The kinds of failures you experience when a standard UNIX file system goes down are different than when one or more
      individual AFS file server machines become unavailable. When a standard UNIX file system is inaccessible, the system simply
      locks up and you can lose changes to any files with which you were working.</para>

      <para>When an AFS file server machine becomes inaccessible, you cannot access the files on that machine. If a copy of the file
      is available from another file server machine, however, you do not necessarily even notice the server outage. This is because
      AFS gives your cell's system administrators the ability to store copies of popular programs on multiple file servers. The
      Cache Manager chooses between the copies automatically; when one copy becomes unavailable, the Cache Manager simply chooses
      another.</para>

      <para>If there are no other copies of a file that is stored on an inaccessible server machine, you can usually continue to use
      the copy stored in your client machine's local AFS cache. However, you cannot save changes to files stored on an inaccessible
      file server machine until it is accessible again.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ18">
      <title>Remote Commands</title>

      <para><indexterm><primary>UNIX, differences with AFS</primary><secondary>commands</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>remote commands</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>ftp</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>ftp command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>rcp</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>rcp command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>rsh</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>rsh command</primary></indexterm> The UNIX <emphasis>remote commands</emphasis> enable you
      to run programs on a remote machine without establishing a connection to it by using a program such as <emphasis
      role="bold">telnet</emphasis>. Many of the remote commands (such as <emphasis role="bold">ftp</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">rcp</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">rsh</emphasis>) remain available in AFS, depending on how your
      administrators have configured them. If the remote machine has a Cache Manager, your token is used there also and you are
      authenticated while the remote command runs. If the remote machine does not run a Cache Manager, you receive the following
      message:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Warning: unable to authenticate.
</programlisting>

      <para>In this case, you are logged into the remote machine's UNIX file system, but you are not authenticated to AFS. You can
      access the local files on the remote machine and the AFS directories that grant access to the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group, but you cannot access protected AFS directories.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_28">
      <title>Differences in the Semantics of Standard UNIX Commands</title>

      <para>This section summarizes differences in the functionality of some commonly issued UNIX commands.

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">chmod <indexterm><primary>chmod command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>chmod</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Only members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group can use this command to turn on
            the setuid, setgid or sticky mode bits on AFS files. (For more information about this group, see <link
            linkend="HDRWQ50">Using the System Groups on ACLs</link>.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">chown <indexterm><primary>chown command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>chown</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Only members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group can issue this command on AFS
            files.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">chgrp <indexterm><primary>chgrp command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>chgrp</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Only members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group can issue this command on AFS
            files and directories.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">groups <indexterm><primary>groups command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>groups</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the user's AFS tokens are identified by a process authentication group (PAG), the output of this command
            includes two large numbers. For a description of PAGs, see <link linkend="HDRWQ24">Authenticating with
            AFS</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">inetd <indexterm><primary>inetd command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>inetd</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The AFS version of this daemon authenticates remote issuers of the AFS-modified <emphasis
            role="bold">rcp</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">rsh</emphasis> commands with AFS.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">login utilities <indexterm><primary>login utility</primary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>AFS-modified login utilities both log you into the local UNIX file system and authenticate you with AFS.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">ln <indexterm><primary>ln command</primary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>commands</primary><secondary>ln</secondary></indexterm> </emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>You cannot use this command to create a hard link between files that reside in different AFS directories. You must
            add the <emphasis role="bold">-s</emphasis> option to create a symbolic link instead.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ19">
    <title>Using AFS with NFS</title>

    <para>Some cells use the Networking File System (NFS) in addition to AFS. If you work on an NFS client machine, your system
    administrator can configure it to access the AFS filespace through a program called the <emphasis>NFS/AFS
    Translator</emphasis><superscript>TM</superscript>. See <link linkend="HDRWQ80">Appendix A, Using the NFS/AFS
    Translator</link>.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
