<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="afs1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>afs</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>afs</refname>
    <refpurpose>Introduction to AFS commands</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>AFS provides many commands that enable users and system administrators to
    use and customize its features. Many of the commands belong to the
    following categories, called <emphasis>command suites</emphasis>.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>backup</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface for configuring and operating the AFS Backup System.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>bos</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface to the Basic Overseer (BOS) Server for administering server
          processes and configuration files.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>fs</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface for administering access control lists (ACLs), the Cache
          Manager, and other miscellaneous file system functions.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>fstrace</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface for tracing Cache Manager operations when debugging problems.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>kas</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface to the Authentication Server for administering security and
          authentication information.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>pts</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface to the Protection Server for administering AFS ID and group
          membership information.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>uss</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface for automated administration of user accounts.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>vos</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Interface to the Volume Server and Volume Location (VL) Server for
          administering volumes.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>In addition, there are several commands that do not belong to
    suites.</para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>AFS Command Syntax</title>
      <para>AFS commands that belong to suites have the following structure:</para>

      <para><emphasis>command_suite</emphasis> <emphasis>operation_code</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-switch</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>value</emphasis>&gt;[+] [<emphasis role="bold">-flag</emphasis>]</para>

      <refsect3>
        <title>Command Names</title>
        <para>Together, the <emphasis>command_suite</emphasis> and <emphasis>operation_code</emphasis> make up the <emphasis>command
        name</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>The <emphasis>command_suite</emphasis> specifies the group of related commands to which the
        command belongs, and indicates which command interpreter and server
        process perform the command.  AFS has several command suites, including
        <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">pts</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">vos</emphasis>.  Some of
        these suites have an interactive mode in which the issuer omits the
        <emphasis>operation_code</emphasis> portion of the command name.</para>

        <para>The <emphasis>operation_code</emphasis> tells the command interpreter and server process
        which action to perform. Most command suites include several operation
        codes. The man pages for each command name describe each operation code in
        detail, and the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis> describes how to use them
        in the context of performing administrative tasks.</para>

        <para>Several AFS commands do not belong to a suite and so their names do not
        have a <emphasis>command_suite</emphasis> portion. Their structure is otherwise similar to
        the commands in the suites.</para>

      </refsect3>
      <refsect3>
        <title>Options</title>
        <para>The term <emphasis>option</emphasis> refers to both arguments and flags, which are described
        in the following sections.</para>

      </refsect3>
      <refsect3>
        <title>Arguments</title>
        <para>One or more arguments can follow the command name. Arguments specify the
        entities on which to act while performing the command (for example, which
        server machine, server process, or file). To minimize the potential for
        error, provide a command's arguments in the order prescribed in its syntax
        definition.</para>

        <para>Each argument has two parts, which appear in the indicated order:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis>switch</emphasis> specifies the argument's type and is preceded by a hyphen
            (<emphasis role="bold">-</emphasis>). For instance, the switch <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> usually indicates that the
            argument names a server machine. Switches can often be omitted, subject to
            the rules outlined in Conditions for Omitting Switches.</para>

          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis>value</emphasis> names a particular entity of the type specified by the
            preceding switch. For example, the proper value for a <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> switch is
            a server machine name like <computeroutput>fs3.abc.com</computeroutput>. Unlike switches (which have a
            required form), values vary depending on what the issuer wants to
            accomplish. Values appear surrounded by angle brackets (<computeroutput>&lt;&gt;</computeroutput>) in
            command descriptions and the online help to show that they are
            user-supplied variable information.</para>

          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Some arguments accept multiple values, as indicated by trailing plus sign
        (<computeroutput>+</computeroutput>) in the command descriptions and online help. How many of a
        command's arguments take multiple values, and their ordering with respect
        to other arguments, determine when it is acceptable to omit switches. See
        Conditions for Omitting Switches.</para>

        <para>Some commands have optional as well as required arguments; the command
        descriptions and online help show optional arguments in square brackets
        (<computeroutput>[]</computeroutput>).</para>

      </refsect3>
      <refsect3>
        <title>Flags</title>
        <para>Some commands have one or more flags, which specify the manner in which
        the command interpreter and server process perform the command, or what
        kind of output it produces. Flags are preceded by hyphens like switches,
        but they take no values. Although the command descriptions and online help
        generally list a command's flags after its arguments, there is no
        prescribed order for flags. They can appear anywhere on the command line
        following the operation code, except in between the parts of an
        argument. Flags are always optional.</para>

      </refsect3>
      <refsect3>
        <title>An Example Command</title>
        <para>The following example illustrates the different parts of a command that
        belongs to an AFS command suite.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos getdate -server fs1.abc.com -file ptserver kaserver

</programlisting>
          <para>where</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis> is the command suite. The BOS Server executes most of the commands
              in this suite.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">getdate</emphasis> is the operation code. It tells the BOS Server on the specified
              server machine (in this case <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput>) to report the modification
              dates of binary files in the local <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><computeroutput>-server fs1.abc.com</computeroutput> is one argument, with <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> as the switch and
              <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput> as the value. This argument specifies the server machine on
              which BOS Server is to collect and report binary dates.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><computeroutput>-file ptserver kaserver</computeroutput> is an argument that takes multiple values. The
              switch is <emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis> and the values are <computeroutput>ptserver</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>kaserver</computeroutput>. This
              argument tells the BOS Server to report the modification dates on the
              files <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin/kaserver</replaceable> and <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin/ptserver</replaceable>.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </refsect3>
        <refsect3>
          <title>Rules for Entering AFS Commands</title>
          <para>Enter each AFS command on a single line (press &lt;Return&gt; only at the end of
          the command). Some commands in this document appear broken across multiple
          lines, but that is for legibility only.</para>

          <para>Use a space to separate each element on a command line from its
          neighbors. Spaces rather than commas also separate multiple values of an
          argument.</para>

          <para>In many cases, the issuer of a command can reduce the amount of typing
          necessary by using one or both of the following methods:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Omitting switches.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Using accepted abbreviations for operation codes, switches (if they are
              included at all), and some types of values.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The following sections explain the conditions for omitting or shortening
          parts of the command line. It is always acceptable to type a command in
          full, with all of its switches and no abbreviations.</para>

        </refsect3>
        <refsect3>
          <title>Conditions for Omitting Switches</title>
          <para>It is always acceptable to type the switch part of an argument, but in
          many cases it is not necessary. Specifically, switches can be omitted if
          the following conditions are met.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>All of the command's required arguments appear in the order prescribed by
              the syntax statement.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>No switch is provided for any argument.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>There is only one value for each argument (but note the important
              exception discussed in the following paragraph).</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Omitting switches is possible only because there is a prescribed order for
          each command's arguments. When the issuer does not include switches, the
          command interpreter relies instead on the order of arguments; it assumes
          that the first element after the operation code is the command's first
          argument, the next element is the command's second argument, and so
          on. The important exception is when a command's final required argument
          accepts multiple values. In this case, the command interpreter assumes
          that the issuer has correctly provided one value for each argument up
          through the final one, so any additional values at the end belong to the
          final argument.</para>

          <para>The following list describes the rules for omitting switches from the
          opposite perspective: an argument's switch must be provided when any of
          the following conditions apply.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The command's arguments do not appear in the prescribed order.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>An optional argument is omitted but a subsequent optional argument is
              provided.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A switch is provided for a preceding argument.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>More than one value is supplied for a preceding argument (which must take
              multiple values, of course); without a switch on the current argument, the
              command interpreter assumes that the current argument is another value for
              the preceding argument.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </refsect3>
        <refsect3>
          <title>An Example of Omitting Switches</title>
          <para>Consider again the example command from An Example Command.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos getdate -server fs1.abc.com -file ptserver kaserver

</programlisting>
            <para>This command has two required arguments: the server machine name
            (identified by the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> switch) and binary file name (identified by
            the <emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis> switch). The second argument accepts multiple values. By
            complying with all three conditions, the issuer can omit the switches:</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos getdate fs1.abc.com ptserver kaserver

</programlisting>
              <para>Because there are no switches, the bos command interpreter relies on the
              order of arguments. It assumes that the first element following the
              operation code, <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput>, is the server machine name, and that the
              next argument, <computeroutput>ptserver</computeroutput>, is a binary file name. Then, because the
              command's second (and last) argument accepts multiple values, the command
              interpreter correctly interprets <computeroutput>kaserver</computeroutput> as an additional value for
              it.</para>

              <para>On the other hand, the following is not acceptable because it violates the
              first two conditions in Conditions for Omitting Switches: even though
              there is only one value per argument, the arguments do not appear in the
              prescribed order, and a switch is provided for one argument but not the
              other.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos getdate ptserver -server fs1.abc.com

</programlisting>
              </refsect3>
              <refsect3>
                <title>Rules for Using Abbreviations and Aliases</title>
                <para>This section explains how to abbreviate operation codes, option names,
                server machine names, partition names, and cell names. It is not possible
                to abbreviate other types of values.</para>

              </refsect3>
              <refsect3>
                <title>Abbreviating Operation Codes</title>
                <para>It is acceptable to abbreviate an operation code to the shortest form that
                still distinguishes it from the other operation codes in its suite.</para>

                <para>For example, it is acceptable to shorten <emphasis role="bold">bos install</emphasis> to <emphasis role="bold">bos i</emphasis>
                because there are no other operation codes in the <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis> command suite
                that begin with the letter <computeroutput>i</computeroutput>. In contrast, there are several <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis>
                operation codes that start with the letter <computeroutput>s</computeroutput>, so the abbreviations must
                be longer to remain unambiguous:</para>

                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos sa</emphasis> for bos salvage</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos seta</emphasis> for bos setauth</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos setc</emphasis> for bos setcellname</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos setr</emphasis> for bos setrestart</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos sh</emphasis> for bos shutdown</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos start</emphasis> for bos start</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos startu</emphasis> for bos startup</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos stat</emphasis> for bos status</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">bos sto</emphasis> for bos stop</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para></para>

                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <para>In addition to abbreviations, some operation codes have an <emphasis>alias</emphasis>, a
                short form that is not derived by abbreviating the operation code to its
                shortest unambiguous form. For example, the alias for the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis>
                command is <emphasis role="bold">fs sa</emphasis>, whereas the shortest unambiguous abbreviation is <emphasis role="bold">fs
                seta</emphasis>.</para>

                <para>There are two usual reasons an operation code has an alias:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Because the command is frequently issued, it is convenient to have a form
                    shorter than the one derived by abbreviating. The <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command is
                    an example.</para>

                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Because the command's name has changed, but users of previous versions of
                    AFS know the former name. For example, <emphasis role="bold">bos listhosts</emphasis> has the alias
                    <emphasis role="bold">bos getcell</emphasis>, its former name.  It is acceptable to abbreviate aliases
                    to their shortest unambiguous form (for example, <emphasis role="bold">bos getcell</emphasis> to <emphasis role="bold">bos
                    getc</emphasis>).</para>

                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Even if an operation code has an alias, it is still acceptable to use the
                shortest unambiguous form. Thus, the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command has three
                acceptable forms: <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> (the full form), <emphasis role="bold">fs seta</emphasis> (the shortest
                abbreviation), and <emphasis role="bold">fs sa</emphasis> (the alias).</para>

              </refsect3>
              <refsect3>
                <title>Abbreviating Switches and Flags</title>
                <para>It is acceptable to shorten a switch or flag to the shortest form that
                distinguishes it from the other switches and flags for its operation
                code. It is often possible to omit switches entirely, subject to the
                conditions listed in Conditions for Omitting Switches.</para>

              </refsect3>
              <refsect3>
                <title>Abbreviating Server Machine Names</title>
                <para>AFS server machines must have fully-qualified Internet-style host names
                (for example, <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput>), but it is not always necessary to type the
                full name on the command line. AFS commands accept unambiguous shortened
                forms, but depend on the cell's name service (such as the Domain Name
                Service) or a local host table to resolve a shortened name to the
                fully-qualified equivalent when the command is issued.</para>

                <para>Most commands also accept the dotted decimal form of the machine's IP
                address as an identifier.</para>

              </refsect3>
              <refsect3>
                <title>Abbreviating Partition Names</title>
                <para>Partitions that house AFS volumes must have names of the form
                <replaceable>/vicep</replaceable><emphasis>x</emphasis><replaceable></replaceable> or <replaceable>/vicep</replaceable><emphasis>xx</emphasis><replaceable></replaceable>, where the variable final portion is one
                or two lowercase letters. By convention, the first server partition
                created on a file server machine is called <replaceable>/vicepa</replaceable>, the second
                <replaceable>/vicepb</replaceable>, and so on.  The <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis> explains how to
                configure and name a file server machine's partitions in preparation for
                storing AFS volumes on them.</para>

                <para>When issuing AFS commands, you can abbreviate a partition name using any
                of the following forms:</para>

<programlisting>
   /vicepa     =     vicepa      =      a      =      0
   /vicepb     =     vicepb      =      b      =      1

</programlisting>
                  <para>After /vicepz (for which the index is 25) comes</para>

<programlisting>
   /vicepaa    =     vicepaa     =      aa     =      26
   /vicepab    =     vicepab     =      ab     =      27

</programlisting>
                    <para>and so on through</para>

<programlisting>
   /vicepiv    =     vicepiv     =      iv     =      255

</programlisting>
                    </refsect3>
                    <refsect3>
                      <title>Abbreviating Cell Names</title>
                      <para>A cell's full name usually matches its Internet domain name (such as
                      <emphasis role="bold">stateu.edu</emphasis> for the State University or <computeroutput>abc.com</computeroutput> for ABC
                      Corporation). Some AFS commands accept unambiguous shortened forms,
                      usually with respect to the local <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc/CellServDB file</replaceable> but
                      sometimes depending on the ability of the local name service to resolve
                      the corresponding domain name.</para>

                    </refsect3>
                    <refsect3>
                      <title>Displaying Online Help for AFS Commands</title>
                      <para>To display online help for AFS commands that belong to suites, use the
                      <emphasis role="bold">help</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">apropos</emphasis> operation codes.  A <emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis> flag is also available
                      on every almost every AFS command.</para>

                      <para>The online help entry for a command consists of two or three lines:</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>The first line names the command and briefly describes what it does.</para>

                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>If the command has aliases, they appear on the next line.</para>

                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>The final line, which begins with the string <computeroutput>Usage:</computeroutput>, lists the
                          command's options in the prescribed order; online help entries use the
                          same typographical symbols (brackets and so on) as this documentation.</para>

                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                      <para>If no operation code is specified, the <emphasis role="bold">help</emphasis> operation code displays the
                      first line (short description) for every operation code in the suite:</para>

<programlisting>
   % &amp;lt;command_suite&amp;gt; help

</programlisting>
                        <para>If the issuer specifies one or more operation codes, the <emphasis role="bold">help</emphasis> operation
                        code displays each command's complete online entry (short description,
                        alias if any, and syntax):</para>

<programlisting>
   % &amp;lt;command_suite&amp;gt; help &amp;lt;operation_code&amp;gt;+

</programlisting>
                          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis> flag displays a command's syntax but not the short
                          description or alias:</para>

<programlisting>
   % &amp;lt;command_name&amp;gt; -help

</programlisting>
                            <para>The apropos operation code displays the short description of any command
                            in a suite whose operation code or short description includes the
                            specified keyword:</para>

<programlisting>
   % &amp;lt;command_suite&amp;gt; apropos "&amp;lt;help string&amp;gt;"

</programlisting>
                              <para>The following example command displays the complete online help entry for
                              the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs help setacl
   fs setacl: set access control list
   aliases: sa
   Usage: fs setacl -dir &amp;lt;directory&amp;gt;+ -acl &amp;lt;access list entries&amp;gt;+
   [-clear] [-negative] [-id] [-if] [-help]

</programlisting>
                                <para>To see only the syntax statement, use the <emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis> flag:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs setacl -help
   Usage: fs setacl -dir &amp;lt;directory&amp;gt;+ -acl &amp;lt;access list entries&amp;gt;+
   [-clear] [-negative] [-id] [-if] [-help]

</programlisting>
                                  <para>In the following example, a user wants to display the quota for her home
                                  volume. She knows that the relevant command belongs to the <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> suite,
                                  but cannot remember the operation code. She uses <emphasis role="bold">quota</emphasis> as the keyword:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs apropos quota
   listquota: list volume quota
   quota: show volume quota usage
   setquota: set volume quota

</programlisting>
                                    <para>The following illustrates the error message that results if no command
                                    name or short description contains the keyword:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs apropos "list quota"
   Sorry, no commands found

</programlisting>
                                    </refsect3>
                                  </refsect2>
                                </refsect1>
                                <refsect1>
                                  <title>Privilege Required</title>
                                  <para>Many AFS commands require one or more types of administrative
                                  privilege. See the reference page for each command.</para>

                                </refsect1>
                                <refsect1>
                                  <title>See Also</title>
                                  <para><link linkend="afsd8">afsd(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="afsmonitor1">afsmonitor(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="backup8">backup(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="bos8">bos(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="bosserver8">bosserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="buserver8">buserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="butc8">butc(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="dlog1">dlog(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="dpass1">dpass(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="fileserver8">fileserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="fms8">fms(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="fs1">fs(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="fstrace8">fstrace(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kadb_check8">kadb_check(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kaserver8">kaserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kdb8">kdb(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="klog1">klog(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="knfs1">knfs(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kpasswd1">kpasswd(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="kpwvalid8">kpwvalid(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="package1">package(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="pagsh1">pagsh(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="prdb_check8">prdb_check(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="ptserver8">ptserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="rxdebug1">rxdebug(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="salvager8">salvager(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="scout1">scout(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="sys1">sys(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="tokens1">tokens(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="translate_et1">translate_et(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="unlog1">unlog(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="up1">up(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="upclient8">upclient(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="upserver8">upserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="uss8">uss(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="vldb_check8">vldb_check(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="vlserver8">vlserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="volinfo8">volinfo(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="volserver8">volserver(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="vos1">vos(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="xfs_size_check8">xfs_size_check(8)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="xstat_cm_test1">xstat_cm_test(1)</link>,
                                  <link linkend="xstat_fs_test1">xstat_fs_test(1)</link></para>

                                </refsect1>
                                <refsect1>
                                  <title>Copyright</title>
                                  <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

                                  <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
                                  converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
                                  Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

                                </refsect1>
                              </refentry>
