<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="fs_diskfree1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>fs diskfree</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>fs diskfree</refname>
    <refpurpose>Shows data about the partition housing a directory or file</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs diskfree</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs df</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs di</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs diskfree</emphasis> command formats and displays information about the
    partition that houses the volume containing the specified directory or
    file, including its size and how much space is currently used.</para>

    <para>To display information about the volume itself, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis>
    command. The <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs quota</emphasis> commands also display
    information about a volume.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>The partition-related statistics in this command's output do not always
    agree with the corresponding values in the output of the standard UNIX
    <emphasis role="bold">df</emphasis> command. The statistics reported by this command can be up to five
    minutes old, because the Cache Manager polls the File Server for partition
    information at that frequency. Also, on some operating systems, the <emphasis role="bold">df</emphasis>
    command's report of partition size includes reserved space not included in
    this command's calculation, and so is likely to be about 10% larger.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names a file or directory that resides on the partition about which to
          produce output. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the current
          working directory, which is also the default value if this argument is
          omitted.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>The output reports the following information about the volume and
    partition that houses each file or directory:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Volume Name</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the volume.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>kbytes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The partition's total size in kilobytes.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>used</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The number of kilobytes used on the partition.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>avail</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The number of kilobytes available on the partition.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>%used</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The percentage of the partition's total space that is used (the <computeroutput>used</computeroutput>
          statistic divided by the <computeroutput>kbytes</computeroutput> statistic, times 100).</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>If the <computeroutput>%used</computeroutput> statistic is greater than 90%, it is marked with the
    string <computeroutput>&lt;&lt;WARNING</computeroutput> at the right margin.</para>

    <para>If the volume is a read-only volume, the output includes information about
    only one of the partitions that houses it, generally the one on the file
    server machine with the lowest preference rank. To verify which machine
    the output is referring to, use the <emphasis role="bold">vos listvldb</emphasis> command to list the
    volume's locations, and the <emphasis role="bold">vos partinfo</emphasis> command to display the size of
    each one.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following example shows the output for the partitions housing the
    volumes <computeroutput>user.smith</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>sun4x_56.bin</computeroutput>:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs diskfree -path /afs/abc.com/usr/smith /afs/abc.com/sun4x_56/bin
   Volume Name     kbytes  used     avail     %used
   user.smith     4177920 3841258  336662       92% &amp;lt;&amp;lt;WARNING
   sun4x_56.bin   4423680 3174500 1249180       72%

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must have the <computeroutput>l</computeroutput> (lookup) permission on the ACL of the root
      directory of the volume that houses the file or directory named by the
      <emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> argument, and on the ACL of each directory that precedes it in
      the pathname.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="fs_examine1">fs_examine(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
