<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="fs_flushmount1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>fs flushmount</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>fs flushmount</refname>
    <refpurpose>Forces the Cache Manager to discard a mount point</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs flushmount</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs flushm</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs flushmount</emphasis> command removes from the cache all information
    associated with each mount point named by the <emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> argument. The next
    time an application accesses the mount point, the Cache Manager fetches
    the most current version of it from the File Server. Data cached from the
    associated volume is not affected.</para>

    <para>The command's intended use is to discard information about mount points
    that has become corrupted in the cache. (The Cache Manager periodically
    refreshes cached mount points, but the only other way to discard them
    immediately is to reinitialize the Cache Manager by rebooting the
    machine.) Symptoms of a corrupted mount point included garbled output from
    the <emphasis role="bold">fs lsmount</emphasis> command, and failed attempts to change directory to or
    list the contents of a mount point.</para>

    <para>To flush cached data rather than a mount point, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs flush</emphasis> or
    <emphasis role="bold">fs flushvolume</emphasis> command.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dir/file path</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names each mount point to flush from the cache. Partial pathnames are
          interpreted relative to the current working directory, which is also the
          default value if this argument is omitted.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following command flushes from the cache the mount point for user
    <computeroutput>pat</computeroutput>'s home directory:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs flushm /afs/abc.com/usr/pat

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must have the <computeroutput>l</computeroutput> (lookup) permission on the ACL of the root
      directory of the volume that houses the file or directory named by the
      <emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> argument, and on the ACL of each directory that precedes it in
      the pathname.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="fs_flush1">fs_flush(1)</link>,
      <link linkend="fs_flushvolume1">fs_flushvolume(1)</link>,
      <link linkend="fs_lsmount1">fs_lsmount(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
