<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="fs_sysname1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>fs sysname</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>fs sysname</refname>
    <refpurpose>Reports or sets the CPU/operating system type</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs sysname</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-newsys</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new sysname</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">fs sy</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-n</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new sysname</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs sysname</emphasis> command sets or displays the local machine's
    CPU/operating system type as recorded in kernel memory. The Cache Manager
    substitutes the string for the <emphasis>@sys</emphasis> variable which can occur in AFS
    pathnames; the <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis> and <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
    Guide</emphasis> explain how using <emphasis>@sys</emphasis> can simplify cell configuration. It is
    best to use it sparingly, however, because it can make the effect of
    changing directories unpredictable.</para>

    <para>The command always applies to the local machine only. If issued on an NFS
    client machine accessing AFS via the NFS/AFS Translator, the string is set
    or reported for the NFS client machine. The Cache Manager on the AFS
    client machine serving as the NFS client's NFS/AFS translator machine
    stores the value in its kernel memory, and so can provide the NFS client
    with the proper version of program binaries when the user issues commands
    for which the pathname to the binaries includes <emphasis>@sys</emphasis>. There is a
    separate record for each user logged into the NFS client, which implies
    that if a user adopts a new identity (UNIX UID) during a login session on
    the NFS client -- perhaps by using the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command -- he or she
    must verify that the correct string is set for the new identity also.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-newsys</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new sysname</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the CPU/operating system indicator string for the local machine. If
          this argument is omitted, the output displays the current setting
          instead. AFS uses a standardized set of strings; consult the <emphasis>IBM AFS
          Quick Beginnings</emphasis> or <emphasis>AFS Release Notes</emphasis>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>When the <emphasis role="bold">-newsys</emphasis> argument is omitted, the output reports the machine's
    system type in the following format:</para>

<programlisting>
   Current sysname is '&amp;lt;system_type&amp;gt;'

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <para>The following example shows the output produced on a Sun SPARCStation
      running Solaris 5.7:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs sysname
   Current sysname is 'sun4x_57'

</programlisting>
        <para>The following command defines a machine to be a IBM RS/6000 running AIX
        4.2:</para>

<programlisting>
   % fs sysname -newsys rs_aix42

</programlisting>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>Privilege Required</title>
          <para>To display the current setting, no privilege is required. To include the
          <emphasis role="bold">-newsys</emphasis> argument on an AFS client machine, the issuer must be logged in
          as the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>See Also</title>
          <para><link linkend="fs_exportafs1">fs_exportafs(1)</link>,
          <link linkend="sys1">sys(1)</link></para>

          <para><emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis></para>

          <para><emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis></para>

        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>Copyright</title>
          <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

          <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
          converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
          Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

        </refsect1>
      </refentry>
