<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="pts_rename1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pts rename</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>pts rename</refname>
    <refpurpose>Changes the name of a Protection Database entry</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-oldname</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>old name</emphasis>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-newname</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new name</emphasis>&gt;
        [<emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;]  [<emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-force</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">pts ren</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-o</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>old name</emphasis>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-ne</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new name</emphasis>&gt; [<emphasis role="bold">-c</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-no</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-f</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> command changes the name of the user, machine, or group
    entry specified by the <emphasis role="bold">-oldname</emphasis> argument to the name specified by the
    <emphasis role="bold">-newname</emphasis> argument. It is not possible to change a user or machine
    entry's name to look like a regular group entry's name (have a colon in
    it).</para>

    <para>Members of the system:administrators group can change a regular group name
    into a prefix-less name and vice versa. When changing a prefix-less group
    name into a regular group name or a regular group name to another regular
    group name, the owner field of the new name (the part before the colon)
    must correctly reflect the group's owner.</para>

    <para>Changing a regular group's owner with the <emphasis role="bold">pts chown</emphasis> command
    automatically changes the owner field (the part before the colon) of the
    group's name, but does not change the owner field of any groups owned by
    the group. Use this command to rename those groups to a form that
    accurately reflects their ownership.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>By convention, many aspects of an AFS user account have the same name as
    the user's Protection Database entry, including the Authentication
    Database entry, volume, and mount point. When using this command to change
    a user name, also change the names of all related entities to maintain
    consistency. For instructions, see the chapter on user accounts in the
    <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis>.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-oldname</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>old name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the current full name of the entry.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-newname</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>new name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the new full name for the entry. For regular groups, the owner
          field (the part before the colon) of the new name must reflect the actual
          ownership of the group.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names the cell in which to run the command. For more details, see
          <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigns the unprivileged identity anonymous to the issuer. For more
          details, see <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-force</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enables the command to continue executing as far as possible when errors
          or other problems occur, rather than halting execution at the first error.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following example changes the name of the group staff, owned by the
    privileged user <computeroutput>admin</computeroutput>, to <computeroutput>admin:staff</computeroutput>:</para>

<programlisting>
   % pts rename -oldname staff -newname admin:staff

</programlisting>
      <para>The following example changes the name of the group <computeroutput>admin:finance</computeroutput> to
      the group <computeroutput>finance</computeroutput>. The issuer must belong to the system:administrators
      group.</para>

<programlisting>
   % pts rename -oldname admin:finance -newname finance

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Privilege Required</title>
        <para>To change a regular group name to a prefix-less name or vice versa, or to
        change a user or machine entry's name, the issuer must belong to the
        system:administrators group.</para>

        <para>To change a group name to a new name of the same type (regular or
        prefix-less), the issuer must own the group or belong to the
        system:administrators group.</para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para><link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>,
        <link linkend="pts_chown1">pts_chown(1)</link></para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Copyright</title>
        <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
        converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
        Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
