<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="pts_listowned1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pts listowned</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>pts listowned</refname>
    <refpurpose>Show the Protection Database groups owned by a user or group</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>user or group name or id</emphasis>&gt;+
        [-cell &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-force</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">pts listo</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-na</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>user or group name or id</emphasis>&gt;+
        [-c &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-no</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-f</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> command lists the groups owned by each user or group
    specified by the <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> argument.</para>

    <para>To list any <emphasis>orphaned group</emphasis>s, whose owners have themselves been deleted
    from the Protection Database, provide a value of <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> (zero) for the
    <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> argument. To change the owner to a user or group that still
    exists, use the <emphasis role="bold">pts chown</emphasis> command.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>user or group name or id</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the name or AFS UID of each user, or the name or AFS GID of each
          group, for which to display the list of owned groups. It is acceptable to
          mix users and groups on the same command line, as well as names and
          IDs. Precede the GID of each group with a hyphen to indicate that it is
          negative.</para>

          <para>A value of 0 (zero) lists group entries for groups whose owners no longer
          have entries in the Protection Database.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names the cell in which to run the command. For more details, see
          <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigns the unprivileged identity anonymous to the issuer. For more
          details, see <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-force</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enables the command to continue executing as far as possible when errors
          or other problems occur, rather than halting execution at the first error.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>The first line of the output indicates the name and AFS UID or AFS GID of
    each user or group for which ownership information is requested, in the
    following format:</para>

<programlisting>
   Groups owned by &amp;lt;name&amp;gt; (id: &amp;lt;ID&amp;gt;) are:

</programlisting>
      <para>A list of groups follows. The list does not include groups owned by groups
      that the user or group owns, or to which the user or group belongs. If the
      user or group does not own any groups, only the header line appears.</para>

      <para>The following error message appears if the issuer is not privileged to
      view ownership information. By default, for both user and group entries
      the second privacy flag is the hyphen, which denies permission to anyone
      other than the user (for a user entry) and the members of the
      system:administrators group.</para>

<programlisting>
   pts: Permission denied so failed to get owner list for &amp;lt;name&amp;gt; (id: &amp;lt;ID&amp;gt;)

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <para>The following example lists the groups owned by user terry and shows that
        the group <computeroutput>terry:friends</computeroutput> does not own any groups:</para>

<programlisting>
   % pts listowned terry terry:friends
   Groups owned by terry (id: 1045) are:
     terry:friends
     terry:project1
     terry:project2
   Groups owned by terry:friends (id: -673) are:

</programlisting>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>Privilege Required</title>
          <para>The required privilege depends on the setting of the second privacy flag
          in the Protection Database entry of each user or group indicated by the
          <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> argument (use the <emphasis role="bold">pts examine</emphasis> command to display the
          flags):</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If it is the hyphen and the <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> argument specifies a group, only
              the members of the system:administrators group and the owner of a group
              can list the groups it owns.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>If it is the hyphen and the <emphasis role="bold">-nameorid</emphasis> argument specifies a user, only
              the members of the system:administrators group and the associated user can
              list the groups he or she owns.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>If it is uppercase letter <computeroutput>O</computeroutput>, anyone who can access the cell's database
              server machines can list the groups owned by this user or group.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>See Also</title>
          <para><link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link>,
          <link linkend="pts_chown1">pts_chown(1)</link>,
          <link linkend="pts_examine1">pts_examine(1)</link>,
          <link linkend="pts_setfields1">pts_setfields(1)</link></para>

        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
          <title>Copyright</title>
          <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

          <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
          converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
          Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

        </refsect1>
      </refentry>
