<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="sys1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>sys</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>sys</refname>
    <refpurpose>Reports the compile-time CPU/operating system type</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">sys</emphasis></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">sys</emphasis> command displays the string set at compile time that indicates
    the local machine's CPU/operating system (OS) type, conventionally called
    the <emphasis>sysname</emphasis>.  This string is the default for the value stored in kernel
    memory.  The Cache Manager substitutes this string for the <emphasis>@sys</emphasis>
    variable which can occur in AFS pathnames; the <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis> explain how using <emphasis>@sys</emphasis> can simplify
    cell configuration.</para>

    <para>To set a new value in kernel memory, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs sysname</emphasis> command.  To
    view the current value set in the kernel, use either <emphasis role="bold">fs sysname</emphasis> or
    <emphasis role="bold">livesys</emphasis>.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>You almost always want to use <emphasis role="bold">livesys</emphasis> rather than this command.  The
    <emphasis role="bold">sys</emphasis> command displays a single value hard-coded at compile time.  It
    does not query the Cache Manager for the current value and it does not
    report sysname lists.  If you have changed the local system type with <emphasis role="bold">fs
    sysname</emphasis>, or if you run a version of <emphasis role="bold">sys</emphasis> compiled differently than the
    Cache Manager running on the system, the value retured will not match the
    behavior of the Cache Manager.  The only reason to use <emphasis role="bold">sys</emphasis> is that
    <emphasis role="bold">livesys</emphasis> wasn't available in older versions of AFS.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>The machine's system type appears as a text string:</para>

<programlisting>
   I&amp;lt;system_type&amp;gt;

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <para>The following example shows the output produced on a Sun SPARCStation
      running Solaris 5.7:</para>

<programlisting>
   % sys
   sun4x_57

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Privilege Required</title>
        <para>None</para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para><link linkend="fs_sysname1">fs_sysname(1)</link>,
        <link linkend="livesys1">livesys(1)</link></para>

        <para><emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis></para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Copyright</title>
        <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
        converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
        Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
