<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ562">
  <title>Managing Access Control Lists</title>

  <para>To control access to a directory and all of the files in it, AFS associates an <emphasis>access control list</emphasis>
  (<emphasis>ACL</emphasis>) with it, rather than the mode bits that the UNIX file system (UFS) associates with individual files or
  directories. AFS ACLs provide more refined access control because there are seven access permissions rather than UFS's three, and
  there is room for approximately 20 user or group entries on an ACL, rather than just the three UFS entries (<emphasis
  role="bold">owner</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">group</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">other</emphasis>).</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ563">
    <title>Summary of Instructions</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to perform the following tasks by using the indicated commands:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="57*" />

        <colspec colwidth="43*" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Examine access control list</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Edit ACL's normal permissions section</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Edit ACL's negative permissions section</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> with <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Replace an ACL</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> with <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Copy an ACL</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Remove obsolete AFS UIDs</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs cleanacl</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ565">
    <title>Protecting Data in AFS</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>protection of file data</primary>

      <secondary>see also: <emphasis>ACL</emphasis></secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>protection of file data</primary>

      <secondary>AFS compared to UFS<emphasis>ACL</emphasis></secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>This section describes the main differences between the AFS and UFS file protection systems, discusses the implications of
    directory-level protections, and describes the seven access permissions.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ566">
      <title>Differences Between UFS and AFS Data Protection</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>UFS</primary>

        <secondary>file protection compared to AFS</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>protection of file data</primary>

        <secondary>AFS compared to UFS<emphasis>ACL</emphasis></secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>compared to UNIX protection</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The UFS mode bits data protection system and the AFS ACL system differ in the following ways: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Protection at the file level (UFS) versus the directory level (AFS)</para>

            <para>UFS associates a set of nine mode bits with each file element, three (<emphasis role="bold">rwx</emphasis>) for
            each of the element's owner, owning group, and all other users. A similar set of mode bits on the file's directory
            applies to the file only in an oblique way.</para>

            <para>An AFS ACL instead protects all files in a directory in the same way. If a certain file is more sensitive than
            others, store it in a directory with a more restrictive ACL.</para>

            <para>Defining access at the directory level has important consequences: <indexterm>
                <primary>directory-level data protection</primary>

                <secondary>implications</secondary>
              </indexterm> <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The permissions on a directory's ACL apply to all of the files in the directory. When you move a file to a
                  different directory, you effectively change the access permissions that apply to it to those on its new
                  directory's ACL. Changing a directory's ACL changes the protection on all the files in it.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>When you create a subdirectory, its initial ACL is created as a copy of its parent directory's ACL. You can
                  then change the subdirectory's ACL independently. However, the parent directory's ACL continues to control access
                  to the subdirectory in the following way: the parent directory's ACL must grant the <emphasis
                  role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission to a user (or a group the user
                  belongs to) in order for the user to access the subdirectory at all.</para>

                  <para>In general, then, it is best to assign fairly liberal access permissions to high-level directories
                  (including user home directories). In particular, it often makes sense to grant at least the <emphasis
                  role="bold">l</emphasis> permission to the <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> or <emphasis
                  role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group on high-level directories. For further discussion, see <link
                  linkend="HDRWQ571">Using Groups on ACLs</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>How the mode bits are interpreted</para>

            <para>Mode bits are the only file-protection system in UFS. AFS allows you to set the UNIX mode bits on a file in
            addition to the ACL on its directory, but it interprets them differently. See <link linkend="HDRWQ580">How AFS
            Interprets the UNIX Mode Bits</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Three access permissions (UFS) versus seven (AFS)</para>

            <para>UFS defines three access permissions in the form of mode bits: <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis
            role="bold">read</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>), and <emphasis
            role="bold">x</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">execute</emphasis>). AFS defines seven permissions, which makes access
            control more precise. For detailed descriptions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ567">The AFS ACL Permissions</link>.
            <simplelist>
                <member><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lock</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>)</member>

                <member><emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>)</member>
              </simplelist></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Three defined users and groups (UFS) versus many (AFS)</para>

            <para>UFS controls access for one user and two groups by providing a set of mode bits for each: the user who owns the
            file or directory, a single defined group, and everyone who has an account on the system.</para>

            <para>AFS, in contrast, allows you to place many entries (individual users or groups) on an ACL, granting a different
            set of access permissions to each one. The number of possible entries is about 20, and depends on how much space each
            entry occupies in the memory allocated for the ACL itself.</para>

            <para>AFS defines two system groups, <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> and <emphasis
            role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis>, which represent all users and all authenticated users, respectively; for further
            discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ571">Using Groups on ACLs</link>. In addition, users can define their own groups in
            the Protection Database, consisting of individual users or machine IP addresses. Users who have the <emphasis
            role="bold">a</emphasis> permission on an ACL can create entries for the system groups as well as groups defined by
            themselves or other users. For information on defining groups, see <link linkend="HDRWQ531">Administering the Protection
            Database</link>.</para>

            <para>When a user requests access to a file or directory, the File Server sums together all of the permissions that the
            relevant ACL extends to the user and to groups to which the user belongs. Placing group entries on ACLs therefore can
            control access for many more users than the ACL can accommodate as individual entries.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ567">
      <title>The AFS ACL Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>access</primary>

        <secondary>permissions on ACL (see entries: <emphasis>permissions on ACL</emphasis>, <emphasis>ACL</emphasis>)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>permissions on ACL</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>permissions defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Functionally, the seven standard ACL permissions fall into two groups: one that applies to the directory itself and one
      that applies to the files it contains.</para>

      <sect3 id="HDRWQ568">
        <title>The Four Directory Permissions</title>

        <para>The four permissions in this group are meaningful with respect to the directory itself. For example, the <emphasis
        role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>) permission does not control addition of data to a file,
        but rather creation of a new file or subdirectory. <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The l (lookup) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission functions as something of a gate keeper for access to the directory and its files, because a
                user must have it in order to exercise any other permissions. In particular, a user must have this permission to
                access anything in the directory's subdirectories, even if the ACL on a subdirectory grants extensive permissions.
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>lookup ACL permission</primary>

                    <secondary></secondary>

                    <see>l ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>l ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>

                <para>This permission enables a user to issue the following commands: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis> command to list the names of the files and subdirectories in the
                      directory</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> command to obtain complete status information for the
                      directory element itself</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command to examine the directory's ACL</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist></para>

                <para>This permission does not enable a user to read the contents of a file in the directory, to issue the <emphasis
                role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command on a file in the directory, or to issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs
                listacl</emphasis> command with the filename as the <emphasis role="bold">-path</emphasis> argument. Those
                operations require the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission which
                is described in <link linkend="HDRWQ569">The Three File Permissions</link>.</para>

                <para>Similarly, this permission does not enable a user to issue the <emphasis role="bold">ls</emphasis>, <emphasis
                role="bold">ls -l</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">fs
                listacl</emphasis> commands against a subdirectory of the directory. Those operations require the <emphasis
                role="bold">l</emphasis> permission on the ACL of the subdirectory itself.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The i (insert) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables a user to add new files to the directory, either by creating or copying, and to create
                new subdirectories. It does not extend into any subdirectories, which are protected by their own ACLs. <indexterm>
                    <primary>insert ACL permission</primary>

                    <secondary></secondary>

                    <see>i ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>i ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The d (delete) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables a user to remove files and subdirectories from the directory or move them into other
                directories (assuming that the user has the <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> permission on the ACL of the other
                directories). <indexterm>
                    <primary>delete ACL permission</primary>

                    <secondary></secondary>

                    <see>d ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>d ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The a (administer) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables a user to change the directory's ACL. Members of the <emphasis
                role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group implicitly have this permission on every directory (that is, even
                if that group does not appear on the ACL). Similarly, the owner of a directory implicitly has this permission on its
                ACL and those of all directories below it that he or she owns. <indexterm>
                    <primary>administer ACL permission</primary>

                    <secondary></secondary>

                    <see>a ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>a ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="HDRWQ569">
        <title>The Three File Permissions</title>

        <para>The three permissions in this group are meaningful with respect to files in a directory, rather than the directory
        itself or its subdirectories. <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The r (read) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables a user to read the contents of files in the directory and to issue the <emphasis
                role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command to stat the file elements. <indexterm>
                    <primary>read</primary>

                    <secondary>ACL permission</secondary>

                    <see>r ACL permission)</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>r ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The w (write) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables a user to modify the contents of files in the directory and to issue the <emphasis
                role="bold">chmod</emphasis> command to change their UNIX mode bits. <indexterm>
                    <primary>write</primary>

                    <secondary>ACL permission</secondary>

                    <see>write ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>w ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">The k (lock) permission</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This permission enables the user to run programs that issue system calls to lock files in the directory.
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>lock ACL permission</primary>

                    <secondary></secondary>

                    <see>k ACL permission</see>
                  </indexterm> <indexterm>
                    <primary>k ACL permission</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_635">
        <title>The Eight Auxiliary Permissions</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>undefined ACL permissions</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>auxiliary ACL permissions</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>ACL</primary>

          <secondary>auxiliary permissions</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>AFS provides eight additional permissions that do not have a defined meaning, denoted by the uppercase letters
        <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">D</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">G</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">H</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>You can write application programs that assign a meaning to one or more of the permissions, and then place them on
        ACLs to control file access by those programs. For example, you can modify a print program to recognize and interpret the
        permissions, and then place them on directories that house files that the program accesses. Use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
        listacl</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> commands to display and set the auxiliary permissions on
        ACLs just like the standard seven.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_636">
        <title>Shorthand Notation for Sets of Permissions</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>ACL</primary>

          <secondary>shorthand notation for grouping permissions</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>shorthand notation</primary>

          <secondary>ACL permissions</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>You can combine the seven permissions in any way in an ACL entry, but certain combinations are more useful than
        others. Four of the more common combinations have corresponding shorthand forms. When using the <emphasis role="bold">fs
        setacl</emphasis> command to define ACL entries, you can provide either one or more of the individual letters that represent
        the permissions, or one of the following shorthand forms: <variablelist>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>all shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Represents all seven standard permissions (<emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>). <indexterm>
                    <primary>none shorthand for ACL permissions</primary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Removes the entry from the ACL, leaving the user or group with no permissions. <indexterm>
                    <primary>read</primary>

                    <secondary>shorthand for ACL permissions</secondary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Represents the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) and <emphasis
                role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permissions. <indexterm>
                    <primary>write</primary>

                    <secondary>shorthand for ACL permissions</secondary>
                  </indexterm></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Represents all permissions except <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis
                role="bold">administer</emphasis>): <emphasis role="bold">rlidwk</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ570">
      <title>Using Normal and Negative Permissions</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>normal vs. negative permissions</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>normal ACL permissions</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>negative ACL permissions</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>ACLs enable you both to grant and to deny access to a directory and the files in it. To grant access, use the <emphasis
      role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to create an ACL entry that associates a set of permissions with a user or group, as
      described in <link linkend="HDRWQ573">Setting ACL Entries</link>. When you use the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
      command to display an ACL (as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>), such entries appear underneath
      the following header, which uses the term <emphasis>rights</emphasis> to refer to permissions:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Normal rights
</programlisting>

      <para>There are two ways to deny access: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The recommended method is simply to omit an entry for the user or group from the ACL, or to omit the appropriate
            permissions from the entry. Use the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to remove or edit an existing
            entry, using the instructions in <link linkend="HDRWQ574">To add, remove, or edit normal ACL permissions</link>. In most
            circumstances, this method is enough to prevent access of certain kinds or by certain users. You must take care,
            however, not to grant the undesired permissions to any groups to which such users belong.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The more explicit method for denying access is to use the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag to the
            <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to create an entry that associates <emphasis>negative
            permissions</emphasis> with the user or group; for instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ575">To add, remove, or edit
            negative ACL permissions</link>. The output from the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command lists negative
            entries underneath the following header: <programlisting>
   Negative rights
</programlisting></para>

            <para>When determining what type of access to grant to a user, the File Server first compiles a set of permissions by
            examining all of the entries in the <computeroutput>Normal rights</computeroutput> section of the ACL. It then subtracts
            any permissions associated with the user (or with groups to which the user belongs) on the <computeroutput>Negative
            rights</computeroutput> section of the ACL. Therefore, negative permissions always cancel out normal permissions.</para>

            <para>Using negative permissions reverses the usual semantics of the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command,
            introducing the potential for confusion. In particular, combining the <emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand
            and the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag constitutes a double negative: by removing an entry from the
            <computeroutput>Negative rights</computeroutput> section of the ACL, you enable a user once again to obtain permissions
            via entries in the <computeroutput>Normal rights</computeroutput> section. Combining the <emphasis
            role="bold">all</emphasis> shorthand with the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag explicitly denies all
            permissions.</para>

            <para>Note also that it is pointless to create an entry in the <computeroutput>Negative rights</computeroutput> section
            if an entry in the <computeroutput>Normal rights</computeroutput> section grants the denied permissions to the <emphasis
            role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group. In this case, users can obtain the permissions simply by using the
            <emphasis role="bold">unlog</emphasis> command to discard their tokens. When they do so, the File Server recognizes them
            as the <emphasis role="bold">anonymous</emphasis> user, who belongs to the <emphasis
            role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group but does not match the entries on the <computeroutput>Negative
            rights</computeroutput> section of the ACL.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ571">
      <title>Using Groups on ACLs</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>group</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry, usefulness of</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>group entries, usefulness</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>As previously mentioned, placing a group entry on an ACL enables you to control access for many users at once. You can
      grant a new user access to many files and directories simply by adding the user to a group that appears on the relevant ACLs.
      You can also create groups of machines, in which case any user logged on to the machine obtains the access that is granted to
      the group. On directories where they have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> permission on the ACL, users can define their
      own groups and can create ACL entries for any groups, not just groups that they create or own themselves. For instructions on
      creating groups of users or machines, and a discussion of the most effective ways to use different types of groups, see <link
      linkend="HDRWQ531">Administering the Protection Database</link>. <indexterm>
          <primary>system groups</primary>

          <secondary>using on ACLs</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>group</primary>

          <secondary>system-defined on ACLs</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>ACL</primary>

          <secondary>system groups on</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>system:anyuser group</primary>

          <secondary>using on ACLs</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>system:authuser group</primary>

          <secondary>using on ACLs</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <para>AFS also defines the following two system groups, which can be very useful on ACLs because they potentially represent a
      large group of people. For more information about these groups, see <link linkend="HDRWQ535">The System Groups</link>.
      <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Includes anyone who can access the cell's file tree, including users who have logged in as the local superuser
              <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>, have connected to a local machine from somewhere outside the cell, and AFS
              users who belong to a foreign cell. This group includes users who do not have tokens that are valid for the local AFS
              servers; the servers recognize them as the user <emphasis role="bold">anonymous</emphasis>.</para>

              <para>Note that creating an ACL entry for this group is the only way to extend access to AFS users from foreign cells,
              unless you create local authentication accounts for them. <indexterm>
                  <primary>ACL</primary>

                  <secondary>foreign users on</secondary>
                </indexterm></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Includes all users who have a valid AFS token obtained from the local cell's authentication service.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <para>It is particularly useful to grant the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>)
      permission to the <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group on the ACL of most directories in the file system,
      especially at the upper levels. This permission enables users only to learn the names of files and subdirectories in a
      directory, but without it they cannot traverse their way through the directories in the path to a target file.</para>

      <para>A slightly more restrictive alternative is to grant the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission to the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group. If that is still not restrictive enough, you can grant the <emphasis
      role="bold">l</emphasis> to specific users or groups, which cannot exceed about 20 in number on a given ACL.</para>

      <para>Another reason to grant certain permissions to the <emphasis role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group is to enable
      the correct operation of processes that provide services such as printing and mail delivery. For example, in addition to the
      <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permission, a print process possibly needs the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis>
      (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission in order to access the contents of files, and a mail delivery process
      possibly requires the <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>) permission to deliver new
      pieces of mail.</para>

      <para>The ACL on the root directory of every newly created volume grants all permissions to the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. You can remove this entry if you wish, but members of the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group always implicitly have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis
      role="bold">administer</emphasis>), and by default also the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis>, permission on every
      directory's ACL. The <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> permission enables them to grant themselves other permissions
      explicitly when necessary. To learn about changing this default set of permissions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ586">Administering
      the system:administrators Group</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ572">
    <title>Displaying ACLs</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>displaying</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>displaying</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To display the ACL associated with a file, directory or symbolic link, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs
    listacl</emphasis> command. The output for a symbolic link displays the ACL that applies to its target file or directory, rather
    than the ACL on the directory that houses the symbolic link.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine on which you issue the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command is configured to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit,
    you can use the command to display the ACL on DFS files and directories. To display a DFS directory's Initial Container and
    Initial Object ACL instead of the regular one, include the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command's <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flag. For instructions, see the <emphasis>IBM AFS/DFS
    Migration Toolkit Administration Guide and Reference</emphasis>. The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter
    ignores the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when
    displaying an AFS ACL. <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>listacl</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs listacl</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_640">
      <title>To display an ACL</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">la</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">listacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis
                role="bold">lista</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">dir/file path</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names one or more files or directories for which to display the ACL. For files, the output displays the ACL
                for its directory. If you omit this argument, the output is for the current working directory. Partial pathnames are
                interpreted relative to the current working directory. You can also use the following notation on its own or as part
                of a pathname: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(A single period). Specifies the current working directory.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">..</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(Two periods). Specifies the current working directory's parent directory.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>
                      <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>(The asterisk). Specifies each file and subdirectory in the current working directory. The ACL
                        displayed for a file is always the same as for its directory, but the ACL for each subdirectory can
                        differ.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                  </variablelist></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following error message indicates that you do not have the permissions needed to display an ACL. To specify a
      directory name as the dir/file path argument, you must have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis
      role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on the ACL. To specify a filename, you must also have the <emphasis
      role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission on its directory's ACL.</para>

      <programlisting>
   fs: You don't have the required access permissions on 'dir/file path'
</programlisting>

      <para>Members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group and the directory's owner (as reported by
      the <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> command) implicitly have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis
      role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission on every directory's ACL, and can use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      setacl</emphasis> command to grant themselves the required permissions; for instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ573">Setting
      ACL Entries</link>.</para>

      <para>The output for each file or directory specified as dir/file path begins with the following header to identify it:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Access list for  dir/file path is
</programlisting>

      <para>The <computeroutput>Normal rights</computeroutput> header appears on the next line, followed by lines that each pair a
      user or group name and a set of permissions. The permissions appear as the single letters defined in <link
      linkend="HDRWQ567">The AFS ACL Permissions</link>, and always in the order <emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>. If there
      are any negative permissions, the <computeroutput>Negative rights</computeroutput> header appears next, followed by pairs of
      negative permissions.</para>

      <para>The following example displays the ACL on user <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory in the ABC
      Corporation cell:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs la /afs/abc.com/usr/terry</emphasis>
   Access list for /afs/abc.com/usr/terry is
   Normal permissions:
      system:authuser rl
      pat rlw
      terry rlidwka
   Negative permissions:
      terry:other-dept rl
      jones rl
</programlisting>

      <para>where <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>, and <emphasis
      role="bold">jones</emphasis> are individual users, <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> is a system group, and
      <emphasis role="bold">terry:other-dept</emphasis> is a group that <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> owns. The list of
      normal permissions grants all permissions to <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis>
      (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>), and
      <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>) permissions to <emphasis
      role="bold">pat</emphasis>, and the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions to
      the members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group.</para>

      <para>The list of negative permissions denies the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis>
      permissions to <emphasis role="bold">jones</emphasis> and the members of the <emphasis role="bold">terry:other-dept</emphasis>
      group. These entries effectively prevent them from accessing <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis>'s home directory in any
      way, because they cancel out the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions
      extended to the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group, which is the only entry on the <computeroutput>Normal
      rights</computeroutput> section of the ACL that possibly applies to them.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ573">
    <title>Setting ACL Entries</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>setting entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>editing entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>adding entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>removing entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>changing</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>setting</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>granting</primary>

      <secondary>file access by setting ACL</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entry</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>adding</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entry</secondary>

      <tertiary>normal permissions</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>removing</primary>

      <secondary>ACL entry</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To add, remove, or edit ACL entries, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command. By default, the command
    manipulates entries on the normal permissions section of the ACL. To manipulate entries on the negative permissions section,
    include the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis> flag.</para>

    <para>You must have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission on an ACL to
    edit it. The owner of a directory (as reported by the <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis>) command and members of the
    <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group always implicitly have it on every ACL. By default, members of the
    <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group also implicitly have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis>
    (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine on which you issue the <emphasis
    role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command is configured to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit,
    you can use the command to set the ACL on DFS files and directories. To set a DFS directory's Initial Container and Initial
    Object ACL instead of the regular one, include the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command's <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flag. For instructions, see the <emphasis>IBM AFS/DFS
    Migration Toolkit Administration Guide and Reference</emphasis>. The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter
    ignores the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when setting
    an AFS ACL. <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>setacl</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs setacl</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ574">
      <title>To add, remove, or edit normal ACL permissions</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission
          on each directory for which you are editing the ACL. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
          command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to edit entries in the normal permissions section of
          the ACL. To remove an entry, specify the <emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand as the permissions. If an ACL
          entry already exists, the permissions you specify completely replace those in the existing entry. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl  -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;+ <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;+
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis>
                is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
                role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the current working
                directory.</para>

                <para>Specify the read/write path to each directory, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to change a
                read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period before the cell name at the
                pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>). For further discussion of the
                concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link linkend="HDRWQ209">The Rules of Mount
                Point Traversal</link>.</para>

                <para>You can also use the following notation on its own or as part of a pathname:</para>

                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(A single period). If used by itself, sets the ACL on the current working directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">..</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(Two periods). If used by itself, sets the ACL on the current working directory's parent
                      directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(The asterisk). Sets the ACL on each of the subdirectories in the current working directory. You must
                      precede it with the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> switch, since it potentially designates multiple
                      directories. The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter generates the following error message
                      for each file in the directory: <programlisting>
   fs: 'filename': Not a directory
</programlisting></para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>

                <para>If you specify only one directory or file name, you can omit the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> and
                <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> switches.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
                the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces.</para>

                <para>To define the permissions, provide either:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>One or more of the letters that represent the standard or auxiliary permissions (<emphasis
                    role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">ABCDEFGH</emphasis>), in any order</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>One of the four shorthand notations: <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rlidwka</emphasis>)</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">none</emphasis> (removes the entry)</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rl</emphasis>)</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis> (equals <emphasis role="bold">rlidwk</emphasis>)</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>For a more detailed description of the permissions and shorthand notations, see <link linkend="HDRWQ567">The
                AFS ACL Permissions</link>.</para>

                <para>On a single command line, you can combine user and group entries. You can also use individual letters in some
                pairs and the shorthand notations in other pairs, but cannot combine letters and shorthand notation within a single
                pair.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Either of the following examples grants user <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis>
      (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>)
      permissions on the ACL of the <emphasis role="bold">notes</emphasis> subdirectory in the issuer's home directory. They
      illustrate how it is possible to omit the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis>
      switches when you name only one directory.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa ~/notes pat rl</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa ~/notes pat read</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example edits the ACL for the current working directory. It removes the entry for the <emphasis
      role="bold">system:anyuser</emphasis> group, and adds two entries: one grants all permissions except <emphasis
      role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) to the members of the <emphasis
      role="bold">terry:colleagues</emphasis> group and the other grants the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis
      role="bold">read</emphasis>) and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permissions to
      the <emphasis role="bold">system:authuser</emphasis> group. The command appears on two lines here only for legibility.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs  sa  -dir . -acl  system:anyuser  none  terry:colleagues  write  \
           system:authuser  rl</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>setacl</secondary>

        <tertiary>with -negative flag</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs setacl</secondary>

        <tertiary>with -negative flag</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>creating</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry in negative permissions section</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>adding</primary>

        <secondary>ACL entry</secondary>

        <tertiary>negative permissions</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>denying</primary>

        <secondary>file access with negative ACL entry</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ575">
      <title>To add, remove, or edit negative ACL permissions</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission
          on each directory for which you are editing the ACL. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
          command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis>
          flag to edit entries in the negative permissions section of the ACL. To remove an entry, specify the <emphasis
          role="bold">none</emphasis> shorthand as the permissions. If an ACL entry already exists for a user or group, the
          permissions you specify completely replace those in the existing entry. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;+ <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;+  <emphasis
                role="bold">-negative</emphasis> 
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis>
                is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the negative ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
                role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. Specify the read/write path to each directory, to avoid the failure that
                results when you attempt to change a read-only volume. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link
                linkend="HDRWQ574">To add, remove, or edit normal ACL permissions</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
                the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces. For a detailed description of acceptable values,
                see <link linkend="HDRWQ574">To add, remove, or edit normal ACL permissions</link>. Keep in mind that the usual
                meaning of each permission is reversed.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Places the entries defined by the <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument on the negative permissions
                section of the ACL for each directory named by the <emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis> argument.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example denies user <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis
      role="bold">write</emphasis>) and <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>) permissions for
      the <emphasis role="bold">project</emphasis> subdirectory of the current working directory.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs sa project pat wd -neg</emphasis>
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ576">
    <title>Completely Replacing an ACL</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>replacing all entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>clearing</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>replacing</primary>

      <secondary>all entries on ACL</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>erasing</primary>

      <secondary>all ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>clearing</primary>

      <secondary>all ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>removing</primary>

      <secondary>all ACL entries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>It is sometimes simplest to clear an ACL completely before defining new permissions on it, for instance if the mix of
    normal and negative permissions makes it difficult to understand how their interaction affects a user's access to the directory.
    To clear an ACL completely while you define new entries, include the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag on the
    <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command. When you include this flag, you can create entries on either the normal
    permissions or the negative permissions section of the ACL, but not on both at once.</para>

    <para>Remember to create an entry that grants appropriate permissions to the directory's owner. The owner implicitly has the
    <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission required to replace a deleted entry,
    but the effects of a missing ACL entry (particularly the lack of the <emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis> permission) can be
    so confusing that it becomes difficult for the owner to realize that the missing entry is causing the problems. <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>setacl</secondary>

        <tertiary>with -clear flag</tertiary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs setacl</secondary>

        <tertiary>with -clear flag</tertiary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_645">
      <title>To replace an ACL completely</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission
          on each directory for which you are editing the ACL. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
          command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag
          to clear the ACL completely before setting either normal or negative permissions. Because you need to grant the owner of
          the directory all permissions, it is better in most cases to set normal permissions at this point. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl -dir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;+ <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>access list entries</replaceable>&gt;+ <emphasis
                role="bold">-clear</emphasis>  \
               [<emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">sa</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setacl</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">seta</emphasis>
                is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-dir</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names one or more directories to which to apply the negative ACL entries defined by the <emphasis
                role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument. Specify the read/write path to each directory, to avoid the failure that
                results when you attempt to change a read-only volume. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link
                linkend="HDRWQ574">To add, remove, or edit normal ACL permissions</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies one or more ACL entries, each of which pairs a user or group name and a set of permissions. Separate
                the pairs, and the two parts of each pair, with one or more spaces. Remember to grant all permissions to the owner
                of the directory. For a detailed description of acceptable values, see <link linkend="HDRWQ574">To add, remove, or
                edit normal ACL permissions</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Removes all entries from each ACL before creating the entries indicated by the <emphasis
                role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-negative</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Places the entries defined by the <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> argument on the negative permissions
                section of each ACL.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ577">
    <title>Copying ACLs Between Directories</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>ACL</primary>

      <secondary>copying between directories</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>ACL as copy of another</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>copying</primary>

      <secondary>ACL between directories</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis> command copies a source directory's ACL to one or more destination
    directories. It does not affect the source ACL at all, but changes each destination ACL as follows: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry on the source ACL does not exist on the destination ACL, the command copies it to the destination
          ACL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry on the destination ACL does not also exist on the source ACL, the command does not remove it unless you
          include the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag to overwrite the destination ACL completely.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If an entry is on both ACLs, the command changes the permissions on the destination ACL entry to match the source
          ACL entry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note for AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit users:</emphasis> If the machine is configured to enable AFS
    users to access a DCE cell's DFS filespace via the AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit, then you can use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
    copyacl</emphasis> command to copy ACLs between DFS files and directories also. The command includes <emphasis
    role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags for altering a DFS directory's Initial Container and
    Initial Object ACLs as well as its regular ACL; see the <emphasis>IBM AFS/DFS Migration Toolkit Administration Guide and
    Reference</emphasis>. You cannot copy ACLs between AFS and DFS directories, because they use different ACL formats. The
    <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> command interpreter ignores the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="bold">-if</emphasis> flags if you include them when copying AFS ACLs. <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>copyacl</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs copyacl</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_647">
      <title>To copy an ACL between directories</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have the <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on
          the source ACL and the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission on each
          destination ACL. To identify the source directory by naming a file in it, you must also have the <emphasis
          role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) permission on the source ACL. If necessary, issue the
          <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying
          ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ578" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl</emphasis> command to copy a source ACL to the ACL
          on one or more destination directories. (The command appears here on two lines only for legibility.) <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl -fromdir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>source directory</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-todir</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>destination directory</replaceable>&gt;+  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis>]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">co</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">copyacl</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-fromdir</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the source directory from which to copy the ACL. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the
                current working directory. If this argument names a file, the ACL is copied from its directory.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-todir</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names each destination directory to which to copy the source ACL. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative
                to the current working directory. Filenames are not acceptable.</para>

                <para>Specify the read/write path to each directory, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to change a
                read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period before the cell name at the
                pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>). For further discussion of the
                concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link linkend="HDRWQ209">The Rules of Mount
                Point Traversal</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Completely overwrites each destination directory's ACL with the source ACL.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example copies the ACL from the current working directory's <emphasis role="bold">notes</emphasis>
      subdirectory to the <emphasis role="bold">plans</emphasis> subdirectory. The issuer does not include the <emphasis
      role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag, so the entry for user <emphasis role="bold">pat</emphasis> remains on the <emphasis
      role="bold">plans</emphasis> directory's ACL although there is no corresponding entry on the <emphasis
      role="bold">notes</emphasis> directory's ACL.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs la notes plans</emphasis>
   Access list for notes is
   Normal permissions:
      terry rlidwka
      smith rl
      jones rl
   Access list for plans is
   Normal permissions:
      terry rlidwk
      pat rlidwk
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs copyacl notes plans</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs la notes plans</emphasis>
   Access list for notes is
   Normal permissions:
      terry rlidwka
      smith rl
      jones rl
   Access list for plans is
   Normal permissions:
      terry rlidwka
      pat rlidwk
      smith rl
      jones rl
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>removing obsolete AFS IDs</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>removing</primary>

        <secondary>obsolete AFS IDs from ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>AFS UID</primary>

        <secondary>removing obsolete from ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>AFS GID</primary>

        <secondary>removing obsolete from ACL</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACL</primary>

        <secondary>cleaning</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ579">
    <title>Removing Obsolete AFS IDs from ACLs</title>

    <para>When you remove a user or group entry from the Protection Database, the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
    command displays the user's AFS UID (or group's AFS GID) in ACL entries, rather than the name. In the following example, user
    <emphasis role="bold">terry</emphasis> has an ACL entry for the group <emphasis role="bold">terry:friends</emphasis> (AFS GID
    -567) on her home directory in the ABC Corporation cell, and then removes the group from the Protection Database.</para>

    <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl /afs/abc.com/usr/terry</emphasis>
   Access list for /afs/abc.com/usr/terry is
   Normal permissions:
     terry:friends rlik
     system:anyuser l
     terry rlidwka
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts delete terry:friends</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl /afs/abc.com/usr/terry</emphasis>
   Access list for /afs/abc.com/usr/terry is
   Normal permissions:
     -567 rlik
     system:anyuser l
     terry rlidwka
</programlisting>

    <para>Leaving AFS IDs on ACLs serves no function, because the ID no longer corresponds to an active user or group. Furthermore,
    if the ID is ever assigned to a new user or group, then the new possessor of the ID gains access that the owner of the directory
    actually intended for the previous possessor. (Reusing AFS IDs is not recommended precisely for this reason.)</para>

    <para>To remove obsolete AFS UIDs from ACLs, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs cleanacl</emphasis> command. <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fs cleanacl</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>fs commands</primary>

        <secondary>cleanacl</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_649">
      <title>To clean obsolete AFS IDs from an ACL</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have the <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permission
          on each directory for which you are cleaning the ACL. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis>
          command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs cleanacl</emphasis> command to remove entries for obsolete AFS IDs.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs cleanacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">cl</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">cleanacl</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">dir/file path</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names each directory for which to clean the ACL. If this argument names a file, its directory's ACL is
                cleaned. Omit this argument to clean the current working directory's ACL.</para>

                <para>Specify the read/write path to each directory, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to change a
                read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period before the cell name at the
                pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>). For further discussion of the
                concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link linkend="HDRWQ209">The Rules of Mount
                Point Traversal</link>.</para>

                <para>You can also use the following notation on its own or as part of a pathname:</para>

                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(A single period). If used by itself, cleans the current working directory's ACL.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">..</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(Two periods). If used by itself, cleans the ACL on the current working directory's parent
                      directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>

                  <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>(The asterisk). Cleans the ACL of each of the subdirectories in the current working directory. However,
                      if you use the asterisk and there are obsolete AFS IDs on any directory's ACL, the following error message
                      appears for every file in the directory: <programlisting>
   fs: 'filename': Not a directory
</programlisting></para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If there are obsolete AFS IDs on a directory, the command interpreter displays its cleaned ACL under the following
      header.</para>

      <programlisting>
   Access list for directory is now
</programlisting>

      <para>If a directory's ACL has no obsolete AFS IDs on it, the following message appears for each.</para>

      <programlisting>
   Access list for directory is fine.
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ580">
    <title>How AFS Interprets the UNIX Mode Bits</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>UNIX</primary>

      <secondary>mode bits, interpretation in AFS</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>UFS</primary>

      <secondary>mode bits, interpretation in AFS</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>mode bits (UNIX)</primary>

      <secondary>interpretation in AFS</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Although AFS uses ACLs to protect file data rather than the mode bits that UFS uses, it does not ignore the mode bits
    entirely. When you issue the <emphasis role="bold">chmod</emphasis> command on an AFS file or directory, AFS changes the bits
    appropriately. To change a file's mode bits, you must have the AFS <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis
    role="bold">write</emphasis>) permission on the ACL of the file's directory. To change a directory's mode bits, you must have
    the <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>), <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis
    role="bold">insert</emphasis>), and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permissions on
    its ACL.</para>

    <para>AFS also uses the UNIX mode bits as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It uses the initial bit to determine the element's type. This is the bit that appears first in the output from the
        <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command and shows the hyphen (<emphasis role="bold">-</emphasis>) for a file or the
        letter <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> for a directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It does not use any of the mode bits on a directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For a file, the first (owner) set of bits interacts with the ACL entries that apply to the file in the following way:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the first <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> mode bit is not set, no one (including the owner) can read the
              file, no matter what permissions they have on the ACL. If the bit is set, users also need the <emphasis
              role="bold">r</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">read</emphasis>) and <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on
              the ACL of the file's directory to read the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the first <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> mode bit is not set, no one (including the owner) can modify the
              file. If the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> bit is set, users also need the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the file's directory to modify the file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>There is no ACL permission directly corresponding to the <emphasis role="bold">x</emphasis> mode bit, but to
              execute a file stored in AFS, the user must also have the <emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> permissions on the ACL of the file's directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>