<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ419">
  <title>Configuring Client Machines with the package Program</title>

  <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program automates many aspects of the client configuration process. With the
  <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program, you can easily configure the local disk of numerous clients by defining global
  configuration files. <indexterm>
      <primary>configuring</primary>

      <secondary>local disk of client with package</secondary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
      <primary>client</primary>

      <secondary>configuring local disk with package</secondary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
      <primary>disk</primary>

      <secondary>local</secondary>

      <see>local disk</see>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
      <primary>local disk</primary>

      <secondary>configuring on client, using package</secondary>
    </indexterm></para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ420">
    <title>Summary of Instructions</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to perform the following tasks by using the indicated commands or instructions in a prototype
    file:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="37*" />

        <colspec colwidth="63*" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Configure a client machine's local disk</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define directory</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis> [update_code] directory owner group mode_bits</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define file</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> [update_code] file source_file [owner group mode_bits]</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define symbolic link</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis> [update_code] link actual_file [owner group mode_bits]</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define block special device</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis> device_name major_device_number minor_device_number owner group
            mode_bits</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define character special device</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> device_name major_device_number minor_device_number owner group
            mode_bits</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define socket</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis> socket_name [owner group mode_bits]</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ422">
    <title>Using the package Program</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>prototype file</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>prototype files in package</primary>

      <secondary>about</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program uses system-independent <emphasis>prototype files</emphasis> to
    define a standard disk configuration; a prototype file indicates which files reside on the local client disk, which files are
    links into AFS, etc. The prototype files are then compiled into <emphasis>configuration files</emphasis> for each different
    system type.</para>

    <para>Not all client machines have the same configuration. If desired, you can create different prototype files for different
    client functions (print server, regular client, etc.).</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program compares the contents of a local client disk with the configuration
    file. If there are any differences, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program makes the necessary updates to the
    local disk by copying the files from AFS onto the disk. The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program can also be
    configured to delete files that are not part of the system configuration or automatically reboot the client when certain files
    (such as the <emphasis role="bold">dkload</emphasis> file) have been updated.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program does require that you take some time to prepare the prototype files,
    but it provides the following benefits: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You no longer need to configure each machine individually; the prototype configuration file applies to all
          machines.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can change the configuration of machines simply by changing the prototype file and rebooting the clients.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disk organization is uniform across a set of machines.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The configuration files serve as a record of files on the disk and symbolic links into AFS.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_494">
      <title>Using Package on File Server Machines</title>

      <para>While the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program was designed for use on client machines, it can also be used
      to configure a file server machine's disk. However, if any of the files referred to in a configuration file reside in volumes
      on the file server, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program cannot access the volumes during reboot (and until
      the File Server process and Volume Server process start up again).</para>

      <para>Since the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program aborts when it cannot access a file, you need to eliminate
      references to files in AFS that reside in volumes on the file server machine. Because of these constraints, the remainder of
      this chapter assumes the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program is being used for client configurations.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ423">
    <title>Package Overview</title>

    <para>There are three main steps to follow before running the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Preparing function-specific <emphasis>prototype files</emphasis> (and any included <emphasis>library
          files</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Modifying the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> and compiling
          prototype files into system-specific <emphasis>configuration files</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Modifying client machines to run the appropriate <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> configuration file
          automatically.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>The following sections summarize these steps.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_496">
      <title>Preparing Prototype Files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>preparing prototype files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>prototype files in package</primary>

        <secondary>preparing</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Begin by listing the different functions or roles client machines perform and the local disk configurations that support
      those functions. Example roles include a standard client that provides AFS access, a print server that drives a printer, and a
      backup machine on which you issue commands from the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> suite. Create a different
      <emphasis>prototype file</emphasis> for each role.</para>

      <para>A prototype file defines the disk configuration that supports a specific role. Usually, prototype files are
      function-specific, but system independent; system-specific values can be defined using variables and library files. Then, when
      you modify a variable or library file, the change gets propagated to all appropriate clients when the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program is invoked.</para>

      <para>Methods for building flexible prototype files that are easy to maintain are presented in <link
      linkend="HDRWQ427">Example Prototype and Library Files</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ424">
      <title>Compiling Prototype Files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>compiling prototype files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>configuration files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>configuration files</primary>

        <secondary>package program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Prototype files are usually system-independent, but can include <computeroutput>ifdef</computeroutput> statements to
      satisfy the needs of different system types. The prototype files are compiled to generate operating-system specific versions.
      During compilation, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program selects the definitions suitable for each system type
      and replaces any variables with actual values. These compiled, machine-specific files are called <emphasis>configuration
      files</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Prototype files are compiled using a standard-type <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file, as described in <link
      linkend="HDRWQ438">The Package Makefile File</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_498">
      <title>Preparing Clients</title>

      <para>Once system-specific configuration files exist, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program is ready to run on
      the clients. You must first make the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary available and specify the correct
      configuration file.</para>

      <para>Modify the clients as described below: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a <emphasis role="bold">.package</emphasis> file in the root ( <emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis> )
            directory of each client's local disk that defines the default configuration file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/package</emphasis>) available
            on the local disk.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Modify the machine's initialization file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/rc</emphasis> or equivalent) to include a
            call to the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>These steps are discussed more completely in <link linkend="HDRWQ447">Modifying Client Machines</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ425">
    <title>The package Directory Structure</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>directory structure</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>This section assumes that the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>-related files have been installed in three
    subdirectories of the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname/<emphasis role="bold">wsadmin</emphasis> directory:
    <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis>, as
    recommended in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>These directories contain several sample prototype, library, and configuration files, which can help to clarify how the
    <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program works. However, they are not necessarily suitable for use in your cell; you
    must modify them for your needs.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ426">
      <title>The src directory</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis> directory contains some sample prototype files (used to build the configuration
      files), the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file used to build them, and the resulting compiled configuration
      files.</para>

      <para>Prototype files have names of the form function.<emphasis role="bold">proto</emphasis>. For example, a <emphasis
      role="bold">minimal.proto</emphasis> file defines the minimum set of library files need to run AFS and a<emphasis
      role="bold">staff.dkload.proto</emphasis> file defines a client configuration that uses the a dynamic kernel loading program.
      Prototype files can also contain definitions for system administrative files, such as a <emphasis
      role="bold">hosts.equiv</emphasis> file.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file is used to compile the system-independent prototype files into
      system-specific configuration files. To learn how to modify this file for use in your cell, see <link linkend="HDRWQ438">The
      Package Makefile File</link>.</para>

      <para>Configuration files are the compiled version of the prototype files and are named function<emphasis
      role="bold">.</emphasis>sysname. Configuration files also appear in the <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis> subdirectory,
      which the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program accesses when configuring disks.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_501">
      <title>The lib directory</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis> directory contains many of the example library files referred to in prototype
      files. For example, the <emphasis role="bold">base.generic</emphasis> file is a system-independent file which includes a
      definition of the cell name, system options, and variables; these are used to set the owner, group, and mode_bits fields in
      the file and the symbolic link definitions.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_502">
      <title>The etc directory</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis> directory contains the system-specific configuration files built from the
      prototype files in the <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis> subdirectory. The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program
      uses the configuration files in the <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis> directory to configure disks.</para>

      <para>Some of the example files include <emphasis role="bold">minimal</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">staff</emphasis>
      prototype files compiled for different system types.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ427">
    <title>Example Prototype and Library Files</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>example prototype files</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>prototype files in package</primary>

      <secondary>examples</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>A prototype file is a template that defines the configuration of a client's local disk. Prototype files are usually
    function-specific (for example, a backup machine, print server, etc.) but system-independent. Prototype files support the use of
    <computeroutput>ifdef</computeroutput> statements and variables, so you can include system-specific definitions. The actual
    system-specific configuration file is generated when the prototype file is compiled.</para>

    <para>The components defined in a prototype file can include the directories, files, symbolic links, block special devices,
    character special devices and sockets that need to reside on a client's local disk in order for it to perform a specific role,
    such as a print server or backup machine. Thus, we recommend that you construct a unique prototype file for each different
    client function.</para>

    <para>To make the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program more effective and easy to maintain, create prototype files
    that are modular and generic, instead of specific, by using library files and variables: <indexterm>
        <primary>library files in package</primary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>library files</secondary>
      </indexterm> <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>By creating general-purpose library files, you can include the same library file in many prototype files. Thus, you
          can make global configuration changes by modifying a single library file; you do not need to modify each prototype
          file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Variables enable you to change definitions simply by changing the variable's value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ428">
      <title>An Example Prototype File</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>prototype files for package</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following is part of an example prototype file that contains the minimum definitions necessary to run AFS. A similar
      file called <emphasis role="bold">minimal.proto</emphasis> can reside in your <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis>
      subdirectory. As recommended, this prototype file references library files and does not include actual definitions.</para>

      <programlisting>
            .
            .
   # Package prototype for a minimal configuration.
   # Base components
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/base.generic
   # Machine-specific components
   %ifdef rs_aix42
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.readonly
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.AFS
   %endif rs_aix42
   %ifdef alpha_dux40
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/alpha_dux40.readonly
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/alpha_dux40.AFS
   %endif alpha_dux40
   %ifdef sun4x_56
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.readonly
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.AFS
   %endif sun4x_56
            .
            .
</programlisting>

      <para>In the previous example, the first uncommented line includes the <emphasis role="bold">/lib/base.generic</emphasis>
      library file. This library file can contain definitions appropriate for many prototype files; the <emphasis
      role="bold">base.generic</emphasis> library file can also be included in other prototype files, like a <emphasis
      role="bold">staff.proto</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">backup.proto</emphasis> file. An example library file appears in
      the following section.</para>

      <para>Note that system-specific definitions are permitted through the use of <computeroutput>ifdef</computeroutput> statements
      and variables (for example, <computeroutput>${wsadmin}</computeroutput> is used to specify pathnames). Thus, the same
      prototype file can be used to configure a machine running AIX 4.2 or Solaris 2.6, even though they require different files,
      directories, symbolic links and devices.</para>

      <para>In the next uncommented lines of this example, the administrator has constructed different library files for different
      system types. Each of these is compiled into unique configuration files. For instance, the following lines in this prototype
      file tell the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program to use the library files <emphasis
      role="bold">lib/rs_aix42.readonly</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">lib/rs_aix42.AFS</emphasis> for the configuration file
      when the value rs_aix42 has been declared. (The system-type definition is declared in the <emphasis
      role="bold">Makefile</emphasis>; see <link linkend="HDRWQ438">The Package Makefile File</link>.)</para>

      <programlisting>
   %ifdef rs_aix42
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.readonly
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.AFS
   %endif rs_aix42
</programlisting>

      <para>Similarly, the following lines tell the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program to use the library files
      <emphasis role="bold">lib/sun4x_56.readonly</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">lib/sun4x_56.AFS</emphasis> when the value
      sun4x_56 has been declared.</para>

      <programlisting>
   %ifdef sun4x_56
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.readonly
   %include ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.AFS
   %endif sun4x_56
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_505">
      <title>Example Library File</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>example library files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>library files in package</primary>

        <secondary>examples</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>preparing prototype files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>library files for package</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following is part of an example library file for basic configuration definitions. A similar file, called <emphasis
      role="bold">base.generic</emphasis>, can reside in your <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis> subdirectory. Note that
      configurations are defined using standard <computeroutput>ifdef</computeroutput> statements.</para>

      <programlisting>
            .
            .
   #
   # Base package definitions.
   #
   %ifndef      cell
   %define      cell    abc.com
   %endif       cell
   %ifndef      sys
   %include /etc/package.sys
   %endif       sys
   %define      ${name}         ${name}
   %define      ${cpu}          ${cpu}
   %define      ${sys}          ${sys}
   %define      ${dept}         ${dept}
   %define      ${hostname}     ${hostname}
   %ifdef       rs_aix42
   %    define  AIX
   %    define  rootlinks
   %ifndef      noafsd 
   %    define  afsd
   %endif       noafsd
   %endif       rs_aix42
            .
            .
   #
   # Some definitions to handle common combinations of owner, group,
   # and protection fields.
   #
   %define      rzmode          root wheel 600
   %define      usermode        root wheel 666
   %define      systemmode      root wheel 644
   %define      diskmode        root wheel 644
   %define      ptymode         root wheel 666
   %define      ttymode         root wheel 666
            .
            .
   %define aix_rootbin     root bin
   %define aix_rootprintq  root printq
   %define aix_rootstaff   root staff
   %define aix_rootsys     root system
   %define aix_binbin      bin bin
   %define aix_binmail     bin mail
   %define aix_binsys      bin system
   %define aix_addsys      adduser system
   %define aix_romode      444
   %define aix_loginmode   544
   %define aix_usermode    666
   %define aix_systemmode  644
   %define aix_textmode    644
   %define aix_rwmode1     660
   %define aix_allrugw     664
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example library file uses <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>-specific syntax to define files,
      directories, sockets, etc. Each line, called a <emphasis>configuration file instruction</emphasis>, defines a specific
      component of disk configuration. The proper syntax for these instructions is briefly described in <link
      linkend="HDRWQ429">Package Configuration File Instruction Syntax</link>; see the reference page for the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> configuration file in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Reference</emphasis> for detailed
      descriptions.</para>

      <para>In this example, the library file contains instructions specific to the configuration of an <emphasis
      role="bold">rs_aix42</emphasis> machine. You can have similar library files in your <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis>
      subdirectory.</para>

      <programlisting>
            .
            .
   #
   # Generic configuration for an AFS rs_aix42 machine.
   #
   D    /                                       ${treemode}
   D    /afs
   FAQ  /unix          ${machine}/unix.std      ${binmode}
   LA   /unix.std       /unix
   D    /bin                                    ${treemode}
   F    /bin/as         ${machine}              ${binmode}
   F    /bin/ld         ${machine}              ${binmode}
   F    /bin/nm         ${machine}              ${binmode}
   FO   /bin/login      ${afstest}              ${suidmode}
            .
            .
   FAQ  /usr/vice/etc/ThisCell  ${common}/etc/ThisCell ${textmode}
   FQ   /usr/vice/etc/afsd      ${afstest}/root.client ${binmode}
   FA   /usr/vice/etc/bos       ${afstest}/bin/bos     ${binmode}
   FA   /usr/vice/etc/fs        ${afstest}/bin/fs      ${binmode}
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ429">
    <title>Package Configuration File Instruction Syntax</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>configuration file instructions</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>configuration file</primary>

      <secondary>instructions for package program</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Within a library file, configuration file instructions are used to define the specific disk configuration. Each
    instruction can be used to define a file, directory, socket, or device on the client machine. The syntax for each valid
    instruction type is described briefly here; detailed descriptions of the fields appear in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Command
    Reference Manual</emphasis>. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis> defines a directory</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> defines a file</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis> defines a link</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis> defines a block special device</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> defines a character special device</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis> defines a socket</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <note>
      <para>Each configuration instruction must appear on a single, unbroken line. Instructions sometimes appear here on multiple
      lines only for legibility.</para>

      <para>The configuration file must be completely correct. If there are any syntax errors or incorrect values, the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> command interpreter exits without executing any instruction.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ430">
      <title>Local Files versus Symbolic Links</title>

      <para>You can take advantage of the AFS by keeping the number of files on the local client disk to a minimum; instead, create
      symbolic links that point into AFS. This can improve machine performance by allowing more space for caching and
      swapping.</para>

      <para>Some files, however, must reside on the local disk, as described below. Create these files in the prototype or library
      files using the <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> (file) instruction, not the <emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis> (symbolic
      link) instruction.</para>

      <para>The following types of files must reside on the local disk of all AFS clients: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Boot sequence files executed before the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> program runs.</para>

            <para>Until <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> runs and initializes the Cache Manager, AFS is inaccessible from the
            client. Any files that are executed before the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> program runs must reside on the
            local client disk.</para>

            <para>For example, on a machine that uses a disk cache, the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice/cache</emphasis> directory
            must exist when you bring up the Cache Manager, so that there is a location to create cache files. The binary files
            <emphasis role="bold">/etc/mount</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/etc/umount</emphasis> must be available on the
            local disk as the machine boots in order to mount the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice/cache</emphasis> directory.</para>

            <para>In addition, certain UNIX files, such as initialization files (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/rc</emphasis> or
            equivalent) and file system mapping files (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/fstab</emphasis> or equivalent), must reside on
            the local disk.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Diagnostic and recovery files</para>

            <para>Certain commands can be used to diagnose and recover from problems caused by a file server outage. It is best to
            keep copies of the binaries for these commands on the local disk. For example, store the <emphasis
            role="bold">bos</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> binaries in the <emphasis
            role="bold">/usr/vice/etc</emphasis> directory on the local disk, as well as in the <emphasis
            role="bold">/usr/afsws</emphasis> directory (which in the conventional configuration is a symbolic link into AFS). Then,
            set PATH variables so that the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws</emphasis> directory appears before the <emphasis
            role="bold">/usr/vice/etc</emphasis> directory. Thus, even if users cannot access AFS (for example, due to a file server
            outage) they can still access copies of the <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis>
            binaries in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice/etc</emphasis> directory on the local disk.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Files in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice</emphasis> directory</para>

            <para>The contents of the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice</emphasis> directory, including the cache files in the
            <emphasis role="bold">cache</emphasis> subdirectory and the configuration files in the <emphasis
            role="bold">etc</emphasis> subdirectory, must reside on the local disk. For a description of the files in the directory,
            see <link linkend="HDRWQ391">Configuration and Cache-Related Files on the Local Disk</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>D instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>D instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining directory in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>directory</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ431">
      <title>Defining a Directory</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis> instruction defines a directory to be created on the local disk. If a symbolic
      link, file, or other element on the local disk has the same name, it is replaced with a directory. If the directory already
      exists, its owner, group, and mode bits are changed if necessary to conform with the instruction.</para>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a directory:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>[update_code]   directory   owner   group   mode_bits
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example defines the <emphasis role="bold">/usr</emphasis> directory:</para>

      <programlisting>
   D /usr root wheel 755
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>F instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>F instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining file in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>file</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ432">
      <title>Defining a File</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> instruction defines a file to be created on the local disk. The source file can
      reside in either AFS or the local disk.</para>

      <para>If a file of this name already exists, then it is updated with (overwritten by) the source file, unless the <emphasis
      role="bold">I</emphasis> update code is specified. If a symbolic link or directory of this name exists, the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program replaces it with the source file.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Some files must reside on the local disk; they cannot be symbolic links. See <link linkend="HDRWQ430">Local Files
        versus Symbolic Links</link>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a file:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>[update_code]   file   source_file  [owner   group   mode_bits]
</programlisting>

      <para>An example which creates/updates the file <emphasis role="bold">/bin/grep</emphasis> on the local disk, using <emphasis
      role="bold">/afs/abc.com/rs_aix42/bin/grep</emphasis> as the source:</para>

      <programlisting>
   F /bin/grep /afs/abc.com/rs_aix42 root wheel 755
</programlisting>

      <para>In the following example, two update codes are used, and the <emphasis>owner</emphasis>, <emphasis>group</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>mode_bits</emphasis> slots are left empty, so that the disk file adopts the source file's values for those
      slots.</para>

      <programlisting>
   FAQ /usr/vice/etc/ThisCell /afs/abc.com/common/etc/ThisCell
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>L instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>L instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining symbolic link in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>symbolic link</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ433">
      <title>Defining a Symbolic Link</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis> instruction defines a symbolic link to be created on the local disk. The symbolic
      link can point to the AFS file system or the local disk. If the identical symbolic link already exists, the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program does nothing. However, if an element of the same name exists on the disk as a file or
      directory, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program replaces the element with a symbolic link.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Some files must reside on the local disk; they cannot be symbolic links. See <link linkend="HDRWQ430">Local Files
        versus Symbolic Links</link>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a symbolic link:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis>[update_code]  link actual_file  [owner   group   mode_bits]
</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>Do not create a symbolic link to a file whose name begins with the number sign (<emphasis role="bold">#</emphasis>) or
        percent sign (<emphasis role="bold">%</emphasis>). The Cache Manager interprets such a link as a mount point to a regular or
        Read/Write volume, respectively.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The following example creates a symbolic link from the <emphasis role="bold">/etc/ftpd</emphasis> directory on the local
      disk to the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com/hp_ux110/etc/ftpd</emphasis> file in AFS. Since the <emphasis>owner</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>group</emphasis> and <emphasis>mode_bits</emphasis> fields are empty, the symbolic link adopts values for those
      fields from the actual file:</para>

      <programlisting>
   L /etc/ftpd /afs/abc.com/hp_ux110 
</programlisting>

      <para>This example uses the <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis> update code:</para>

      <programlisting>
   LA /etc/printcap /afs/abc.com/common/etc/printcap.remote 
               root wheel 644
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>B instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>B instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining block special device in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>block special device</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ434">
      <title>Defining a Block Special Device</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis> instruction defines a block special device, which is a device that handles data
      in units of multibyte blocks, such as a disk. If a device of the same name already exists, the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program replaces it with the specified block device.</para>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a block special device (it appears on two lines here only for
      legibility):</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis> device_name   major_device_number   minor_device_number  \
      owner   group   mode_bits
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example defines a disk called <emphasis role="bold">/dev/hd0a</emphasis> to have major and minor device
      numbers <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis>:</para>

      <programlisting>
   B /dev/hd0a 1 0 root wheel 644
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>C instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>C instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining character special device in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>character special device</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ435">
      <title>Defining a Character Special Device</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> instruction defines a character special device, which is device that handles data
      in units of a single character at a time, such as a terminal or tty. If a device of the same name already exists, the
      <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program replaces it with the specified character device.</para>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a character special device (it appears here on two lines only for
      legibility):</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> device_name   major_device_number   minor_device_number  \
      owner   group   mode_bits
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example defines the tty called <emphasis role="bold">/dev/ttyp5</emphasis> with major and minor device
      numbers <emphasis role="bold">6</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">5</emphasis>:</para>

      <programlisting>
   C /dev/ttyp5 6 5 root wheel 666
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>S instruction</primary>

        <secondary>package configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>S instruction in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package</primary>

        <secondary>defining socket in configuration file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>socket</primary>

        <secondary>creating with package</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ436">
      <title>Defining a Socket</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis> instruction defines a socket, which is communications device for UDP and TCP/IP
      connections. If a socket of the same name already exists, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program replaces
      it.</para>

      <para>Use the following instruction to define a socket:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis>   socket_name   [owner   group   mode_bits]
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example defines a socket called <emphasis role="bold">/dev/printer</emphasis>:</para>

      <programlisting>
   S /dev/printer root wheel 777
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ437">
    <title>Constructing Prototype and Library Files</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>constructing prototype and library files</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>prototype files in package</primary>

      <secondary>constructing</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>library files in package</primary>

      <secondary>constructing</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>This section describes the general steps required to create <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> prototype and library
    files. Refer to the previous sections for guidelines, and the files in your <emphasis role="bold">wsadmin</emphasis> directory
    for examples. The construction of prototype and library files is different for each cell.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_515">
      <title>To construct a prototype file and its component library files</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Determine where the three <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>-related subdirectories (<emphasis
          role="bold">src</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis>) reside in your
          cell's file tree; the following instructions assume they were loaded into the <emphasis
          role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin</emphasis> directory, as described in the IBM AFS Quick
          Beginnings.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Decide how many different functions you want client machines in your cell to perform. We recommend that you
          construct a separate prototype file for each function. Common functions include: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Standard workstation: provides users with access to files in AFS</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Printer server: drives a printer; can be combined with "staff" functionality</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Backup machine: performs backups of AFS volumes to tape by running the AFS Backup System software</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Determine the minimum functionality needed for all clients (such as AFS setup) and place these generic definitions
          in one or more library files.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For each type of client (printer server, backup machine, and so on), place all system-independent definitions in one
          file, and all operating-system dependent definitions in another file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ438">
    <title>The Package Makefile File</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>Makefile</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Makefile for package</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>files</primary>

      <secondary>package Makefile</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Once you have created the appropriate prototype and library files, you must compile the prototype for each system type.
    The result is a system-specific configuration file.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file defines the prototype and library files used and the order of
    compilation. We recommend that you create your <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file by modifying the example provided
    with the AFS distribution, as described in this section. In the conventional configuration, it is located at <emphasis
    role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin/src/Makefile</emphasis>.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_517">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>The following list summarizes the sections in the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> <emphasis
      role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file, identifying each by the header name that begins the section. More detailed descriptions
      follow. <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">CONFIG=</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Lists all of the configuration files to be created and defines which prototype files are compiled for which
              system types. See <link linkend="HDRWQ439">The CONFIG Section</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">BASE_LIBS=</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Lists the pathnames of all operating-system- and function independent library files included in any prototype
              files. See <link linkend="HDRWQ440">The BASE_LIBS Section</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">MACHINE_LIBS=</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Lists the pathnames of all operating-system-specific library files included in any prototype files. See <link
              linkend="HDRWQ441">The MACHINE_LIBS Section</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">LIBS=</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A one-line instruction that defines LIBS as the combination of BASE_LIBS and MACHINE_LIBS. See <link
              linkend="HDRWQ442">The LIBS Section</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">.SUFFIXES</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Defines all of the suffixes that can appear on a prototype or configuration file. See <link
              linkend="HDRWQ443">The .SUFFIXES Section</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <para>Finally, the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file contains a set of instructions that the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program follows to generate configuration files. It is not generally necessary to alter this
      section. See <link linkend="HDRWQ444">The Makefile Instructions Section</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ439">
      <title>The CONFIG Section</title>

      <para>As mentioned, a configuration file is a prototype file that has been compiled for a specific operating system type. The
      CONFIG section of the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file defines the prototype files to compile for each system
      type. The resulting compiled file is a system-specific configuration file.</para>

      <para>Study the following example taken from the sample <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file. Configuration files
      are defined by specifying the prototype-system combination as prototype_file<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>sysname. Note
      that it is not necessary to generate a configuration file for each prototype-system type combination.</para>

      <programlisting>
   #Makefile...
   #    (C) Copyright IBM Corporation 1999
   #    Licensed Materials - Property of IBM
   #    All Rights Reserved.
   #
   CONFIG = \
            staff.rs_aix42 \
            staff.alpha_dux40 \
            staff.xdm.alpha_dux40 \
            staff.sun4x_56 \
            staff.hp_ux110 \
            minimal.rs_aix42 \
            minimal.alpha_dux40 \
            minimal.hp_ux110 \
            minimal.sun4x_56
</programlisting>

      <para>An entry in the CONFIG section has the following format: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The first part of the entry defines the prototype file and is the same as the prototype file name (without the
            <emphasis role="bold">.proto</emphasis> extension). The second part of the entry indicates the system type for which the
            prototype file is to be compiled. A complete list of these suffixes is in the .SUFFIXES section of the <emphasis
            role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ443">The .SUFFIXES Section</link>. This
            prototype_file<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>sysname definition becomes the name of the compiled configuration
            file.</para>

            <para>For example, <emphasis role="bold">staff.rs_aix42</emphasis> indicates that the <emphasis
            role="bold">staff.proto</emphasis> file is compiled for machines running AIX 4.2. The resulting compiled configuration
            file is called <emphasis role="bold">staff.rs_aix42</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Each configuration file must appear on a separate line.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A backslash must follow the CONFIG= header and every name but the last one. A backslash must also appear on blank
            lines.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ440">
      <title>The BASE_LIBS Section</title>

      <para>This section defines the complete pathname of all system- and function-independent library files included in any
      prototype file. (System-specific library files are defined in the MACHINE_LIBS section). The pathnames can include the
      ${wsadmin} variable, whose value is supplied on the <emphasis role="bold">make</emphasis> command line.</para>

      <para>You must include all of the library files referred to in your prototype files; files included but not used are
      ignored.</para>

      <para>Study the following example. Note that the all entries (except the last one) must be followed by a backslash.</para>

      <programlisting>
   BASE_LIBS = \
           ${wsadmin}/src/admin \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/devel \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/base.generic
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ441">
      <title>The MACHINE_LIBS Section</title>

      <para>This section lists the complete pathname of all operating-system-specific library files included in prototype files.
      (System- and function-independent library files are defined in the BASE_LIBS section.)</para>

      <para>Study the following example. Note that in this example, library files were grouped by operating-system type. Again, all
      lines (except the last one) must be followed by a backslash, the ${wsadmin} variable is allowed, and files included but not
      used are ignored.</para>

      <programlisting>
   MACHINE_LIBS = \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.generic \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.generic.dev \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.readonly \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.readwrite \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rt_aix42.generic.printer \
    \
    .
    .
           ${wsadmin}/lib/alpha_dux40.AFS \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/hp_ux110.AFS \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.AFS \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.AFS
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ442">
      <title>The LIBS Section</title>

      <para>This section contains only one instruction, which indicates that LIBS is defined as the combination of MACHINE_LIBS and
      BASE_LIBS. Insert a blank line after the line to separate this section from the next.</para>

      <programlisting>
   LIBS = ${MACHINE_LIBS} ${BASE_LIBS}
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ443">
      <title>The .SUFFIXES Section</title>

      <para>This section lists the valid machine-type suffixes. This list includes system types currently supported for AFS. Unused
      suffixes are ignored.</para>

      <programlisting>
   .SUFFIXES: .rs_aix42 \
              .alpha_dux40 \
              .proto \
              .sun4x_56 \
              .i386_linux22 \
              .hp_ux110
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ444">
      <title>The Makefile Instructions Section</title>

      <para>The remainder of the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file controls how the <emphasis
      role="bold">package</emphasis> program generates configuration files.</para>

      <para>Study the following instructions; it is assumed that you are familiar with programming and <emphasis
      role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> concepts.</para>

      <programlisting>
   #The following appear on a single line each in the actual file
   .proto.rs_aix42: ;  mpp -Dwsadmin=${wsadmin} -Dsys=rs_aix42  
                           -Dname=$* $*.proto &gt; $@
   .proto.alpha_dux40: ; mpp -Dwsadmin=${wsadmin} -Dsys=alpha_dux40 
                           -Dname=$* $*.proto &gt; $@
   .proto.sun4x_56:  ; mpp -Dwsadmin=${wsadmin} -Dsys=sun4x_56 
                           -Dname=$* $*.proto &gt; $@
   .proto.hp_ux110:  ; mpp -Dwsadmin=${wsadmin} -Dsys=hp_ux110  
                           -Dname=$* $*.proto &gt; $@
   all: ${CONFIG}
   ${CONFIG}: ${LIBS}
   system: install
   install: ${CONFIG}
           cp ${CONFIG} ${wsadmin}/etc
   clean:
           rm -f ${CONFIG} *.BAK *.CKP
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ445">
    <title>Modifying the Makefile</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>modifying the Makefile</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Makefile for package</primary>

      <secondary>modifying</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>modifying</primary>

      <secondary>package Makefile</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Modify the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> files when you <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add a new prototype file (function<emphasis role="bold">.proto</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add a new system type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add new library files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The following sections provide brief examples of how to modify the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file for
    these reasons.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_525">
      <title>Adding a New Prototype File</title>

      <para>When you create a new prototype file, add the file name and each system type for which it is to be built into the CONFIG
      section of the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file.</para>

      <para>For example, to add a function<emphasis role="bold">.proto</emphasis> file for <emphasis
      role="bold">alpha_dux40</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">hp_ux110</emphasis>, add the following entries to the CONFIG
      section:</para>

      <programlisting>
   CONFIG = \
   ...
           function.alpha_dux40 \
           function.hp_ux110 \
   ...
</programlisting>

      <para>If you have added new library files for this prototype function, add those to the MACHINE_LIBS section.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_526">
      <title>Adding a New System Type</title>

      <para>For each prototype file that you want to build for the new system type, add an entry to the CONFIG section. Also add any
      new libraries to the MACHINE_LIBS section, and the new system type to the .SUFFIXES section.</para>

      <para>The following example shows the modifications appropriate when building the <emphasis role="bold">staff</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="bold">minimal</emphasis> prototype files for this new system type.</para>

      <programlisting>
   CONFIG = \
   ...
           staff.sysname \
           minimal.sysname \
   ...
</programlisting>

      <para>If you have created corresponding library files for this new machine type, add them to the MACHINE_LIBS section.</para>

      <programlisting>
   MACHINE_LIBS = \
   ...
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sysname.generic \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sysname.generic.dev \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sysname.readonly \
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sysname.readwrite \
   ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Add the new system type to the SUFFIXES section.</para>

      <programlisting>
   .SUFFIXES: ...\
            .sysname \
   ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Add a line to build the configuration files for this system in the section with the rest of the commands to build
      configuration files:</para>

      <programlisting>
   .proto.sysname: ; mpp -Dwsadmin=${wsadmin} \
   -Dsys=sysname  -Dname=$* $*.proto &gt; $
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_527">
      <title>Adding New Library Files</title>

      <para>If you added a new library file for each system type, sysname<emphasis
      role="bold">.</emphasis><emphasis>library_file</emphasis>, add these files to the MACHINE_LIBS section of the <emphasis
      role="bold">Makefile</emphasis>.</para>

      <programlisting>
   MACHINE_LIBS = \
   ...
           ${wsadmin}/lib/rs_aix42.library_file \
   ...
           ${wsadmin}/lib/alpha_dux40.library_file \
   ...
           ${wsadmin}/lib/sun4x_56.library_file \
   ...
</programlisting>

      <para>If you added a new library file that is common to all system types, library_file, add this only to the BASE_LIBS
      section:</para>

      <programlisting>
   BASE_LIBS = \
   ...
           ${wsadmin}/lib/library_file \
   ...
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ446">
    <title>Compiling Prototype Files</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>compiling</primary>

      <secondary>package prototype file</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>compiling prototype files</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program generates configuration files and installs them in the <emphasis
    role="bold">etc</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis> subdirectories of the directory designated as <emphasis
    role="bold">wsadmin=</emphasis> on the <emphasis role="bold">make</emphasis> command line. Recompile whenever you modify a
    prototype or library file.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_529">
      <title>To compile prototype files</title>

      <note>
        <para>These instructions assume that you store your <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>-related files in the <emphasis
        role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin</emphasis> directory. If you use a different directory,
        substitute its name for <emphasis role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin</emphasis>.</para>
      </note>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you have all privileges in the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis
          role="bold">/wsadmin</emphasis> directory and in its <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis>, <emphasis
          role="bold">lib</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis> subdirectories. If necessary, issue the <emphasis
          role="bold">fs</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">listacl</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [dir/file path]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Change to the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin/src</emphasis>
          subdirectory. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">cd /afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin/src</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create a backup copy of the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file included in the AFS distribution.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">cp  Makefile Makefile.example</emphasis> 
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Modify the CONFIG, BASE_LIBS and MACHINE_LIBS sections of the <emphasis role="bold">Makefile</emphasis> file, as
          described in <link linkend="HDRWQ439">The CONFIG Section</link>, <link linkend="HDRWQ440">The BASE_LIBS Section</link>,
          and <link linkend="HDRWQ441">The MACHINE_LIBS Section</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compile the prototype files using the <emphasis role="bold">make</emphasis> command.</para>

          <para>Use the <emphasis role="bold">wsadmin=</emphasis> argument to specify the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>
          directory. This becomes the value of the ${wsadmin} variable in the prototype and the library files.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program generates configuration files and installs them in the
          <emphasis role="bold">etc</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis> subdirectories of the directory designated
          as <emphasis role="bold">wsadmin=</emphasis>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">make system wsadmin=/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin</emphasis>
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ447">
    <title>Modifying Client Machines</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package directory</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>client</primary>

      <secondary>modifying to run package</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>package</primary>

      <secondary>modifying clients to run</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>modifying</primary>

      <secondary>clients to run package</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To prepare a client to run the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program automatically, perform the following
    steps. The instructions are generic because they do not refer to system-specific configuration files. If desired, you can invoke
    the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program with specific arguments, as described in the <emphasis>IBM AFS
    Administration Reference</emphasis>. <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify the configuration file to use.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">.package</emphasis> file in the client machine's root ( <emphasis
          role="bold">/</emphasis>) directory is redirected as an argument to the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> command;
          the <emphasis role="bold">.package</emphasis> file specifies which configuration file the <emphasis
          role="bold">package</emphasis> program uses.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary available to the client, either by copying it to the local
          disk, or by creating a symbolic link to AFS. <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>A symbolic link saves local disk space. However, when the file server machine that houses it is down, the
                <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary is inaccessible.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Keeping the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary on the local disk enables you to run the <emphasis
                role="bold">package</emphasis> program even if file server is down. However, a file server machine outage usually
                makes it difficult to run the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program because most configuration file
                instructions refer to files in AFS. A local copy of the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary can be
                useful if the files referred to in instructions are in replicated volumes.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Modify the client machine's initialization file to invoke the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program at
          reboot. The client machine reboots a second time if the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program updates any files
          marked with the <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update code.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_531">
      <title>To prepare a client machine to run the package program</title>

      <para>Repeat these instructions on every client that runs the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program.</para>

      <para>These instructions assume that the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> configuration files (created when the
      prototype files were compiled) reside in the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis
      role="bold">/wsadmin/etc</emphasis> directory. <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by
            issuing the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create the <emphasis role="bold">.package</emphasis> file in the root ( <emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>)
            directory and specify the name of the prototype file to use. Do not include the system-type suffix (such as <emphasis
            role="bold">.rs_aix42</emphasis>); the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program automatically determines the
            correct machine type. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">echo "/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin/etc/</emphasis>config_file<emphasis
                  role="bold">" &gt;&gt; /.package</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

            <para>For example, to configure a machine for a member of staff machine (assuming the proper prototype file had been
            defined and compiled for the system type), the appropriate command is:</para>

            <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">echo "/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/wsadmin/etc/staff" &gt;&gt; /.package</emphasis>
</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary available on the local disk as <emphasis
            role="bold">/etc/package</emphasis>. Issue one of the following commands, depending on whether you want to create a file
            or create a symbolic link.</para>

            <para>To store the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary locally, enter the following command:</para>

            <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">cp /afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>sysname<emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/etc/package   /etc/package</emphasis>
</programlisting>

            <para>To create a symbolic link, enter the following command:</para>

            <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">ln -s /afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>sysname<emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/etc/package   /etc/package</emphasis>
</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add the following lines to the appropriate initialization file, after the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis>
            command is invoked. If this is a file server machine, the <emphasis role="bold">bosserver</emphasis> command must follow
            the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> command.</para>

            <para>Using the <emphasis role="bold">-v</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-c</emphasis> options is recommended. The
            <emphasis role="bold">-v</emphasis> flag produces a detailed trace, and the <emphasis role="bold">-c</emphasis> option
            appends the system type to the base name of the configuration file. See the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
            Reference</emphasis> for a description of other options.</para>

            <note>
              <para>Replace the <emphasis role="bold">shutdown</emphasis> command with a similar command if it is not appropriate
              for rebooting your machine.</para>
            </note>

            <programlisting>
   if [ -f /etc/package ]; then
           if [ -f /.package ]: then
                   /etc/package -v -c `cat /.package` &gt;/dev/console
           else
                   /etc/package -v &gt;/dev/console
   fi
   case $? in
   0)
           echo "Package completed successfully" &gt;/dev/console 2&gt;&amp;1
           date &gt;/dev/console 2&gt;&amp;1
           ;;
   4)
           echo "Rebooting to restart system" &gt;/dev/console 2&gt;&amp;1
           echo &gt;/fastboot
           shutdown
           ;;
   *)
           echo "Update failed, continuing anyway" &gt;/dev/console 2&gt;&amp;1
           ;;
   esac
   fi
</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ448">
    <title>Running the package program</title>

    <para>After you have created and compiled prototype files and modified client machines, you are ready to run the <emphasis
    role="bold">package</emphasis> program. It is probably most convenient to run the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>
    program automatically at reboot by invoking it in the machine's AFS initialization file, but you can also issue the command at
    the command shell prompt.</para>

    <para>The configuration file must be completely correct. If there are any syntax errors or incorrect values, the program exits
    without executing any instruction. To check the configuration file, issue the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> command
    with the <emphasis role="bold">-noaction</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis> flags at the command shell
    prompt. They display a list of potential problems without actually executing instructions.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program follows these general rules. Complete explanations are in <link
    linkend="HDRWQ429">Package Configuration File Instruction Syntax</link>. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program does not delete any files from the disk unless the <emphasis
          role="bold">R</emphasis> update code was specified in the prototype file. If the <emphasis role="bold">R</emphasis> update
          code is associated with the parent directory, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program removes anything from
          the local disk directory that is not specified in the configuration file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Local files are updated only if they are out of date. For each <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> instruction in the
          configuration file, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program compares the time of the local file with the
          indicated source file. If the source file is newer than the local, the file is updated.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When the initialization file is modified as recommended in <link linkend="HDRWQ447">Modifying Client
          Machines</link>, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program reboots the workstation automatically if any files
          marked with the <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update code are updated, and if the <emphasis
          role="bold">package</emphasis> program has been invoked from the initialization file. When a file marked with the
          <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update code is changed, the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program exits with
          status code 4, causing a reboot (as directed in the initialization file). Files that require a reboot before changes are
          recognized (such as the operating system kernel and <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice/etc/CellServDB</emphasis> files) must
          be marked with a <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update code in the configuration file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program copies the configuration file it has just used to <emphasis
          role="bold">/etc/package.</emphasis>sysname, where sysname reflects this machine's system type. The <emphasis
          role="bold">package</emphasis> command interpreter consults this file if you do not provide a configuration file name. To
          be sure that it configures the local disk as you wish, review its contents.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_533">
      <title>To invoke the package program by rebooting</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Recommended)</emphasis> Verify the following: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">/.package</emphasis> file identifies the desired configuration file</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary is available as <emphasis
                role="bold">/etc/package</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The initialization file is properly modified to invoke the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program
                automatically</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reboot the machine, using the appropriate command. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">shutdown</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>package</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>package command</primary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_534">
      <title>To invoke the package program directly (without rebooting)</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Verify the following: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">/.package</emphasis> file identifies the desired configuration file</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> binary is available as <emphasis
                role="bold">/etc/package</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The initialization file is properly modified to invoke the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program
                automatically</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>base name of configuration file</replaceable>&gt;]  \
    [<emphasis role="bold">-fullconfig</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>full name of configuration file, or stdin for standard input</replaceable>&gt;]  \
    [<emphasis role="bold">-overwrite</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-noaction</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis>]  [<emphasis
                role="bold">-silent</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-rebootfiles</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the full pathname of the configuration file to use, ending in the file's base name, which omits
                  the suffix that indicates the machine type. The <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program knows how to
                  determine a machine's type, and automatically selects the appropriate version of the base file name. An example of
                  the proper value for this argument is <emphasis role="bold">staff</emphasis> rather than <emphasis
                  role="bold">staff.rs_aix42</emphasis>. You can also have the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program
                  refer to <emphasis role="bold">/.package</emphasis> to learn the configuration file name by providing the
                  following value:</para>

                  <para><emphasis role="bold">`cat /.package`</emphasis></para>

                  <para>Use either this argument or the <emphasis role="bold">-fullconfig</emphasis> argument.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-fullconfig</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the full name of the configuration file to use, complete with the machine-type extension. Examples
                  are <emphasis role="bold">staff.rs_aix42</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">minimal.hp_ux110</emphasis>
                  files.</para>

                  <para>Another possibility is the string <emphasis role="bold">stdin</emphasis>, which indicates that the issuer is
                  providing configuration information via the standard input stream, either as a piped file or by typing the
                  configuration file at the keyboard. Press &lt;<emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-d</emphasis>&gt; to conclude the
                  input.</para>

                  <para>Use either this argument or the <emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis> argument.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-overwrite</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Overwrite elements on the local disk with the source version indicated in the configuration file, even if
                  the first (owner) <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>) mode bit is turned
                  off on the local disk copy of the file. Files protected by the <emphasis role="bold">I</emphasis> update code are
                  not overwritten; see the definition for the <emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis> instruction.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-noaction</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Displays on the standard output stream a trace of potential problems in running the command, rather than
                  actually running it. If the <emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis> flag is added, the trace also notes the
                  actions the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program attempts.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-silent</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Explicitly invokes the default level of tracing, which includes only a list of problems encountered while
                  executing the command.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Produces a detailed trace of the program's actions on the standard output stream. The trace records on the
                  transfer and ownership/mode bit setting of each element in the configuration file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-rebootfiles</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Prevents the overwrite of any element marked with the <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update-mode code in
                  the configuration file. This effectively prevents the machine from rebooting automatically again when the
                  <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> program is invoked from an initialization file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you think files marked with the <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis> update code were updated, reboot the machine.
          This reboot does not occur automatically.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>