<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ323">
  <title>Monitoring and Auditing AFS Performance</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>scout program</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>monitoring</primary>

    <secondary>file server processes with scout</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>monitoring</primary>

    <secondary>file server processes with afsmonitor</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>monitoring</primary>

    <secondary>Cache Manager processes with afsmonitor</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>monitoring</primary>

    <secondary>Cache Manager performance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

    <secondary>monitoring performance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>client machine</primary>

    <secondary>monitoring performance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>file system</primary>

    <secondary>monitoring activity</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>AFS comes with three main monitoring tools: <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program, which monitors and gathers statistics on File Server
        performance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command suite, which traces Cache Manager operations in detail.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program, which monitors and gathers statistics on both the File Server
        and the Cache Manager.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>AFS also provides a tool for auditing AFS events on file server machines running AIX.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ324">
    <title>Summary of Instructions</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to perform the following tasks by using the indicated commands:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="70*" />

        <colspec colwidth="30*" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Initialize the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Display information about a trace log</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Display information about an event set</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Change the size of a trace log</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Set the state of an event set</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Dump contents of a trace log</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Clear a trace log</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Initialize the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ326">
    <title>Using the scout Program</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>scout program</primary>

      <secondary>features summarized</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program monitors the status of the File Server process running on file server
    machines. It periodically collects statistics from a specified set of File Server processes, displays them in a graphical
    format, and alerts you if any of the statistics exceed a configurable threshold.</para>

    <para>More specifically, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program includes the following features. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can monitor, from a single location, the File Server process on any number of server machines from the local and
          foreign cells. The number is limited only by the size of the display window, which must be large enough to display the
          statistics.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can set a threshold for many of the statistics. When the value of a statistic exceeds the threshold, the
          <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program highlights it (displays it in reverse video) to draw your attention to it.
          If the value goes back under the threshold, the highlighting is deactivated. You control the thresholds, so highlighting
          reflects what you consider to be a noteworthy situation. See <link linkend="HDRWQ332">Highlighting Significant
          Statistics</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program alerts you to File Server process, machine, and network outages
          by highlighting the name of each machine that does not respond to its probe, enabling you to respond more quickly.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can set how often the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program collects statistics from the File Server
          processes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ327">
      <title>System Requirements</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>requirements</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>requirements</primary>

        <secondary>scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>curses graphics utility</primary>

        <secondary>scout program requirements</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>setting terminal type</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>setting</primary>

        <secondary>terminal type for scout</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>terminal type</primary>

        <secondary>setting for scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dumb terminal</primary>

        <secondary>use in scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program runs on any AFS client machine that has access to the <emphasis
      role="bold">curses</emphasis> graphics package, which most UNIX distributions include as a standard utility. It can run on
      both dumb terminals and under windowing systems that emulate terminals, but the output looks best on machines that support
      reverse video and cursor addressing. For best results, set the TERM environment variable to the correct terminal type, or one
      with characteristics similar to the actual ones. For machines running AIX, the recommended TERM setting is <emphasis
      role="bold">vt100</emphasis>, assuming the terminal is similar to that. For other operating systems, the wider range of
      acceptable values includes <emphasis role="bold">xterm</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">xterms</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">vt100</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">vt200</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">wyse85</emphasis>.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>privilege</primary>

        <secondary>required for scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>No privilege is required to run the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program, so any user who can access the
      directory where its binary resides (the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/bin</emphasis> directory in the conventional
      configuration) can use it. The program's probes for collecting statistics do not impose a significant burden on the File
      Server process, but you can restrict its use by placing the binary file in a directory with a more restrictive access control
      list (ACL).</para>

      <para>Multiple instances of the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program can run on a single client machine, each over
      its own dedicated connection (in its own window). It must run in the foreground, so the window in which it runs does not
      accept further input except for an interrupt signal.</para>

      <para>You can also run the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program on several machines and view its output on a single
      machine, by opening telnet connections to the other machines from the central one and initializing the program in each remote
      window. In this case, you can include the <emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis
      role="bold">scout</emphasis> command to make the name of each remote machine appear in the <emphasis>banner line</emphasis> at
      the top of the window displaying its output. See <link linkend="HDRWQ330">The Banner Line</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ328">
      <title>Using the -basename argument to Specify a Domain Name</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>basename</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>basenames in scout program</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>As previously mentioned, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program can monitor the File Server process on any
      number of file server machines. If all of the machines belong to the same cell, then their hostnames probably all have the
      same domain name suffix, such as <emphasis role="bold">abc.com</emphasis> in the ABC Corporation cell. In this case, you can
      use the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> command, which has
      several advantages: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can omit the domain name suffix as you enter each file server machine's name on the command line. The
            <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program automatically appends the domain name to each machine's name, resulting
            in a fully-qualified hostname. You can omit the domain name suffix even when you don't include the <emphasis
            role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument, but in that case correct resolution of the name depends on the state of your
            cell's naming service at the time of connection.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The machine names are more likely to fit in the appropriate column of the display without having to be truncated
            (for more on truncating names in the display column, see <link linkend="HDRWQ331">The Statistics Display
            Region</link>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The domain name appears in the banner line at the top of the display window to indicate the name of the cell you
            are monitoring.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ329">
      <title>The Layout of the scout Display</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>display layout</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>display layout in scout program window</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program can display statistics either in a dedicated window or on a plain
      screen if a windowing environment is not available. For best results, use a window or screen that can print in reverse video
      and do cursor addressing.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program screen has three main regions: the <emphasis>banner line</emphasis>,
      the <emphasis>statistics display region</emphasis> and the <emphasis>probe/message</emphasis> line. This section describes
      their contents, and graphic examples appear in <link linkend="HDRWQ336">Example Commands and Displays</link>.</para>

      <sect3 id="HDRWQ330">
        <title>The Banner Line</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>scout program</primary>

          <secondary>banner line</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>banner line on the scout program screen</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>By default, the string <computeroutput>scout</computeroutput> appears in the banner line at the top of the window or
        screen, to indicate that the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program is running. You can display two additional types
        of information by include the appropriate option on the command line: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Include the <emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis> flag to display the local machine's name in the banner line.
              This is particularly useful when you are running the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program on several
              machines but displaying the results on a single machine.</para>

              <para>For example, the following banner line appears when you run the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program
              on the machine <emphasis role="bold">client1.abc.com</emphasis> and use the<emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis>
              flag:</para>

              <programlisting>
   [client1.abc.com] scout
</programlisting>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Include the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument to display the specified cell domain name in the
              banner line. For further discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ328">Using the -basename argument to Specify a Domain
              Name</link>.</para>

              <para>For example, if you specify a value of <emphasis role="bold">abc.com</emphasis> for the <emphasis
              role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument, the banner line reads:</para>

              <programlisting>
   scout for abc.com
</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="HDRWQ331">
        <title>The Statistics Display Region</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>scout program</primary>

          <secondary>statistics displayed</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>statistics display by scout program</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>The statistics display region occupies most of the window and is divided into six columns. The following list
        describes them as they appear from left to right in the window. <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><computeroutput>Conn</computeroutput></term>

              <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Conn statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>Displays the number of RPC connections open between the File Server process and client machines. This number
                normally equals or exceeds the number in the fourth <computeroutput>Ws</computeroutput> column. It can exceed the
                number in that column because each user on the machine can have more than one connection open at once, and one
                client machine can handle several users.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><computeroutput>Fetch</computeroutput></term>

              <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Fetch statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>Displays the number of fetch-type RPCs (fetch data, fetch access list, and fetch status) that the File Server
                process has received from client machines since it started. It resets to zero when the File Server process
                restarts.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><computeroutput>Store</computeroutput></term>

              <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Store statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>Displays the number of store-type RPCs (store data, store access list, and store status) that the File Server
                process has received from client machines since it started. It resets to zero when the File Server process
                restarts.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><computeroutput>Ws</computeroutput></term>

              <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>active</primary>

                  <secondary>clients statistic from scout program</secondary>
                </indexterm>

                <indexterm>
                  <primary>client machines statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Ws statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>Displays the number of client machines (workstations) that have communicated with the File Server process
                within the last 15 minutes (such machines are termed <emphasis>active</emphasis>). This number is likely to be
                smaller than the number in the <computeroutput>Conn</computeroutput>) column because a single client machine can
                have several connections open to one File Server process.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">[Unlabeled column]</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Displays the name of the file server machine on which the File Server process is running. It is 12 characters
                wide. Longer names are truncated and an asterisk (<computeroutput>*</computeroutput>) appears as the last character
                in the name. If all machines have the same domain name suffix, you can use the <emphasis
                role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument to decrease the need for truncation; see <link linkend="HDRWQ328">Using
                the -basename argument to Specify a Domain Name</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput></term>

              <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>disk partition</primary>

                  <secondary>monitoring usage of</secondary>
                </indexterm>

                <indexterm>
                  <primary>monitoring</primary>

                  <secondary>disk usage with scout program</secondary>
                </indexterm>

                <indexterm>
                  <primary>scout program</primary>

                  <secondary>monitoring disk usage</secondary>
                </indexterm>

                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Disk attn statistic from scout program</primary>
                </indexterm>

                <para>Displays the number of kilobyte blocks available on up to 26 of the file server machine's AFS server
                (<emphasis role="bold">/vicep</emphasis>) partitions. The display for each partition has the following format:
                <programlisting>
   partition_letter:free_blocks
</programlisting></para>

                <para>For example, <computeroutput>a:8949</computeroutput> indicates that partition <emphasis
                role="bold">/vicepa</emphasis> has 8,949 KB free. If the window is not wide enough for all partition entries to
                appear on a single line, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program automatically stacks the partition
                entries into subcolumns within the sixth column.</para>

                <para>The label on the <computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput> column indicates the threshold value at which
                entries in the column become highlighted. By default, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program highlights
                a partition that is over 95% full, in which case the label is as follows:</para>

                <programlisting>
   Disk attn: &gt; 95% used
</programlisting>

                <para>For more on this threshold and its effect on highlighting, see <link linkend="HDRWQ332">Highlighting
                Significant Statistics</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>

        <para>For all columns except the fifth (file server machine name), you can use the <emphasis
        role="bold">-attention</emphasis> argument to set a threshold value above which the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis>
        program highlights the statistic. By default, only values in the fifth and sixth columns ever become highlighted. For
        instructions on using the <emphasis role="bold">-attention</emphasis> argument, see <link linkend="HDRWQ332">Highlighting
        Significant Statistics</link>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_368">
        <title>The Probe Reporting Line</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>scout program</primary>

          <secondary>probe reporting line</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>message line in scout program display</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>The bottom line of the display indicates how many times the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program has probed
        the File Server processes for statistics. The statistics gathered in the latest probe appear in the statistics display
        region. By default, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program probes the File Servers every 60 seconds, but you can
        use the <emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> argument to specify a different probe frequency.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ332">
      <title>Highlighting Significant Statistics</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>highlighting in</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>highlighting statistics in scout display</primary>

        <secondary>use of reverse video</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>reverse video</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>reverse video</primary>

        <secondary>use in scout program display</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>To draw your attention to a statistic that currently exceed a threshold value, the <emphasis
      role="bold">scout</emphasis> program displays it in reverse video (highlights it). You can set the threshold value for most
      statistics, and so determine which values are worthy of special attention and which are normal.</para>

      <sect3 id="HDRWQ333">
        <title>Highlighting Server Outages</title>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>outages</primary>

          <secondary>monitoring with scout program</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>scout program</primary>

          <secondary>outages, monitoring</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>monitoring</primary>

          <secondary>outages with scout program</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>File Server</primary>

          <secondary>monitoring with scout program</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>file server machine</primary>

          <secondary>monitoring outages of</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>The only column in which you cannot control highlighting is the fifth, which identifies the file server machine for
        which statistics are displayed in the other columns. The <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program uses highlighting in
        this column to indicate that the File Server process on a machine fails to respond to its probe, and automatically blanks
        out the other columns. Failure to respond to the probe can indicate a File Server process, file server machine, or network
        outage, so the highlighting draws your attention to a situation that is probably interrupting service to users.</para>

        <para>When the File Server process once again responds to the probes, its name appears normally and statistics reappear in
        the other columns. If all machine names become highlighted at once, a possible network outage has disrupted the connection
        between the file server machines and the client machine running the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_371">
        <title>Highlighting for Extreme Statistic Values</title>

        <para>To set the threshold value for one or more of the five statistics-displaying columns, use the <emphasis
        role="bold">-attention</emphasis> argument. The threshold value applies to all File Server processes you are monitoring (you
        cannot set different thresholds for different machines). For details, see the syntax description in <link
        linkend="HDRWQ335">To start the scout program</link>.</para>

        <para>It is not possible to change the threshold values for a running <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program. Stop
        the current program and start a new one. Also, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program does not retain threshold
        values across restarts, so you must specify all thresholds every time you start the program.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ334">
      <title>Resizing the scout Display</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>display, resizing</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>window</primary>

        <secondary>resizing scout display</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>resizing</primary>

        <secondary>scout display</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Do not resize the display window while the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program is running. Increasing the
      size does no harm, but the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program does not necessarily adjust to the new dimensions.
      Decreasing the display's width can disturb column alignment, making the display harder to read. With any type of resizing, the
      <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program does not adjust the display in any way until it displays the results of the
      next probe.</para>

      <para>To resize the display effectively, stop the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program, resize the window and then
      restart the program. Even in this case, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program's response depends on the accuracy
      of the information it receives from the display environment. Testing during development has shown that the display environment
      does not reliably provide information about window resizing. If you use the X windowing system, issuing the following sequence
      of commands before starting the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program (or placing them in the shell initialization
      file) sometimes makes it adjust properly to resizing.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">set noglob</emphasis>
   % <emphasis role="bold">eval '/usr/bin/X11/resize'</emphasis> 
   % <emphasis role="bold">unset noglob</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>starting</primary>

        <secondary>scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>starting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>initializing</primary>

        <secondary>scout program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>command syntax</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>scout</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ335">
      <title>To start the scout program</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open a dedicated command shell. If necessary, adjust it to the appropriate size.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> command to start the program. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis>]  <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>FileServer name(s) to monitor</replaceable>&gt;+  \
            [<emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>base server name</replaceable>&gt;]  \
            [<emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>poll frequency, in seconds</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis
                role="bold">-host</emphasis>]  \
            [<emphasis role="bold">-attention</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>specify attention (highlighting) level</replaceable>&gt;+]  \
            [<emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>turn debugging output on to the named file</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is an optional string that accommodates the command's use of the AFS command parser. It can be omitted and
                  ignored.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Identifies each File Server process to monitor, by naming the file server machine it is running on. Provide
                  fully-qualified hostnames unless the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument is used. In that case,
                  specify only the initial part of each machine name, omitting the domain name suffix common to all the machine
                  names.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the domain name suffix common to all of the file server machines named by the <emphasis
                  role="bold">-server</emphasis> argument. For discussion of this argument's effects, see <link
                  linkend="HDRWQ328">Using the -basename argument to Specify a Domain Name</link>.</para>

                  <para>Do not include the period that separates the domain suffix from the initial part of the machine name, but do
                  include any periods that occur within the suffix itself. (For example, in the ABC Corporation cell, the proper
                  value is <emphasis role="bold">abc.com</emphasis>, not <emphasis role="bold">.abc.com</emphasis>.)</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sets the frequency, in seconds, of the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program's probes to File
                  Server processes. Specify an integer greater than 0 (zero). The default is 60 seconds.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Displays the name of the machine that is running the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program in the
                  display window's banner line. By default, no machine name is displayed.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-attention</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Defines the threshold value at which to highlight one or more statistics. You can provide the pairs of
                  statistic and threshold in any order, separating each pair and the parts of each pair with one or more spaces. The
                  following list defines the syntax for each statistic.<variablelist>
                      <indexterm>
                        <primary>scout program</primary>

                        <secondary>attention levels, setting</secondary>
                      </indexterm>

                      <indexterm>
                        <primary>highlighting statistics in scout display</primary>

                        <secondary>setting thresholds</secondary>
                      </indexterm>

                      <indexterm>
                        <primary>thresholds for statistics in scout display</primary>

                        <secondary>setting</secondary>
                      </indexterm>

                      <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role="bold">conn connections</emphasis></term>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Highlights the value in the <computeroutput>Conn</computeroutput> (first) column when the number of
                          connections that the File Server has open to client machines exceeds the connections value. The
                          highlighting deactivates when the value goes back below the threshold. There is no default
                          threshold.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>

                      <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role="bold">fetch fetch_RPCs</emphasis></term>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Highlights the value in the <computeroutput>Fetch</computeroutput> (second) column when the number
                          of fetch RPCs that clients have made to the File Server process exceeds the fetch_RPCs value. The
                          highlighting deactivates only when the File Server process restarts, at which time the value returns to
                          zero. There is no default threshold.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>

                      <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role="bold">store store_RPCs</emphasis></term>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Highlights the value in the <computeroutput>Store</computeroutput> (third) column when the number of
                          store RPCs that clients have made to the File Server process exceeds the store_RPCs value. The
                          highlighting deactivates only when the File Server process restarts, at which time the value returns to
                          zero. There is no default threshold.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>

                      <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role="bold">ws active_clients</emphasis></term>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Highlights the value in the <computeroutput>Ws</computeroutput> (fourth) column when the number of
                          active client machines (those that have contacted the File Server in the last 15 minutes) exceeds the
                          active_clients value. The highlighting deactivates when the value goes back below the threshold. There is
                          no default threshold.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>

                      <varlistentry>
                        <term><emphasis role="bold">disk percent_full % or disk min_blocks</emphasis></term>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Highlights the value for a partition in the <computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput> (sixth)
                          column when either the amount of disk space used exceeds the percentage indicated by thepercent_full
                          value, or the number of free KB blocks is less than the min_blocks value. The highlighting deactivates
                          when the value goes back below the percent_full threshold or above the min_blocks threshold.</para>

                          <para>The value you specify appears in the header of the sixth column following the string
                          <computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput>. The default threshold is 95% full.</para>

                          <para>Acceptable values for percent_full are the integers from the range <emphasis
                          role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) to <emphasis role="bold">99</emphasis>, and you must include the percent
                          sign to distinguish this statistic from a min_blocks value..</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist></para>

                  <para>The following example sets the threshold for the <computeroutput>Conn</computeroutput> column to 100, for
                  the <computeroutput>Ws</computeroutput> column to 50, and for the <computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput>
                  column to 75%. There is no threshold for the <computeroutput>Fetch</computeroutput> and
                  <computeroutput>Store</computeroutput> columns.</para>

                  <para><emphasis role="bold">-attention conn 100 ws 50 disk 75%</emphasis></para>

                  <para>The following example has the same affect as the previous one except that it sets the threshold for the Disk
                  attn column to 5000 free KB blocks:</para>

                  <para><emphasis role="bold">-attention disk 5000 ws 50 conn 100</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Enables debugging output and directs it into the specified file. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative
                  to the current working directory. By default, no debugging output is produced.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_374">
      <title>To stop the scout program</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>stopping</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter <emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-c</emphasis> in the display window. This is the proper interrupt signal even if the
          general interrupt signal in your environment is different.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ336">
      <title>Example Commands and Displays</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>scout program</primary>

        <secondary>examples (command and display)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>examples</primary>

        <secondary>scout program display</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>This section presents examples of the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program, combining different arguments and
      illustrating the screen displays that result.</para>

      <para>In the first example, an administrator in the ABC Corporation issues the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> command
      without providing any optional arguments or flags. She includes the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> argument because
      she is providing multiple machine names. She chooses to specify on the initial part of each machine's name even though she has
      not used the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument, relying on the cell's name service to obtain the
      fully-qualified name that the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program requires for establishing a connection.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">scout -server fs1 fs2</emphasis> 
</programlisting>

      <para><link linkend="FIGWQ337">Figure 2</link> depicts the resulting display. Notice first that the machine names in the fifth
      (unlabeled) column appear in the format the administrator used on the command line. Now consider the second line in the
      display region, where the machine name <computeroutput>fs2</computeroutput> appears in the fifth column. The
      <computeroutput>Conn</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>Ws</computeroutput> columns together show that machine <emphasis
      role="bold">fs2</emphasis> has 144 RPC connections open to 44 client machines, demonstrating that multiple connections per
      client machine are possible. The <computeroutput>Fetch</computeroutput> column shows that client machines have made 2,734,278
      fetch RPCs to machine <emphasis role="bold">fs2</emphasis> since the File Server process last started and the
      <computeroutput>Store</computeroutput> column shows that they have made 34,066 store RPCs.</para>

      <para>Six partition entries appear in the <computeroutput>Disk attn</computeroutput> column, marked
      <computeroutput>a</computeroutput> through <computeroutput>f</computeroutput> (for <emphasis role="bold">/vicepa</emphasis>
      through <emphasis role="bold">/vicepf</emphasis>). They appear on three lines in two subcolumns because of the width of the
      window; if the window is wider, there are more subcolumns. Four of the partition entries (<computeroutput>a</computeroutput>,
      <computeroutput>c</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>d</computeroutput>, and <computeroutput>e</computeroutput>) appear in
      reverse video to indicate that they are more than 95% full (the threshold value that appears in the <computeroutput>Disk
      attn</computeroutput> header).</para>

      <figure id="FIGWQ337" label="2">
        <title>First example scout display</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="scout1.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

      <para>In the second example, the administrator uses more of the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program's optional
      arguments. <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>She provides the machine names in the same form as in Example 1, but this time she also uses the <emphasis
            role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument to specify their domain name suffix, <emphasis role="bold">abc.com</emphasis>.
            This implies that the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program does not need the name service to expand the names
            to fully-qualified hostnames, but the name service still converts the hostnames to IP addresses.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>She uses the <emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis> flag to display in the banner line the name of the client
            machine where the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program is running.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>She uses the <emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> argument to changes the probing frequency from its
            default of once per minute to once every five seconds.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>She uses the <emphasis role="bold">-attention</emphasis> argument to changes the highlighting threshold for
            partitions to a 5000 KB minimum rather than the default of 95% full.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">scout -server fs1 fs2 -basename abc.com -host -frequency 5 -attention disk 5000</emphasis> 
</programlisting>

      <para>The use of optional arguments results in several differences between <link linkend="FIGWQ338">Figure 3</link> and <link
      linkend="FIGWQ337">Figure 2</link>. First, because the <emphasis role="bold">-host</emphasis> flag is included, the banner
      line displays the name of the machine running the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> process as
      <computeroutput>[client52]</computeroutput> along with the basename <computeroutput>abc.com</computeroutput> specified with
      the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument.</para>

      <para>Another difference is that two rather than four of machine <emphasis role="bold">fs2</emphasis>'s partitions appear in
      reverse video, even though their values are almost the same as in <link linkend="FIGWQ337">Figure 2</link>. This is because
      the administrator changed the highlight threshold to a 5000 block minimum, as also reflected in the <computeroutput>Disk
      attn</computeroutput> column's header. And while machine <emphasis role="bold">fs2</emphasis>'s partitions <emphasis
      role="bold">/vicepa</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/vicepd</emphasis> are still 95% full, they have more than 5000 free
      blocks left; partitions <emphasis role="bold">/vicepc</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/vicepe</emphasis> are highlighted
      because they have fewer than 5000 blocks free.</para>

      <para>Note also the result of changing the probe frequency, reflected in the probe reporting line at the bottom left corner of
      the display. Both this example and the previous one represent a time lapse of one minute after the administrator issues the
      <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> command. In this example, however, the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program
      has probed the File Server processes 12 times as opposed to once</para>

      <figure id="FIGWQ338" label="3">
        <title>Second example scout display</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="scout2.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

      <para>In <link linkend="FIGWQ339">Figure 4</link>, an administrator in the State University cell monitors three of that cell's
      file server machines. He uses the <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument to specify the <emphasis
      role="bold">stateu.edu</emphasis> domain name.</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">scout -server server2 server3 server4 -basename stateu.edu</emphasis> 
</programlisting>

      <figure id="FIGWQ339" label="4">
        <title>Third example scout display</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="scout3.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

      <para><link linkend="FIGWQ340">Figure 5</link> illustrates three of the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> program's
      features. First, you can monitor file server machines from different cells in a single display: <emphasis
      role="bold">fs1.abc.com</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">server3.stateu.edu</emphasis>, and <emphasis
      role="bold">sv7.def.com</emphasis>. Because the machines belong to different cells, it is not possible to provide the
      <emphasis role="bold">-basename</emphasis> argument.</para>

      <para>Second, it illustrates how the display must truncate machine names that do not fit in the fifth column, using an
      asterisk at the end of the name to show that it is shortened.</para>

      <para>Third, it illustrates what happens when the <emphasis role="bold">scout</emphasis> process cannot reach a File Server
      process, in this case the one on the machine <emphasis role="bold">sv7.def.com</emphasis>: it highlights the machine name and
      blanks out the values in the other columns.</para>

      <figure id="FIGWQ340" label="5">
        <title>Fourth example scout display</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="scout4.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ341">
    <title>Using the fstrace Command Suite</title>

    <para>This section describes the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> commands that system administrators employ to trace
    Cache Manager activity for debugging purposes. It assumes the reader is familiar with the Cache Manager concepts described in
    <link linkend="HDRWQ387">Administering Client Machines and the Cache Manager</link>.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command suite monitors the internal activity of the Cache Manager and enables
    you to record, or trace, its operations in detail. The operations, which are termed <emphasis>events</emphasis>, comprise the
    <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> <emphasis>event set</emphasis>. Examples of <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> events are
    fetching files and looking up information for a listing of files and subdirectories using the UNIX <emphasis
    role="bold">ls</emphasis> command.</para>

    <para>Following are the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> commands and their respective functions: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace apropos</emphasis> command provides a short description of commands.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command clears the trace log.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> command dumps the contents of the trace log.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace help</emphasis> command provides a description and syntax for commands.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command lists information about the trace log.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis> command lists information about the event set.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command changes the size of the trace log.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command sets the state of the event set.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ342">
      <title>About the fstrace Command Suite</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command suite replaces and greatly expands the functionality formerly
      provided by the <emphasis role="bold">fs debug</emphasis> command. Its intended use is to aid in diagnosis of specific Cache
      Manager problems, such as client machine hangs, cache consistency problems, clock synchronization errors, and failures to
      access a volume or AFS file. Therefore, it is best not to keep <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> logging enabled at all
      times, unlike the logging for AFS server processes.</para>

      <para>Most of the messages in the trace log correspond to low-level Cache Manager operations. It is likely that only personnel
      familiar with the AFS source code can interpret them. If you have an AFS source license, you can attempt to interpret the
      trace yourself, or work with the AFS Product Support group to resolve the underlying problems. If you do not have an AFS
      source license, it is probably more efficient to contact the AFS Product Support group immediately in case of problems. They
      can instruct you to activate <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> tracing if appropriate.</para>

      <para>The log can grow in size very quickly; this can use valuable disk space if you are writing to a file in the local file
      space. Additionally, if the size of the log becomes too large, it can become difficult to parse the results for pertinent
      information.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>cmfx trace log (fstrace)</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log from (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>cmfx</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>When AFS tracing is enabled, each time a <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event occurs, a message is written to the
      trace log, <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis>. To diagnose a problem, read the output of the trace log and analyze the
      operations executed by the Cache Manager. The default size of the trace log is 60 KB, but you can increase or decrease
      it.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>cm event set (fstrace)</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>event set (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>cm</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>To use the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command suite, you must first enable tracing and reserve, or
      allocate, space for the trace log with the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command. With this command, you can
      set the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set to one of three states to enable or disable tracing for the event set
      and to allocate or deallocate space for the trace log in the kernel: <variablelist>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>active</primary>

            <secondary>state of fstrace event set</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>inactive (state of fstrace event set)</primary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>dormant (state of fstrace event set)</primary>
          </indexterm>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>active</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Enables tracing for the event set and allocates space for the trace log.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>inactive</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Temporarily disables tracing for the event set; however, the event set continues to allocate space occupied by
              the log to which it sends data.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>dormant</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Disables tracing for the event set; furthermore, the event set releases the space occupied by the log to which
              it sends data. When the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set that sends data to the <emphasis
              role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> trace log is in this state, the space allocated for that log is freed or
              deallocated.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>persistent fstrace event set or trace log</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>persistence</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>event set (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>persistence</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Both event sets and trace logs can be designated as <emphasis>persistent</emphasis>, which prevents accidental resetting
      of an event set's state or clearing of a trace log. The designation is made as the kernel is compiled and cannot be
      changed.</para>

      <para>If an event set such as <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> is persistent, you can change its state only by including
      the <emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command. (That is,
      you cannot change its state along with the state of all other event sets by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace
      setset</emphasis> command with no arguments.) Similarly, if a trace log such as <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> is
      persistent, you can clear it only by including either the <emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="bold">-log</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command (you cannot clear it along
      with all other trace logs by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command with no arguments.)</para>

      <para>When a problem occurs, set the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set to active using the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command. When tracing is enabled on a busy AFS client, the volume of events being
      recorded is significant; therefore, when you are diagnosing problems, restrict AFS activity as much as possible to minimize
      the amount of extraneous tracing in the log. Because tracing can have a negative impact on system performance, leave <emphasis
      role="bold">cm</emphasis> tracing in the dormant state when you are not diagnosing problems.</para>

      <para>If a problem is reproducible, clear the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> trace log with the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command and reproduce the problem. If the problem is not easily reproduced, keep the
      state of the event set active until the problem recurs.</para>

      <para>To view the contents of the trace log and analyze the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> events, use the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> command to copy the content lines of the trace log to standard output (stdout) or to a
      file.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If a particular command or process is causing problems, determine its process id (PID). Search the output of the
        <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> command for the PID to find only those lines associated with the
        problem.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ343">
      <title>Requirements for Using the fstrace Command Suite</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>privilege</primary>

        <secondary>required for fstrace commands</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>privilege requirements</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Except for the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace help</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">fstrace apropos</emphasis>
      commands, which require no privilege, issuing the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> commands requires that the issuer
      be logged in as the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the local client machine. Before issuing an
      <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command, verify that you have the necessary privilege.</para>

      <para>The Cache Manager catalog must be in place so that logging can occur. The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis>
      command suite uses the standard UNIX catalog utilities. The default location is <emphasis
      role="bold">/usr/vice/etc/C/afszcm.cat</emphasis>. It can be placed in another directory by placing the file elsewhere and
      using the proper NLSPATH and LANG environment variables.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_379">
      <title>Using fstrace Commands Effectively</title>

      <para>To use <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> commands most effectively, configure them as indicated: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Store the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> binary in a local disk directory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you dump the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> log to a file, direct it to one on the local
            disk.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The trace can grow large in just a few minutes. Before attempting to dump the log to a local file, verify that you
            have enough room. Be particularly careful if you are using disk quotas on partitions in the local file system.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Attempt to limit Cache Manager activity on the AFS client machine other than the problem operation. This reduces
            the amount of extraneous data in the trace.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Activate the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> log for the shortest possibly period of time. If possible
            activate the trace immediately before performing the problem operation, deactivate it as soon as the operation
            completes, and dump the trace log to a file immediately.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If possible, obtain UNIX process ID (PID) of the command or program that initiates the problematic operation. This
            enables the person analyzing the trace log to search it for messages associated with the PID.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ344">
      <title>Activating the Trace Log</title>

      <para>To start Cache Manager tracing on an AFS client machine, you must first configure <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> kernel trace log using the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace
            setlog</emphasis> command</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set using the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis>
            command</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command sets the size of the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis>
      kernel trace log in kilobytes. The trace log occupies 60 kilobytes of kernel by default. If the trace log already exists, it
      is cleared when this command is issued and a new log of the given size is created. Otherwise, a new log of the desired size is
      created.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command sets the state of the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis>
      kernel event set. The state of the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set determines whether information on the events
      in that event set is logged.</para>

      <para>After establishing kernel tracing on the AFS client machine, you can check the state of the event set and the size of
      the kernel buffer allocated for the trace log. To display information about the state of the <emphasis
      role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis> command. To display information
      about the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> trace log, use the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command. See
      the instructions in <link linkend="HDRWQ346">Displaying the State of a Trace Log or Event Set</link>.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>setlog</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace setlog</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>configuring</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>configuring</primary>

        <secondary>trace log (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_381">
      <title>To configure the trace log</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command to set the size of the <emphasis
          role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> kernel trace log. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">-log</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>log_name</replaceable>&gt;+]  <emphasis
                role="bold">-buffersize</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>1-kilobyte_units</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example sets the size of the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> trace log to 80 KB.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog cmfx 80</emphasis> 
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>setset</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace setset</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>event set (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>setting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>setting</primary>

        <secondary>event set (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ345">
      <title>To set the event set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command to set the state of event sets. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>&gt;+] [<emphasis
                role="bold">-active</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-inactive</emphasis>]  \
                    [<emphasis role="bold">-dormant</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example activates the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset cm -active</emphasis>
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ346">
      <title>Displaying the State of a Trace Log or Event Set</title>

      <para>An event set must be in the <emphasis>active state</emphasis> to be included in the trace log. To display an event set's
      state, use the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis> command. To set its state, issue the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ345">To set the event set</link>.</para>

      <para>To display size and allocation information for the trace log, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace
      lslog</emphasis>command with the <emphasis role="bold">-long</emphasis> argument.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>lsset</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace lsset</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>event set (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>displaying state</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>displaying</primary>

        <secondary>state of event set (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_384">
      <title>To display the state of an event set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis> command to display the available event set and its state.
          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example displays the event set and its state on the local machine.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset cm</emphasis>
   Available sets:
   cm active
</programlisting>

      <para>The output from this command lists the event set and its states. The three event states for the <emphasis
      role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set are: <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">active</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Tracing is enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">inactive</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Tracing is disabled, but space is still allocated for the corresponding trace log (<emphasis
              role="bold">cmfx</emphasis>).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">dormant</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Tracing is disabled, and space is no longer allocated for the corresponding trace log (<emphasis
              role="bold">cmfx</emphasis>).Disables tracing for the event set.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>lslog</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace lslog</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>displaying state</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>displaying</primary>

        <secondary>state of trace log (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_385">
      <title>To display the log size</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command to display information about the kernel trace log.
          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>&gt;+]  [<emphasis
                role="bold">-log</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>log_name</replaceable>&gt;]  [<emphasis role="bold">-long</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example uses the <emphasis role="bold">-long</emphasis> flag to display additional information about the
      <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> trace log.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog cmfx -long</emphasis>
   Available logs:
   cmfx : 60 kbytes (allocated)
</programlisting>

      <para>The output from this command lists information on the trace log. When issued without the <emphasis
      role="bold">-long</emphasis> flag, the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command lists only the name of the log.
      When issued with the <emphasis role="bold">-long</emphasis> flag, the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command
      lists the log, the size of the log in kilobytes, and the allocation state of the log.</para>

      <para>There are two allocation states for the kernel trace log: <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>allocated</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Space is reserved for the log in the kernel. This indicates that the event set that writes to this log is either
              <emphasis>active</emphasis> (tracing is enabled for the event set) or <emphasis>inactive</emphasis> (tracing is
              temporarily disabled for the event set); however, the event set continues to reserve space occupied by the log to
              which it sends data.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>unallocated</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Space is not reserved for the log in the kernel. This indicates that the event set that writes to this log is
              <emphasis>dormant</emphasis> (tracing is disabled for the event set); furthermore, the event set releases the space
              occupied by the log to which it sends data.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ347">
      <title>Dumping and Clearing the Trace Log</title>

      <para>After the Cache Manager operation you want to trace is complete, use the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis>
      command to dump the trace log to the standard output stream or to the file named by the <emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis>
      argument. Or, to dump the trace log continuously, use the <emphasis role="bold">-follow</emphasis> argument (combine it with
      the <emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis> argument if desired). To halt continuous dumping, press an interrupt signal such as
      &lt;<emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-c</emphasis>&gt;.</para>

      <para>To clear a trace log when you no longer need the data in it, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis>
      command. (The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command also clears an existing trace log automatically when you
      use it to change the log's size.)</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>dump</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace dump</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>dumping</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>displaying</primary>

        <secondary>contents of trace log (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dumping</primary>

        <secondary>trace log contents (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_387">
      <title>To dump the contents of a trace log</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> command to dump trace logs. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>&gt;+]  [<emphasis
                role="bold">-follow</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>log_name</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                  [<emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>output_filename</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                  [<emphasis role="bold">-sleep</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>seconds_between_reads</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>At the beginning of the output of each dump is a header specifying the date and time at which the dump began. The number
      of logs being dumped is also displayed if the <emphasis role="bold">-follow</emphasis> argument is not specified. The header
      appears as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>
   AFS Trace Dump --
   Date: date time
   Found n logs.
</programlisting>

      <para>where <emphasis>date</emphasis> is the starting date of the trace log dump, <emphasis>time</emphasis> is the starting
      time of the trace log dump, and <emphasis>n</emphasis> specifies the number of logs found by the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace
      dump</emphasis> command.</para>

      <para>The following is an example of trace log dump header:</para>

      <programlisting>
   AFS Trace Dump --
   Date: Fri Apr 16 10:44:38 1999
   Found 1 logs.
</programlisting>

      <para>The contents of the log follow the header and are comprised of messages written to the log from an active event set. The
      messages written to the log contain the following three components: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The timestamp associated with the message (number of seconds from an arbitrary start point)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The process ID or thread ID associated with the message</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The message itself</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>A trace log message is formatted as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>
   time timestamp, pid pid:event message
</programlisting>

      <para>where <emphasis>timestamp</emphasis> is the number of seconds from an arbitrary start point, <emphasis>pid</emphasis> is
      the process ID number of the Cache Manager event, and <emphasis>event message</emphasis> is the Cache Manager event which
      corresponds with a function in the AFS source code.</para>

      <para>The following is an example of a dumped trace log message:</para>

      <programlisting>
   time 749.641274, pid 3002:Returning code 2 from 19
</programlisting>

      <para>For the messages in the trace log to be most readable, the Cache Manager catalog file needs to be installed on the local
      disk of the client machine; the conventional location is <emphasis role="bold">/usr/vice/etc/C/afszcm.cat</emphasis>. Log
      messages that begin with the string <computeroutput>raw op</computeroutput>, like the following, indicate that the catalog is
      not installed.</para>

      <programlisting>
   raw op 232c, time 511.916288, pid 0
   p0:Fri Apr 16 10:36:31 1999
</programlisting>

      <para>Every 1024 seconds, a current time message is written to each log. This message has the following format:</para>

      <programlisting>
   time timestamp, pid pid: Current time: unix_time
</programlisting>

      <para>where timestamp is the number of seconds from an arbitrary start point, pid is the process ID number, and unix_time is
      the standard time format since January 1, 1970.</para>

      <para>The current time message can be used to determine the actual time associated with each log message. Determine the actual
      time as follows: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Locate the log message whose actual time you want to determine.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Search backward through the dump record until you come to a current time message.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the current time message's <emphasis>timestamp</emphasis> is smaller than the log message's
            <emphasis>timestamp</emphasis>, subtract the former from the latter. If the current time message's
            <emphasis>timestamp</emphasis> is larger than the log message's <emphasis>timestamp</emphasis>, add 1024 to the latter
            and subtract the former from the result.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add the resulting number to the current time message's <emphasis>unix_time</emphasis> to determine the log
            message's actual time.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>Because log data is stored in a finite, circular buffer, some of the data can be overwritten before being read. If this
      happens, the following message appears at the appropriate place in the dump:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Log wrapped; data missing.
</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>If this message appears in the middle of a dump, which can happen under a heavy work load, it indicates that not all
        of the log data is being written to the log or some data is being overwritten. Increasing the size of the log with the
        <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command can alleviate this problem.</para>
      </note>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>clear</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fstrace clear</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>trace log (fstrace)</primary>

        <secondary>clearing contents</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>clearing</primary>

        <secondary>contents of trace log (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>removing</primary>

        <secondary>trace log contents (fstrace)</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_388">
      <title>To clear the contents of a trace log</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command to clear logs by log name or by event set.
          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis>  [<emphasis role="bold">-set</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>set_name</replaceable>&gt;+]  [<emphasis
                role="bold">-log</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>log_name</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example clears the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> log used by the <emphasis
      role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set on the local machine.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear cm</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example also clears the <emphasis role="bold">cmfx</emphasis> log on the local machine.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear cmfx</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fstrace commands</primary>

        <secondary>example of use</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ348">
      <title>Examples of fstrace Commands</title>

      <para>This section contains an extensive example of the use of the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> command suite,
      which is useful for gathering a detailed trace of Cache Manager activity when you are working with AFS Product Support to
      diagnose a problem. The Product Support representative can guide you in choosing appropriate parameter settings for the
      trace.</para>

      <para>Before starting the kernel trace log, try to isolate the Cache Manager on the AFS client machine that is experiencing
      the problem accessing the file. If necessary, instruct users to move to another machine so as to minimize the Cache Manager
      activity on this machine. To minimize the amount of unrelated AFS activity recorded in the trace log, place both the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> binary and the dump file must reside on the local disk, not in AFS. You must be logged in as
      the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> to issue <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> commands.</para>

      <para>Before starting a kernel trace, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset</emphasis> command to check the state of
      the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lsset cm</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>If tracing has not been enabled previously or if tracing has been turned off on the client machine, the following output
      is displayed:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Available sets:
   cm inactive
</programlisting>

      <para>If tracing has been turned off and kernel memory is not allocated for the trace log on the client machine, the following
      output is displayed:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Available sets:
   cm inactive (dormant)
</programlisting>

      <para>If the current state of the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set is <computeroutput>inactive</computeroutput>
      or <computeroutput>inactive (dormant)</computeroutput>, turn on kernel tracing by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace
      setset</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-active</emphasis> flag.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset cm -active</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>If tracing is enabled currently on the client machine, the following output is displayed:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Available sets:
   cm active
</programlisting>

      <para>If tracing is enabled currently, you do not need to use the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setset</emphasis> command. Do
      issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear</emphasis> command to clear the contents of any existing trace log, removing
      prior traces that are not related to the current problem.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace clear cm</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>After checking on the state of the event set, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog</emphasis> command with the
      <emphasis role="bold">-long</emphasis> flag to check the current state and size of the kernel trace log .</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace lslog cmfx -long</emphasis>
</programlisting>

      <para>If tracing has not been enabled previously or the <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> event set was set to
      <computeroutput>active</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>inactive</computeroutput> previously, output similar to the
      following is displayed:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Available logs:
   cmfx : 60 kbytes (allocated)
</programlisting>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fstrace</emphasis> tracing utility allocates 60 kilobytes of memory to the trace log by
      default. You can increase or decrease the amount of memory allocated to the kernel trace log by setting it with the <emphasis
      role="bold">fstrace setlog</emphasis> command. The number specified with the <emphasis role="bold">-buffersize</emphasis>
      argument represents the number of kilobytes allocated to the kernel trace log. If you increase the size of the kernel trace
      log to 100 kilobytes, issue the following command.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace setlog cmfx</emphasis> 100
</programlisting>

      <para>After ensuring that the kernel trace log is configured for your needs, you can set up a file into which you can dump the
      kernel trace log. For example, create a dump file with the name <emphasis role="bold">cmfx.dump.file.1</emphasis> using the
      following <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump</emphasis> command. Issue the command as a continuous process by adding the
      <emphasis role="bold">-follow</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-sleep</emphasis> arguments. Setting the <emphasis
      role="bold">-sleep</emphasis> argument to <emphasis>10</emphasis> dumps output from the kernel trace log to the file every 10
      seconds.</para>

      <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">fstrace dump -follow</emphasis> cmfx <emphasis role="bold">-file</emphasis> cmfx.dump.file.1 <emphasis
          role="bold">-sleep</emphasis> 10
   AFS Trace Dump -
      Date: Fri Apr 16 10:54:57 1999
   Found 1 logs.
   time 32.965783, pid 0: Fri Apr 16 10:45:52 1999
   time 32.965783, pid 33657: Close 0x5c39ed8 flags 0x20 
   time 32.965897, pid 33657: Gn_close vp 0x5c39ed8 flags 0x20 (returns
   0x0) 
   time 35.159854, pid 10891: Breaking callback for 5bd95e4 states 1024
   (volume 0)
   time 35.407081, pid 10891: Breaking callback for 5c0fadc states 1024
   (volume 0)
       .                         .
       .                         .
       .                         .
   time 71.440456, pid 33658: Lookup adp 0x5bbdcf0 name g3oCKs fid (756
   4fb7e:588d240.2ff978a8.6) 
   time 71.440569, pid 33658: Returning code 2 from 19 
   time 71.440619, pid 33658: Gn_lookup vp 0x5bbdcf0 name g3oCKs (returns
   0x2) 
   time 71.464989, pid 38267: Gn_open vp 0x5bbd000 flags 0x0 (returns 0x
   0) 
   AFS Trace Dump - Completed
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ349">
    <title>Using the afsmonitor Program</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

      <secondary>features summarized</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program enables you to monitor the status and performance of specified
    File Server and Cache Manager processes by gathering statistical information. Among its other uses, the <emphasis
    role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program can be used to fine-tune Cache Manager configuration and load balance File
    Servers.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program enables you to perform the following tasks. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Monitor any number of File Server and Cache Manager processes on any number of machines (in both local and foreign
          cells) from a single location.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set threshold values for any monitored statistic. When the value of a statistic exceeds the threshold, the <emphasis
          role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program highlights it to draw your attention. You can set threshold levels that apply to
          every machine or only some.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Invoke programs or scripts automatically when a statistic exceeds its threshold.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ350">
      <title>Requirements for running the afsmonitor program</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

        <secondary>requirements for running</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The following software must be accessible to a machine where the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program is
      running: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The AFS <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis> libraries, which the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis>
            program uses to gather data</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">curses</emphasis> graphics package, which most UNIX distributions provide as a standard
            utility</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>curses graphics utility</primary>

        <secondary>afsmonitor program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>xstat as requirement for running afsmonitor</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> screens format successfully both on so-called dumb terminals and in
      windowing systems that emulate terminals. For the output to looks its best, the display environment needs to support reverse
      video and cursor addressing. Set the TERM environment variable to the correct terminal type, or to a value that has
      characteristics similar to the actual terminal type. The display window or terminal must be at least 80 columns wide and 12
      lines long.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

        <secondary>setting terminal type</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>terminal type</primary>

        <secondary>setting for afsmonitor</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dumb terminal</primary>

        <secondary>use with afsmonitor</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program must run in the foreground, and in its own separate, dedicated
      window or terminal. The window or terminal is unavailable for any other activity as long as the <emphasis
      role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program is running. Any number of instances of the <emphasis
      role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program can run on a single machine, as long as each instance runs in its own dedicated
      window or terminal. Note that it can take up to three minutes to start an additional instance.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>privilege</primary>

        <secondary>required for afsmonitor program</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>No privilege is required to run the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program. By convention, it is installed
      in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/bin</emphasis> directory, and anyone who can access the directory can monitor File
      Servers and Cache Managers. The probes through which the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program collects
      statistics do not constitute a significant burden on the File Server or Cache Manager unless hundreds of people are running
      the program. If you wish to restrict its use, place the binary file in a directory available only to authorized users.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_392">
      <title>The afsmonitor Output Screens</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

        <secondary>screen layout</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program displays its data on three screens: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput>: This screen appears automatically when the <emphasis
            role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program initializes. It summarizes separately for File Servers and Cache Managers the
            number of machines being monitored and how many of them have <emphasis>alerts</emphasis> (statistics that have exceeded
            their thresholds). It then lists the hostname and number of alerts for each machine being monitored, indicating if
            appropriate that a process failed to respond to the last probe.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><computeroutput>File Server</computeroutput>: This screen displays File Server statistics for each file server
            machine being monitored. It highlights statistics that have exceeded their thresholds, and identifies machines that
            failed to respond to the last probe.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput>: This screen displays Cache Manager statistics for each client
            machine being monitored. It highlights statistics that have exceeded their thresholds, and identifies machines that
            failed to respond to the last probe.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Fields at the corners of every screen display the following information: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the top left corner, the program name and version number.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the top right corner, the screen name, current and total page numbers, and current and total column numbers.
            The page number (for example, <computeroutput>p. 1 of 3</computeroutput>) indicates the index of the current page and
            the total number of (vertical) pages over which data is displayed. The column number (for example, <computeroutput>c. 1
            of 235</computeroutput>) indicates the index of the current leftmost column and the total number of columns in which
            data appears. (The symbol <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;&gt;</computeroutput> indicates that there is additional data to the
            right; the symbol <computeroutput>&lt;&lt;&lt;</computeroutput> indicates that there is additional data to the
            left.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the bottom left corner, a list of the available commands. Enter the first letter in the command name to run
            that command. Only the currently possible options appear; for example, if there is only one page of data, the
            <computeroutput>next</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>prev</computeroutput> commands, which scroll the screen up and
            down respectively, do not appear. For descriptions of the commands, see the following section about navigating the
            display screens.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the bottom right corner, the <computeroutput>probes</computeroutput> field reports how many times the program
            has probed File Servers (<computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>), Cache Managers (<computeroutput>cm</computeroutput>), or
            both. The counts for File Servers and Cache Managers can differ. The <computeroutput>freq</computeroutput> field reports
            how often the program sends probes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigating the afsmonitor Display Screens</emphasis></para>

      <para>As noted, the lower left hand corner of every display screen displays the names of the commands currently available for
      moving to alternate screens, which can either be a different type or display more statistics or machines of the current type.
      To execute a command, press the lowercase version of the first letter in its name. Some commands also have an uppercase
      version that has a somewhat different effect, as indicated in the following list. <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>cm</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Switches to the <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput> screen. Available only on the
              <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screens.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>fs</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Switches to the <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen. Available only on the
              <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> and the <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput>
              screens.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>left</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Scrolls horizontally to the left, to access the data columns situated to the left of the current set. Available
              when the <computeroutput>&lt;&lt;&lt;</computeroutput> symbol appears at the top left of the screen. Press uppercase
              <emphasis role="bold">L</emphasis> to scroll horizontally all the way to the left (to display the first set of data
              columns).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>next</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Scrolls down vertically to the next page of machine names. Available when there are two or more pages of
              machines and the final page is not currently displayed. Press uppercase <emphasis role="bold">N</emphasis> to scroll
              to the final page.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>oview</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Switches to the <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> screen. Available only on the
              <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screens.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>prev</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Scrolls up vertically to the previous page of machine names. Available when there are two or more pages of
              machines and the first page is not currently displayed. Press uppercase <emphasis role="bold">N</emphasis> to scroll
              to the first page.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>right</computeroutput></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Scrolls horizontally to the right, to access the data columns situated to the right of the current set. This
              command is available when the <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;&gt;</computeroutput> symbol appears at the upper right of the
              screen. Press uppercase <emphasis role="bold">R</emphasis> to scroll horizontally all the way to the right (to display
              the final set of data columns).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_393">
      <title>The System Overview Screen</title>

      <para>The <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> screen appears automatically as the <emphasis
      role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program initializes. This screen displays the status of as many File Server and Cache
      Manager processes as can fit in the current window; scroll down to access additional information.</para>

      <para>The information on this screen is split into File Server information on the left and Cache Manager information on the
      right. The header for each grouping reports two pieces of information: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of machines on which the program is monitoring the indicated process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of alerts and the number of machines affected by them (an <emphasis>alert</emphasis> means that a
            statistic has exceeded its threshold or a process failed to respond to the last probe)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>A list of the machines being monitored follows. If there are any alerts on a machine, the number of them appears in
      square brackets to the left of the hostname. If a process failed to respond to the last probe, the letters
      <computeroutput>PF</computeroutput> (probe failure) appear in square brackets to the left of the hostname.</para>

      <para>The following graphic is an example <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> screen. The <emphasis
      role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program is monitoring six File Servers and seven Cache Managers. The File Server process on
      host <emphasis role="bold">fs1.abc.com</emphasis> and the Cache Manager on host <emphasis role="bold">cli33.abc.com</emphasis>
      are each marked <computeroutput>[ 1]</computeroutput> to indicate that one threshold value is exceeded. The
      <computeroutput>[PF]</computeroutput> marker on host <emphasis role="bold">fs6.abc.com</emphasis> indicates that its File
      Server process did not respond to the last probe.</para>

      <figure id="Figure_6" label="6">
        <title>The afsmonitor System Overview Screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="overview.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_394">
      <title>The File Servers Screen</title>

      <para>The <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen displays the values collected at the most recent probe for File
      Server statistics.</para>

      <para>A summary line at the top of the screen (just below the standard program version and screen title blocks) specifies the
      number of monitored File Servers, the number of alerts, and the number of machines affected by the alerts.</para>

      <para>The first column always displays the hostnames of the machines running the monitored File Servers.</para>

      <para>To the right of the hostname column appear as many columns of statistics as can fit within the current width of the
      display screen or window; each column requires space for 10 characters. The name of the statistic appears at the top of each
      column. If the File Server on a machine did not respond to the most recent probe, a pair of dashes
      (<computeroutput>--</computeroutput>) appears in each column. If a value exceeds its configured threshold, it is highlighted
      in reverse video. If a value is too large to fit into the allotted column width, it overflows into the next row in the same
      column.</para>

      <para>For a list of the available File Server statistics, see <link linkend="HDRWQ617">Appendix C, The afsmonitor Program
      Statistics</link>.</para>

      <para>The following graphic depicts the <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen that follows the System Overview
      Screen example previously discussed; however, one additional server probe has been completed. In this example, the File Server
      process on <emphasis role="bold">fs1</emphasis> has exceeded the configured threshold for the number of performance calls
      received (the <emphasis role="bold">numPerfCalls</emphasis> statistic), and that field appears in reverse video. Host
      <emphasis role="bold">fs6</emphasis> did not respond to Probe 10, so dashes appear in all fields.</para>

      <figure id="Figure_7" label="7">
        <title>The afsmonitor File Servers Screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fserver1.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>

      <para>Both the File Servers and Cache Managers screen (discussed in the following section) can display hundreds of columns of
      data and are therefore designed to scroll left and right. In the preceding graphic, the screen displays the leftmost screen
      and the screen title block shows that column 1 of 235 is displayed. The appearance of the
      <computeroutput>&gt;&gt;&gt;</computeroutput> symbol in the upper right hand corner of the screen and the <emphasis
      role="bold">right</emphasis> command in the command block indicate that additional data is available by scrolling right. (For
      information on the available statistics, see <link linkend="HDRWQ617">Appendix C, The afsmonitor Program
      Statistics</link>.)</para>

      <para>If the <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> command is executed, the screen looks something like the following
      example. Note that the horizontal scroll symbols now point both to the left (<computeroutput>&lt;&lt;&lt;</computeroutput>)
      and to the right (<computeroutput>&gt;&gt;&gt;</computeroutput>) and both the <emphasis role="bold">left</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="bold">right</emphasis> commands appear, indicating that additional data is available by scrolling both left
      and right.</para>

      <figure id="Figure_8" label="8">
        <title>The afsmonitor File Servers Screen Shifted One Page to the Right</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="fserver2.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_395">
      <title>The Cache Managers Screen</title>

      <para>The <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput> screen displays the values collected at the most recent probe for
      Cache Manager statistics.</para>

      <para>A summary line at the top of the screen (just below the standard program version and screen title blocks) specifies the
      number of monitored Cache Managers, the number of alerts, and the number of machines affected by the alerts.</para>

      <para>The first column always displays the hostnames of the machines running the monitored Cache Managers.</para>

      <para>To the right of the hostname column appear as many columns of statistics as can fit within the current width of the
      display screen or window; each column requires space for 10 characters. The name of the statistic appears at the top of each
      column. If the Cache Manager on a machine did not respond to the most recent probe, a pair of dashes
      (<computeroutput>--</computeroutput>) appears in each column. If a value exceeds its configured threshold, it is highlighted
      in reverse video. If a value is too large to fit into the allotted column width, it overflows into the next row in the same
      column.</para>

      <para>For a list of the available Cache Manager statistics, see <link linkend="HDRWQ617">Appendix C, The afsmonitor Program
      Statistics</link>.</para>

      <para>The following graphic depicts a Cache Managers screen that follows the System Overview Screen previously discussed. In
      the example, the Cache Manager process on host <emphasis role="bold">cli33</emphasis> has exceeded the configured threshold
      for the number of cells it can contact (the <emphasis role="bold">numCellsContacted</emphasis> statistic), so that field
      appears in reverse video.</para>

      <figure id="Figure_9" label="9">
        <title>The afsmonitor Cache Managers Screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="cachmgr.png" scale="50" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ351">
    <title>Configuring the afsmonitor Program</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

      <secondary>creating configuration files for</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>configuring</primary>

      <secondary>afsmonitor program</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To customize the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program, create an ASCII-format configuration file and use
    the <emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis> argument to name it. You can specify the following in the configuration file:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The File Servers, Cache Managers, or both to monitor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The statistics to display. By default, the display includes 271 statistics for File Servers and 570 statistics for
          Cache Managers. For information on the available statistics, see <link linkend="HDRWQ617">Appendix C, The afsmonitor
          Program Statistics</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The threshold values to set for statistics and a script or program to execute if a threshold is exceeded. By
          default, no threshold values are defined and no scripts or programs are executed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The following list describes the instructions that can appear in the configuration file: <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Names a client machine for which to display Cache Manager statistics. The order of <emphasis
            role="bold">cm</emphasis> lines in the file determines the order in which client machines appear from top to bottom on
            the <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput> output
            screens.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Names a file server machine for which to display File Server statistics. The order of <emphasis
            role="bold">fs</emphasis> lines in the file determines the order in which file server machines appear from top to bottom
            on the <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> output
            screens.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>thresh fs | cm <replaceable>field_name</replaceable> <replaceable>thresh_val</replaceable>
          [<replaceable>cmd_to_run</replaceable>] [<replaceable>arg1</replaceable>] . . .
          [<replaceable>argn</replaceable>]</computeroutput></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Assigns the threshold value thresh_val to the statistic field_name, for either a File Server statistic (<emphasis
            role="bold">fs</emphasis>) or a Cache Manager statistic (<emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis>). The optional
            cmd_to_execute field names a binary or script to execute each time the value of the statistic changes from being below
            thresh_val to being at or above thresh_val. A change between two values that both exceed thresh_val does not retrigger
            the binary or script. The optional arg1 through argn fields are additional values that the <emphasis
            role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program passes as arguments to the cmd_to_execute command. If any of them include one
            or more spaces, enclose the entire field in double quotes.</para>

            <para>The parameters <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis>, field_name,
            threshold_val, and arg1 through argn correspond to the values with the same name on the <emphasis
            role="bold">thresh</emphasis> line. The host_name parameter identifies the file server or client machine where the
            statistic has crossed the threshold, and the actual_val parameter is the actual value of field_name that equals or
            exceeds the threshold value.</para>

            <para>Use the <emphasis role="bold">thresh</emphasis> line to set either a global threshold, which applies to all file
            server machines listed on <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> lines or client machines listed on <emphasis
            role="bold">cm</emphasis> lines in the configuration file, or a machine-specific threshold, which applies to only one
            file server or client machine. <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>To set a global threshold, place the <emphasis role="bold">thresh</emphasis> line before any of the
                  <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> lines in the file.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>To set a machine-specific threshold, place the <emphasis role="bold">thresh</emphasis> line below the
                  corresponding <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> line, and above any other
                  <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> lines. A machine-specific threshold
                  value always overrides the corresponding global threshold, if set. Do not place a <emphasis role="bold">thresh
                  fs</emphasis> line directly after a <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> line or a <emphasis role="bold">thresh
                  cm</emphasis> line directly after a <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> line.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>show fs | cm <replaceable>field/group/section</replaceable></computeroutput></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies which individual statistic, group of statistics, or section of statistics to display on the
            <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen (<emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis>) or <computeroutput>Cache
            Managers</computeroutput> screen (<emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis>) and the order in which to display them. The
            appendix of <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> statistics in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
            Guide</emphasis> specifies the group and section to which each statistic belongs. Include as many <emphasis
            role="bold">show</emphasis> lines as necessary to customize the screen display as desired, and place them anywhere in
            the file. The top-to-bottom order of the <emphasis role="bold">show</emphasis> lines in the configuration file
            determines the left-to-right order in which the statistics appear on the corresponding screen.</para>

            <para>If there are no <emphasis role="bold">show</emphasis> lines in the configuration file, then the screens display
            all statistics for both Cache Managers and File Servers. Similarly, if there are no <emphasis role="bold">show
            fs</emphasis> lines, the <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen displays all file server statistics, and
            if there are no <emphasis role="bold">show cm</emphasis> lines, the <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput>
            screen displays all client statistics.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold"># comments</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Precedes a line of text that the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program ignores because of the
            initial number (<emphasis role="bold">#</emphasis>) sign, which must appear in the very first column of the line.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para>For a list of the values that can appear in the field/group/section field of a <emphasis role="bold">show</emphasis>
    instruction, see <link linkend="HDRWQ617">Appendix C, The afsmonitor Program Statistics</link>.)</para>

    <para>The following example illustrates a possible configuration file:</para>

    <programlisting>
   thresh cm dlocalAccesses  1000000
   thresh cm dremoteAccesses  500000 handleDRemote
   thresh fs rx_maxRtt_Usec     1000
   cm client5
   cm client33
   cm client14
   thresh cm dlocalAccesses  2000000
   thresh cm vcacheMisses      10000
   cm client2
   fs fs3
   fs fs9
   fs fs5
   fs fs10
   show cm numCellsContacted
   show cm dlocalAccesses
   show cm dremoteAccesses
   show cm vcacheMisses
   show cm Auth_Stats_group
</programlisting>

    <para>Since the first three <emphasis role="bold">thresh</emphasis> instructions appear before any <emphasis
    role="bold">fs</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> instructions, they set global threshold values: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All Cache Manager process in this file use <emphasis role="bold">1000000</emphasis> as the threshold for the
          <emphasis role="bold">dlocalAccesses</emphasis> statistic (except for the machine <emphasis role="bold">client2</emphasis>
          which uses an overriding value of <emphasis role="bold">2000000</emphasis>.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All Cache Manager processes in this file use <emphasis role="bold">500000</emphasis> as the threshold value for the
          <emphasis role="bold">dremoteAccesses</emphasis> statistic; if that value is exceeded, the script <emphasis
          role="bold">handleDRemote</emphasis> is invoked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All File Server processes in this file use <emphasis role="bold">1000</emphasis> as the threshold value for the
          <emphasis role="bold">rx_maxRtt_Usec</emphasis> statistic.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The four <emphasis role="bold">cm</emphasis> instructions monitor the Cache Manager on the machines <emphasis
    role="bold">client5</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">client33</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">client14</emphasis>, and
    <emphasis role="bold">client2</emphasis>. The first three use all of the global threshold values.</para>

    <para>The Cache Manager on <emphasis role="bold">client2</emphasis> uses the global threshold value for the <emphasis
    role="bold">dremoteAccesses</emphasis> statistic, but a different one for the <emphasis role="bold">dlocalAccesses</emphasis>
    statistic. Furthermore, <emphasis role="bold">client22</emphasis> is the only Cache Manager that uses the threshold set for the
    <emphasis role="bold">vcacheMisses</emphasis> statistic.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fs</emphasis> instructions monitor the File Server on the machines <emphasis
    role="bold">fs3</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">fs9</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">fs5</emphasis>, and <emphasis
    role="bold">fs10</emphasis>. They all use the global threshold for the<emphasis role="bold">rx_maxRtt_Usec</emphasis>
    statistic.</para>

    <para>Because there are no <emphasis role="bold">show fs</emphasis> instructions, the File Servers screen displays all File
    Server statistics. The Cache Managers screen displays only the statistics named in <emphasis role="bold">show cm</emphasis>
    instructions, ordering them from left to right. The <emphasis role="bold">Auth_Stats_group</emphasis> includes several
    statistics, all of which are displayed (<emphasis role="bold">curr_PAGs</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">curr_Records</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">curr_AuthRecords</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">curr_UnauthRecords</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">curr_MaxRecordsInPAG</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">curr_LongestChain</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">PAGCreations</emphasis>, <emphasis
    role="bold">TicketUpdates</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">HWM_PAGS</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">HWM_Records</emphasis>,
    <emphasis role="bold">HWM_MaxRecordsInPAG</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">HWM_LongestChain</emphasis>).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ352">
    <title>Writing afsmonitor Statistics to a File</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

      <secondary>creating an output file</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>All of the statistical information collected and displayed by the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program can
    be preserved by writing it to an output file. You can create an output file by using the <emphasis
    role="bold">-output</emphasis> argument when you startup the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> process. You can use
    the output file to track process performance over long periods of time and to apply post-processing techniques to further
    analyze system trends.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program output file is a simple ASCII file that records the information
    reported by the File Server and Cache Manager screens. The output file has the following format:</para>

    <programlisting>
   time   host_name <emphasis role="bold">CM</emphasis>|<emphasis role="bold">FS</emphasis>   list_of_measured_values
</programlisting>

    <para>and specifies the <emphasis>time</emphasis> at which the <emphasis>list_of_measured_values</emphasis> were gathered from
    the Cache Manager (<emphasis role="bold">CM</emphasis>) or File Server (<emphasis role="bold">FS</emphasis>) process housed on
    host_name. On those occasion where probes fail, the value <computeroutput>-1</computeroutput> is reported instead of the
    <emphasis>list_of_measured_values</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>This file format provides several advantages: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It can be viewed using a standard editor. If you intend to view this file frequently, use the <emphasis
          role="bold">-detailed</emphasis> flag with the <emphasis role="bold">-output</emphasis> argument. It formats the output
          file in a way that is easier to read.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It can be passed through filters to extract desired information using the standard set of UNIX tools.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It is suitable for long term storage of the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

      <secondary>command syntax</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>commands</primary>

      <secondary>afsmonitor</secondary>
    </indexterm>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Header_398">
    <title>To start the afsmonitor Program</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open a separate command shell window or use a dedicated terminal for each instance of the <emphasis
        role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program. This window or terminal must be devoted to the exclusive use of the <emphasis
        role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> process because the command cannot be run in the background.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Initialize the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program. The message <computeroutput>afsmonitor Collecting
        Statistics...</computeroutput>, followed by the appearance of the <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> screen,
        confirms a successful start. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis>]  [<emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>configuration file</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>poll frequency, in seconds</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-output</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>storage file name</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis
              role="bold">-detailed</emphasis>]  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>turn debugging output on to the named file</replaceable>&gt;] \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-fshosts</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>list of file servers to monitor</replaceable>&gt;+]  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-cmhosts</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>list of cache managers to monitor</replaceable>&gt;+]
   afsmonitor Collecting Statistics...
</programlisting></para>

        <para>where <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an optional string that accommodates the command's use of the AFS command parser. It can be omitted and
                ignored.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the pathname of an <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> configuration file, which lists the
                machines and statistics to monitor. Partial pathnames are interpreted relative to the current working directory.
                Provide either this argument or one or both of the <emphasis role="bold">-fshosts</emphasis> and <emphasis
                role="bold">-cmhosts</emphasis> arguments. You must use a configuration file to set thresholds or customize the
                screen display. For instructions on creating the configuration file, see <link linkend="HDRWQ351">Configuring the
                afsmonitor Program</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies how often to probe the File Server and Cache Manager processes, as a number of seconds. Acceptable
                values range from <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">86400</emphasis>; the default value
                is <emphasis role="bold">60</emphasis>. This frequency applies to both File Server and Cache Manager probes;
                however, File Server and Cache Manager probes are initiated and processed independent of each other. The actual
                interval between probes to a host is the probe frequency plus the time needed by all hosts to respond to the
                probe.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-output</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the name of an output file to which to write all of the statistical data. By default, no output file
                is created. For information on this file, see <link linkend="HDRWQ352">Writing afsmonitor Statistics to a
                File</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-detailed</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Formats the output file named by the <emphasis role="bold">-output</emphasis> argument to be more easily
                readable. The <emphasis role="bold">-output</emphasis> argument must be provided along with this flag.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-fshosts</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Identifies each File Server process to monitor by specifying the host it is running on. You can identify a
                host using either its complete Internet-style host name or an abbreviation acceptable to the cell's naming service.
                Combine this argument with the <emphasis role="bold">-cmhosts</emphasis> if you wish, but not the <emphasis
                role="bold">-config</emphasis> argument.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-cmhosts</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Identifies each Cache Manager process to monitor by specifying the host it is running on. You can identify a
                host using either its complete Internet-style host name or an abbreviation acceptable to the cell's naming service.
                Combine this argument with the <emphasis role="bold">-fshosts</emphasis> if you wish, but not the <emphasis
                role="bold">-config</emphasis> argument.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Header_399">
    <title>To stop the afsmonitor program</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>afsmonitor program</primary>

      <secondary>stopping</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>To exit an <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program session, Enter the &lt;<emphasis
    role="bold">Ctrl-c</emphasis>&gt; interrupt signal or an uppercase <emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ353">
    <title>The xstat Data Collection Facility</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

      <secondary>libxstat_fs.a library</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

      <secondary>libxstat_cm.a library</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>data collection</primary>

      <secondary>with xstat data collection facility</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>collecting</primary>

      <secondary>data with xstat data collection facility</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>File Server</primary>

      <secondary>collecting data with xstat data collection facility</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

      <secondary>collecting data with xstat data collection facility</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>File Server</primary>

      <secondary>xstat data collection facility libraries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

      <secondary>xstat data collection facility libraries</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program uses the <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis> data collection
    facility to gather and calculate the data that it (the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program) then uses to perform
    its function. You can also use the <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis> facility to create your own data display programs. If
    you do, keep the following in mind. The File Server considers any program calling its RPC routines to be a Cache Manager;
    therefore, any program calling the File Server interface directly must export the Cache Manager's callback interface. The
    calling program must be capable of emulating the necessary callback state, and it must respond to periodic keep-alive messages
    from the File Server. In addition, a calling program must be able to gather the collected data.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis> facility consists of two C language libraries available to user-level
    applications: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/lib/afs/libxstat_fs.a</emphasis> exports calls that gather information from one or
          more running File Server processes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/lib/afs/libxstat_cm.a</emphasis> exports calls that collect information from one or
          more running Cache Managers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The libraries allow the caller to register <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A set of File Servers or Cache Managers to be examined.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The frequency with which the File Servers or Cache Managers are to be probed for data.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A user-specified routine to be called each time data is collected.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The libraries handle all of the lightweight processes, callback interactions, and timing issues associated with the data
    collection. The user needs only to process the data as it arrives.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_401">
      <title>The libxstat Libraries</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>

        <secondary>routines</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>

        <secondary>routines</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">libxstat_fs.a</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">libxstat_cm.a</emphasis> libraries handle
      the callback requirements and other complications associated with the collection of data from File Servers and Cache Managers.
      The user provides only the means of accumulating the desired data. Each <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis> library
      implements three routines: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Initialization (<emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_Init</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">xstat_cm_Init</emphasis>)
            arranges the periodic collection and handling of data.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Immediate probe (<emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_ForceProbeNow</emphasis> and <emphasis
            role="bold">xstat_cm_ForceProbeNow</emphasis>) forces the immediate collection of data, after which collection returns
            to its normal probe schedule.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Cleanup (<emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_Cleanup</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">xstat_cm_Cleanup</emphasis>)
            terminates all connections and removes all traces of the data collection from memory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>File Server</primary>

        <secondary>xstat data collections</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

        <secondary>xstat data collections</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

        <secondary>data collections</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>

        <secondary>data collections</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>

        <secondary>data collections</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The File Server and Cache Manager each define data collections that clients can fetch. A data collection is simply a
      related set of numbers that can be collected as a unit. For example, the File Server and Cache Manager each define profiling
      and performance data collections. The profiling collections maintain counts of the number of times internal functions are
      called within servers, allowing bottleneck analysis to be performed. The performance collections record, among other things,
      internal disk I/O statistics for a File Server and cache effectiveness figures for a Cache Manager, allowing for performance
      analysis.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

        <secondary>obtaining more information</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>

        <secondary>obtaining more information</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>

        <secondary>obtaining more information</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>For a copy of the detailed specification which provides much additional usage information about the <emphasis
      role="bold">xstat</emphasis> facility, its libraries, and the routines in the libraries, contact AFS Product Support.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_402">
      <title>Example xstat Commands</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

        <secondary>example commands</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>

        <secondary>example command using</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>

        <secondary>example command using</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>File Server</primary>

        <secondary>xstat example commands</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

        <secondary>xstat example commands</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>AFS comes with two low-level, example commands: <emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_test</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">xstat_cm_test</emphasis>. The commands allow you to experiment with the <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis>
      facility. They gather information and display the available data collections for a File Server or Cache Manager. They are
      intended merely to provide examples of the types of data that can be collected via <emphasis role="bold">xstat</emphasis>;
      they are not intended for use in the actual collection of data.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>xstat_fs_test</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>libxstat_fs.a library</primary>

        <secondary>xstat_fs_test example command</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>File Server</primary>

        <secondary>xstat_fs_test example command</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

        <secondary>xstat_fs_test example command</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <sect3 id="Header_403">
        <title>To use the example xstat_fs_test command</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Issue the example <emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_test</emphasis> command to test the routines in the <emphasis
            role="bold">libxstat_fs.a</emphasis> library and display the data collections associated with the File Server process.
            The command executes in the foreground. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_test</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis>]  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-fsname</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>File Server name(s) to monitor</replaceable>&gt;+  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-collID</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>Collection(s) to fetch</replaceable>&gt;+  [<emphasis
                  role="bold">-onceonly</emphasis>]  \
                   [<emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>poll frequency, in seconds</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                   [<emphasis role="bold">-period</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>data collection time, in minutes</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis
                  role="bold">-debug</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>

            <para>where <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">xstat_fs_test</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Must be typed in full.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Is an optional string that accommodates the command's use of the AFS command parser. It can be omitted and
                    ignored.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-fsname</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Is the Internet host name of each file server machine on which to monitor the File Server process.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-collID</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Specifies each data collection to return. The indicated data collection defines the type and amount of
                    data the command is to gather about the File Server. Data is returned in the form of a predefined data structure
                    (refer to the specification documents referenced previously for more information about the data
                    structures).</para>

                    <para>There are two acceptable values: <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> reports various internal performance statistics related to the
                          File Server (for example, vnode cache entries and <emphasis role="bold">Rx</emphasis> protocol
                          activity).</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis> reports all of the internal performance statistics provided by
                          the <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> setting, plus some additional, detailed performance figures about
                          the File Server (for example, minimum, maximum, and cumulative statistics regarding File Server RPCs, how
                          long they take to complete, and how many succeed).</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist></para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-onceonly</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Directs the command to gather statistics just one time. Omit this option to have the command continue to
                    probe the File Server for statistics every 30 seconds. If you omit this option, you can use the &lt;<emphasis
                    role="bold">Ctrl-c</emphasis>&gt; interrupt signal to halt the command at any time.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Sets the frequency in seconds at which the program initiates probes to the File Server. If you omit this
                    argument, the default is 30 seconds.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-period</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Sets how long the utility runs before exiting, as a number of minutes. If you omit this argument, the
                    default is 10 minutes.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Displays additional information as the command runs.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>commands</primary>

          <secondary>xstat_cm_test</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>libxstat_cm.a library</primary>

          <secondary>xstat_cm_test example command</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>Cache Manager</primary>

          <secondary>xstat_cm_test example command</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>xstat data collection facility</primary>

          <secondary>xstat_cm_test example command</secondary>
        </indexterm>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_404">
        <title>To use the example xstat_cm_test command</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Issue the example <emphasis role="bold">xstat_cm_test</emphasis> command to test the routines in the <emphasis
            role="bold">libxstat_cm.a</emphasis> library and display the data collections associated with the Cache Manager. The
            command executes in the foreground. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">xstat_cm_test</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis>]  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-cmname</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>Cache Manager name(s) to monitor</replaceable>&gt;+  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-collID</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>Collection(s) to fetch</replaceable>&gt;+ \
                   [<emphasis role="bold">-onceonly</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>poll frequency, in seconds</replaceable>&gt;]  \
                   [<emphasis role="bold">-period</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>data collection time, in minutes</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis
                  role="bold">-debug</emphasis>] 
</programlisting></para>

            <para>where <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">xstat_cm_test</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Must be typed in full.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">initcmd</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Is an optional string that accommodates the command's use of the AFS command parser. It can be omitted and
                    ignored.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-cmname</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Is the host name of each client machine on which to monitor the Cache Manager.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-collID</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Specifies each data collection to return. The indicated data collection defines the type and amount of
                    data the command is to gather about the Cache Manager. Data is returned in the form of a predefined data
                    structure (refer to the specification documents referenced previously for more information about the data
                    structures).</para>

                    <para>There are two acceptable values: <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> provides profiling information about the numbers of times
                          different internal Cache Manager routines were called since the Cache manager was started.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> reports various internal performance statistics related to the
                          Cache manager (for example, statistics about how effectively the cache is being used and the quantity of
                          intracell and intercell data access).</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis> reports all of the internal performance statistics provided by
                          the <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> setting, plus some additional, detailed performance figures about
                          the Cache Manager (for example, statistics about the number of RPCs sent by the Cache Manager and how long
                          they take to complete; and statistics regarding things such as authentication, access, and PAG information
                          associated with data access).</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist></para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-onceonly</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Directs the command to gather statistics just one time. Omit this option to have the command continue to
                    probe the Cache Manager for statistics every 30 seconds. If you omit this option, you can use the &lt;<emphasis
                    role="bold">Ctrl-c</emphasis>&gt; interrupt signal to halt the command at any time.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-frequency</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Sets the frequency in seconds at which the program initiates probes to the Cache Manager. If you omit this
                    argument, the default is 30 seconds.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-period</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Sets how long the utility runs before exiting, as a number of minutes. If you omit this argument, the
                    default is 10 minutes.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><emphasis role="bold">-debug</emphasis></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Displays additional information as the command runs.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ354">
    <title>Auditing AFS Events on AIX File Servers</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AFS</primary>

      <secondary>auditing events on AIX server machines</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AIX</primary>

      <secondary>auditing AFS events</secondary>

      <tertiary>about</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>auditing AFS events on AIX server machines</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>events</primary>

      <secondary>auditing AFS on AIX server machines</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>You can audit AFS events on AIX File Servers using an AFS mechanism that transfers audit information from AFS to the AIX
    auditing system. The following general classes of AFS events can be audited. For a complete list of specific AFS audit events,
    see <link linkend="HDRWQ620">Appendix D, AIX Audit Events</link>. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Authentication and Identification Events</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Security Events</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Privilege Required Events</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Object Creation and Deletion Events</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Attribute Modification Events</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Process Control Events</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <note>
      <para>This section assumes familiarity with the AIX auditing system. For more information, see the <emphasis>AIX System
      Management Guide</emphasis> for the version of AIX you are using.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="Header_406">
      <title>Configuring AFS Auditing on AIX File Servers</title>

      <para>The directory <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/local/audit</emphasis> contains three files that contain the information
      needed to configure AIX File Servers to audit AFS events: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">events.sample</emphasis> file contains information on auditable AFS events. The contents
            of this file are integrated into the corresponding AIX events file (<emphasis
            role="bold">/etc/security/audit/events</emphasis>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">config.sample</emphasis> file defines the six classes of AFS audit events and the events
            that make up each class. It also defines the classes of AFS audit events to audit for the File Server, which runs as the
            local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>. The contents of this file must be integrated into the
            corresponding AIX config file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/security/audit/config</emphasis>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">objects.sample</emphasis> file contains a list of information about audited files. You
            must only audit files in the local file space. The contents of this file must be integrated into the corresponding AIX
            objects file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/security/audit/objects</emphasis>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Once you have properly configured these files to include the AFS-relevant information, use the AIX auditing system to
      start up and shut down the auditing.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_407">
      <title>To enable AFS auditing</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create the following string in the file <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/local/Audit</emphasis> on each File Server on
          which you plan to audit AFS events: <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">AFS_AUDIT_AllEvents</emphasis></programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos restart</emphasis> command (with the <emphasis role="bold">-all</emphasis> flag)
          to stop and restart all server processes on each File Server. For instructions on using this command, see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ170">Stopping and Immediately Restarting Processes</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_408">
      <title>To disable AFS auditing</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove the contents of the file <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/local/Audit</emphasis> on each File Server for which
          you are no longer interested in auditing AFS events.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos restart</emphasis> command (with the <emphasis role="bold">-all</emphasis> flag)
          to stop and restart all server processes on each File Server. For instructions on using this command, see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ170">Stopping and Immediately Restarting Processes</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
