<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ248">
  <title>Configuring the AFS Backup System</title>

  <para>The AFS Backup System helps you to create backup copies of data from AFS volumes and to restore data to the file system if
  it is lost or corrupted. This chapter explains how to configure the Backup System. For instructions on backing up and restoring
  data and displaying dump records, see <link linkend="HDRWQ283">Backing Up and Restoring AFS Data</link>.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ249">
    <title>Summary of Instructions</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to perform the following tasks by using the indicated commands:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="70*" />

        <colspec colwidth="30*" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Determine tape capacity and filemark size</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define Tape Coordinator entry in Backup Database</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Remove Tape Coordinator entry from Backup Database</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup delhost</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Display Tape Coordinator entries from Backup Database</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup listhosts</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Create volume set</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup addvolset</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Add volume entry to volume set</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup addvolentry</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>List volume sets and entries</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup listvolsets</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Delete volume set from Backup Database</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup delvolset</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Delete volume entry from volume set</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup delvolentry</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Define dump level</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup adddump</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Change expiration date on existing dump level</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup setexp</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Delete dump level from dump hierarchy</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup deldump</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Display dump hierarchy</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup listdumps</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Label tape</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Read label on tape</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">backup readlabel</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ251">
    <title>Introduction to Backup System Features</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup System</primary>

      <secondary>introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The AFS Backup System is highly flexible, enabling you to control most aspects of the backup process, including how often
    backups are performed, which volumes are backed up, and whether to dump all of the data in a volume or just the data that has
    changed since the last dump operation. You can also take advantage of several features that automate much of the backup
    process.</para>

    <para>To administer and use the Backup System most efficiently, it helps to be familiar with its basic features, which are
    described in the following sections. For pointers to instructions for implementing the features as you configure the Backup
    System in your cell, see <link linkend="HDRWQ257">Overview of Backup System Configuration</link>.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ252">
      <title>Volume Sets and Volume Entries</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>volume entry</secondary>

        <see>volume entry</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume entry (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>volume set</secondary>

        <see>volume set</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>volume entry</secondary>

        <see>volume entry</see>
      </indexterm>

      <para>When you back up AFS data, you specify which data to include in terms of complete volumes rather than individual files.
      More precisely, you define groups of volumes called <emphasis>volume sets</emphasis>, each of which includes one or more
      volumes that you want to back up in a single operation. You must include a volume in a volume set to back it up, because the
      command that backs up data (the <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> command) does not accept individual volume
      names.</para>

      <para>A volume set consists of one or more <emphasis>volume entries</emphasis>, each of which specifies which volumes to back
      up based on their location (file server machine and partition) and volume name. You can use a wildcard notation to include all
      volumes that share a location, a common character string in their names, or both.</para>

      <para>For instructions on creating and removing volume sets and volume entries, see <link linkend="HDRWQ265">Defining and
      Displaying Volume Sets and Volume Entries</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_274">
      <title>Dumps and Dump Sets</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump</secondary>

        <see>dump</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump set</secondary>

        <see>dump set</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>appended, defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>parent, defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>full, defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>incremental, defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>initial, defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>set</secondary>

        <see>dump set</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>A <emphasis>dump</emphasis> is the collection of data that results from backing up a volume set. A <emphasis>full
      dump</emphasis> includes all of the data in every volume in the volume set, as it exists at the time of the dump operation. An
      <emphasis>incremental dump</emphasis> includes only some of the data from the volumes in the volume set, namely those files
      and directory structures that have changed since a specified previous dump operation was performed. The previous dump is
      referred to as the incremental dump's <emphasis>parent dump</emphasis>, and it can be either a full dump or an incremental
      dump itself.</para>

      <para>A <emphasis>dump set</emphasis> is a collection of one or more dumps stored together on one or more tapes. The first
      dump in the dump set is the <emphasis>initial dump</emphasis>, and any subsequent dump added onto the end of an existing dump
      set is an <emphasis>appended dump</emphasis>. Appending dumps is always optional, but maximizes use of a tape's capacity. In
      contrast, creating only initial dumps can result in many partially filled tapes, because an initial dump must always start on
      a new tape, but does not necessarily extend to the end of the tape. Appended dumps do not have to be related to one another or
      to the initial dump (they do not have to be dumps of the same or related volume sets), but well-planned appending can reduce
      the number of times you have to change tapes during a restore operation. For example, it can make sense to append incremental
      dumps of a volume set together in a single dump set.</para>

      <para>All the records for a dump set are indexed together in the Backup Database based on the initial dump (for more on the
      Backup Database, see <link linkend="HDRWQ256">The Backup Database and Backup Server Process</link>). To delete the database
      record of an appended dump, you must delete the initial dump record, and doing so deletes the records for all dumps in the
      dump set. Similarly, you cannot recycle just one tape in a dump set without deleting the database records of all tapes in the
      dump set.</para>

      <para>For instructions on creating an initial dump, see <link linkend="HDRWQ296">Backing Up Data</link>, and to learn how to
      append dumps, see <link linkend="HDRWQ299">Appending Dumps to an Existing Dump Set</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_275">
      <title>Dump Hierarchies, Dump Levels and Expiration Dates</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump hierarchy</secondary>

        <see>dump hierarchy</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump level</secondary>

        <see>dump hierarchy</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>defined</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>described</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>dump level</secondary>

        <tertiary>defined</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>expiration date on dump level</secondary>

        <tertiary>described</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>A <emphasis>dump hierarchy</emphasis> is a logical structure that defines the relationship between full and incremental
      dumps; that is, it defines which dump serves as the parent for an incremental dump. Each individual component of a hierarchy
      is a <emphasis>dump level</emphasis>. When you create a dump by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis>
      command, you specify a volume set name and a dump level name. The Backup System uses the dump level to determine whether the
      dump is full or incremental, and if incremental, which dump level to use as the parent.</para>

      <para>You can associate an <emphasis>expiration date</emphasis> with a dump level, to define when a dump created at that level
      expires. The Backup System refuses to overwrite a tape until all dumps in the dump set to which the tape belongs have expired,
      so assigning expiration dates automatically determines how you recycle tapes. You can define an expiration date either in
      absolute terms (for example, 13 January 2000) or relative terms (for example, 30 days from when the dump is created). You can
      also change the expiration date associated with a dump level (but not with an actual dump that has already been created at
      that level).</para>

      <para>For instructions on creating dump hierarchies, assigning expiration dates, and establishing a tape recycling schedule,
      see <link linkend="HDRWQ267">Defining and Displaying the Dump Hierarchy</link>.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump name</secondary>

        <see>dump</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>tape name</secondary>

        <see>tapes</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>dump ID number</secondary>

        <see>dump</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>names</secondary>

        <tertiary>described</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>ID number, described</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>name, described</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ253">
      <title>Dump Names and Tape Names</title>

      <para>When you create a dump, the Backup System creates a Backup Database record for it, assigning a name comprising the
      volume set name and the last element in the dump level pathname:</para>

      <programlisting>
   volume_set_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>dump_level_name
</programlisting>

      <para>For example, a dump of the volume set <emphasis role="bold">user</emphasis> at the dump level <emphasis
      role="bold">/sunday/friday</emphasis> is called <emphasis role="bold">user.friday</emphasis>. The Backup System also assigns a
      unique <emphasis>dump ID</emphasis> number to the dump to distinguish it from other dumps with the same name that possibly
      exist.</para>

      <para>The Backup System assigns a similar <emphasis>AFS tape name</emphasis> to each tape that contains a dump set, reflecting
      the volume set and dump level of the dump set's initial dump, plus a numerical index of the tape's position in the dump set,
      and a unique dump ID number:</para>

      <programlisting>
   volume_set_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>dump_level_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>tape_index (dump ID)
</programlisting>

      <para>For example, the second tape in a dump set whose initial dump is of the volume set <emphasis
      role="bold">uservol</emphasis> at the dump level <emphasis role="bold">/sunday/friday</emphasis> has AFS tape name like
      <emphasis role="bold">uservol.friday.2</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">914382400</emphasis>).</para>

      <para>In addition to its AFS tape name, a tape can have an optional <emphasis>permanent name</emphasis> that you assign.
      Unlike the AFS tape name, the permanent name does not have to indicate the volume set and dump level of the initial (or any
      other) dump, and so does not change depending on the contents of the tape. The Backup System does not require a certain format
      for permanent names, so you need to make sure that each tape's name is unique. If a tape has a permanent name, the Backup
      System uses it rather than the AFS tape name when referring to the tape in prompts and the output from most <emphasis
      role="bold">backup</emphasis> commands, but still tracks the AFS tape name internally.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ254">
      <title>Tape Labels, Dump Labels, and EOF Markers</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>label</secondary>

        <tertiary>described</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>label, described</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>filemarks</secondary>

        <see>Tape Coordinator</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>filemark</secondary>

        <tertiary>described</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Every tape used in the Backup System has a magnetic label at the beginning that records the tape's name, capacity, and
      other information. You can use the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command to write a label, or the
      <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> command creates one automatically if you use an unlabeled tape. The label records
      the following information: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The tape's permanent name, which you can assign by using the <emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument to
            the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command. It can be any string of up to 32 characters. If you do
            not assign a permanent name, the Backup System records the value <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput> when you
            use the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command to assign an AFS tape name, or when you use the
            <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> command to write a dump to the tape.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The tape's AFS <emphasis>tape name</emphasis>, which can be one of three types of values: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A name that reflects the volume set and dump level of the dump set's initial dump and the tape's place in
                  the sequence of tapes for the dump set, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ253">Dump Names and Tape Names</link>.
                  If the tape does not have a permanent name, you can assign the AFS tape name by using the <emphasis
                  role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The value <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>, which results when you assign a permanent name, or
                  provide no value for the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command's <emphasis
                  role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>No AFS tape name at all, indicating that you have never labeled the tape or written a dump to it.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>

            <para>If a tape does not already have an actual AFS tape name when you write a dump to it, the Backup System constructs
            and records the appropriate AFS tape name. If the tape does have an AFS tape name and you are writing an initial dump,
            then the name must correctly reflect the dump's volume set and dump level.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The capacity, or <emphasis>size</emphasis>, of the tape, followed by a letter that indicates the unit of measure
            (<computeroutput>k</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>K</computeroutput> for kilobytes,
            <computeroutput>m</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>M</computeroutput> for megabytes,
            <computeroutput>g</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>G</computeroutput> for gigabytes, or
            <computeroutput>t</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>T</computeroutput> for terabytes). The tape's manufacturer
            determines the tape's capacity. For further discussion of how the Backup System uses the value in the capacity field,
            see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig File</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For information about labeling tapes, see <link linkend="HDRWQ272">Writing and Reading Tape Labels</link>.</para>

      <para>In addition to the tape label, the Backup System writes a <emphasis>dump label</emphasis> on the tape for every appended
      dump (the tape label and dump label are the same for the initial dump). A dump label records the following information:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the tape containing the dump</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date and time that the dump operation began</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The cell to which the volumes in the dump belong</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dump's size in kilobytes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dump's dump level</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dump's dump ID</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>The Backup System writes a <emphasis>filemark</emphasis> (also called an End-of-File or EOF marker) between the data
      from each volume in a dump. The tape device's manufacturer determines the filemark size, which is typically between 2 KB and 2
      MB; in general, the larger the usual capacity of the tapes that the device uses, the larger the filemark size. If a dump
      contains a small amount of data from each of a large number of volumes, as incremental dumps often do, then the filemark size
      can significantly affect how much volume data fits on the tape. To enable the Backup System to factor in filemark size as it
      writes a dump, you can record the filemark size in a configuration file; see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the
      tapeconfig File</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ255">
      <title>Tape Coordinator Machines, Port Offsets, and Backup Data Files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>described</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>Tape Coordinator</secondary>

        <see>Tape Coordinator</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>port offsets</secondary>

        <see>Tape Coordinator</see>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>port offset number</secondary>

        <tertiary>defined</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>A <emphasis>Tape Coordinator machine</emphasis> is a machine that drives one or more attached tape devices used for
      backup operations. It must run the AFS client software (the Cache Manager) but reside in a physically secure location to
      prevent unauthorized access to its console. Before backup operations can run on a Tape Coordinator machine, each tape device
      on the machine must be registered in the Backup Database, and certain files and directories must exist on the machine's local
      disk; for instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ262">To configure a Tape Coordinator machine</link>.</para>

      <para>Each tape device on a Tape Coordinator machine listens for backup requests on a different UNIX port. You pick the port
      indirectly by assigning a <emphasis>port offset number</emphasis> to the tape device. The Backup System sets the device's
      actual port by adding the port offset to a base port number that it determines internally. For instructions on assigning port
      offset numbers, see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig File</link>.</para>

      <para>For a tape device to perform backup operations, a Backup Tape Coordinator (<emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis>)
      process dedicated to the device must be running actively on the Tape Coordinator machine. You then direct backup requests to
      the device's Tape Coordinator by specifying its port offset number with the <emphasis role="bold">-portoffset</emphasis>
      argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command.</para>

      <para>In addition to writing backup data to tape, you can direct it to a <emphasis>backup data file</emphasis> on the local
      disk of a Tape Coordinator machine. You can then to transfer the data to a data-archiving system, such as a hierarchical
      storage management (HSM) system, that you use in conjunction with AFS and the Backup System. A backup data file has a port
      offset like a tape device. For instructions on configuring backup data files, see <link linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping Data to a
      Backup Data File</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ256">
      <title>The Backup Database and Backup Server Process</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>described</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>Backup Database</secondary>

        <see>Backup Database</see>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis>Backup Database</emphasis> is a replicated administrative database maintained by the Backup Server process
      on the cell's database server machines. Like the other AFS database server processes, the <emphasis>Backup Server</emphasis>
      uses the Ubik utility to keep the various copies of the database synchronized (for a discussion of Ubik, see <link
      linkend="HDRWQ52">Replicating the AFS Administrative Databases</link>).</para>

      <para>The Backup Database records the following information: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Tape Coordinator machine's hostname and the port offset number for each tape device used for backup
            operations</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The dump hierarchy, which consists of its component dump levels and their associated expiration dates</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The volume sets and their component volume entries</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A record for each dump, which includes the name of each tape it appears on, a list of the volumes from which data
            is included, the dump level, the expiration date, and the dump ID of the initial dump with which the dump is
            associated</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A record for each tape that houses dumped data</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_280">
      <title>Interfaces to the Backup System</title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> suite of commands is the administrative interface to the Backup System. You
      can issue the commands in a command shell (or invoke them in a shell script) on any AFS client or server machine from which
      you can access the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> binary. In the conventional configuration, the binary resides on
      the local disk.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command suite provides an <emphasis>interactive mode</emphasis>, in which
      you can issue multiple commands over a persistent connection to the Backup Server and the Volume Location (VL) Server.
      Interactive mode has several convenient features, including the following: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You need to type only the operation code, omitting the initial <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
            string.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you assume another AFS identity or specify a foreign cell as you enter interactive mode, it applies to all
            subsequent commands.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You do not need to enclose shell metacharacters in double quotes.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You can track current and pending operations with the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) jobs</emphasis> command,
            which is available only in this mode.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You can cancel current and pending operations with the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) kill</emphasis> command,
            which is available only in this mode.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Before issuing a command that requires reading or writing a tape (or backup data file), you must also open a connection
      to the Tape Coordinator machine that is attached to the relevant tape device (or that has the backup data file on its local
      disk), and issue the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command to initialize the Tape Coordinator process. The process
      must continue to run and the connection remain open as long as you need to use the tape device or file for backup
      operations.</para>

      <para>For further discussion and instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ286">Using the Backup System's
      Interfaces</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ257">
    <title>Overview of Backup System Configuration</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup System</primary>

      <secondary>configuration overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Before you can use the Backup System to back up and restore data, you must configure several of its basic components. The
    indicated sections of this chapter explain how to perform the following configuration tasks: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Determining a tape's capacity and a tape device's filemark size, and recording them in the <emphasis
          role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file (see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig
          File</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Determining how to grant administrative privilege to backup operators (see <link linkend="HDRWQ260">Granting
          Administrative Privilege to Backup Operators</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configuring Tape Coordinator machines, tape devices, and backup data files (see <link linkend="HDRWQ261">Configuring
          Tape Coordinator Machines and Tape Devices</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Defining volume sets and volume entries (see <link linkend="HDRWQ265">Defining and Displaying Volume Sets and Volume
          Entries</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Defining dump levels to create a dump hierarchy (see <link linkend="HDRWQ267">Defining and Displaying the Dump
          Hierarchy</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Labeling tapes (see <link linkend="HDRWQ272">Writing and Reading Tape Labels</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Creating a device configuration file to automate the backup process (see <link linkend="HDRWQ275">Automating and
          Increasing the Efficiency of the Backup Process</link>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>If you have already configured all of the components required for performing a backup dump or restore operation, you can
    proceed to the instructions in <link linkend="HDRWQ296">Backing Up Data</link> and <link linkend="HDRWQ306">Restoring and
    Recovering Data</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ258">
    <title>Configuring the tapeconfig File</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>capacity</secondary>

      <tertiary>determining</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>filemark</secondary>

      <tertiary>determining size</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>port offset number</secondary>

      <tertiary>assigning</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>files</primary>

      <secondary>tapeconfig</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapeconfig file</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Several factors interact to determine how much data the Tape Coordinator can fit on a tape: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The tape's capacity (size), as set by the tape manufacturer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The tape device's filemark size, as set by the tape device's manufacturer. Recall from <link linkend="HDRWQ254">Tape
          Labels, Dump Labels, and EOF Markers</link> that the Tape Coordinator writes a filemark between the data from each volume
          in a dump. If a dump contains a small amount of data from each of a large number of volumes, as incremental dumps often
          do, then the filemark size can significantly affect how much volume data fits on the tape.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Whether or not you use the tape device's compression mode.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>(The amount of data that can fit in a backup data file is determined by amount of space available on the partition, and
    the operating system's maximum file size. The Tape Coordinator does not write filemarks when writing to a backup data file. For
    further information about configuring a Tape Coordinator to write to a backup data file, see <link linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping
    Data to a Backup Data File</link>.)</para>

    <para>As the Tape Coordinator (<emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis>) process initializes, it reads the <emphasis
    role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file on its local disk to learn the tape capacity and filemark size (for a
    tape device) or the file size (for a backup data file) to use for dump operations. When you begin a dump operation, the Tape
    Coordinator also reads the tape or backup data file's label to see if you have recorded a different tape capacity or file size.
    If you have, the value on the label overrides the default value from the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis>
    file.</para>

    <para>As the Tape Coordinator writes data to a tape during a dump operation, it uses the capacity and filemark information to
    track how much tape it has used and how much remains before the physical end-of-tape (EOT). Shortly before reaching EOT, the
    Tape Coordinator stops writing and requests a new tape. Similarly, it uses a backup data file's size to know when it is about to
    exhaust the space in the file. If the Tape Coordinator reaches the EOT unexpectedly, it recovers by obtaining a new tape and
    writing to it the entire contents of the volume it was writing when it reached EOT. The interrupted volume remains on the first
    tape, but is never used.</para>

    <para>Many tape devices use tapes that can accommodate multiple gigabytes, or even multiple terabytes, of backup data,
    especially if you use the device's compression mode. When writing to such devices and tapes, allowing the Tape Coordinator to
    hit the EOT unexpectedly is generally recommended. The devices write data so quickly that it usually does not take much extra
    time to rewrite the interrupted volume on the new tape. Similarly, they compress data so well that the data abandoned on the
    first tape from the interrupted volume does not constitute a waste of much tape.</para>

    <para>When writing to tapes that accommodate a smaller amount of data (say, less than two GB), it is better to avoid having the
    Tape Coordinator hit EOT unexpectedly. AFS supports volumes up to 2 GB in size, so an interrupted volume can in fact take up
    most of the tape. For such tapes, recording accurate values for tape capacity and filemark size, if possible, helps to maximize
    both use of tape and the efficiency of dump operations. The following discussion of the fields in the <emphasis
    role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file explains how to determine the appropriate values.</para>

    <para>Use a text editor to create an entry in a Tape Coordinator's <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file for each
    tape device or backup data file that it uses. Each device or file's entry is on its own line and has the following
    format:</para>

    <programlisting>
   [capacity   filemark_size]    device_name    port_offset
</programlisting>

    <para>where <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">capacity</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the capacity of the tapes used with a tape device, or the amount of data to write into a backup data
            file. Specify an integer value followed by a letter that indicates units, with no intervening space. The letter
            <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis> indicates kilobytes, <emphasis
            role="bold">m</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> indicates megabytes, <emphasis role="bold">g</emphasis>
            or <emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis> indicates gigabytes, and <emphasis role="bold">t</emphasis> or <emphasis
            role="bold">T</emphasis> indicates terabytes. If the units letter is omitted, the default is kilobytes.</para>

            <para>To determine the capacity of a tape under two GB in size that you are going to use in regular (noncompression)
            mode, you can either use the value that the tape's manufacturer specifies on the tape's packaging or use the <emphasis
            role="bold">fms</emphasis> command to calculate the capacity, as described later in this section. To avoid having the
            Tape Coordinator reach the EOT unexpectedly, it is best to record in the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis>
            file or on the label a capacity that is about 10% smaller than the actual capacity of the tape. To calculate the
            appropriate value for a small tape used in compression mode, one method is to multiply the tape capacity (as recorded by
            the manufacturer) by the device's compression ratio.</para>

            <para>For tapes that hold multiple gigabytes or terabytes of data, or if using a tape drive's compression mode, the
            recommended configuration is to record a value quite a bit (for instance, two times) larger than the maximum amount you
            believe can fit on the tape. It is not generally worthwhile to run the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command on
            large tapes, even in noncompression mode. The command definitely does not yield accurate results in compression mode.
            The Tape Coordinator is likely to reach the EOT unexpectedly, but compression mode fits so much data on the tape that
            the data abandoned from an interrupted volume does not represent much of the tape's capacity.</para>

            <para>For a backup data file, record a value slightly smaller than the amount of space available on the partition, and
            definitely smaller than the operating system's maximum file size. It is also best to limit the ability of other
            processes to write to the partition, to prevent them from using up the space in the partition.</para>

            <para>If this field is empty, the Tape Coordinator uses the maximum acceptable value (2048 GB or 2 TB). Either leave
            both this field and the filemark_size field empty, or provide a value in both of them.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">filemark_size</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the tape device's filemark size, which usually falls between 2 KB and 2 MB. Use the same notation as for
            the capacity field, but note that if you omit the units letter, the default unit is bytes rather than kilobytes.</para>

            <para>For a tape device in regular (noncompression) mode, you can use the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command
            to determine filemark size, or use the value reported by the device's manufacturer. To help the Tape Coordinator avoid
            reaching EOT unexpectedly, increase the value by about 10% when recording it in the <emphasis
            role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file.</para>

            <para>The recommended value for a tape device in compression mode is <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero). The
            <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command does not yield accurate results in compression mode, so you cannot use it
            to determine the filemark size.</para>

            <para>The recommended value for a backup data file is also <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero). The Tape
            Coordinator does not use filemarks when writing to a file, but a value must appear in this field nevertheless if there
            is also a value in the capacity field.</para>

            <para>If this field is empty, the Tape Coordinator uses the value <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero). Either
            leave both this field and the capacity field empty, or provide a value in both of them.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">device_name</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the complete pathname of the tape device or backup data file. The format of tape device names depends on
            the operating system, but on UNIX systems, device names generally begin with the string <emphasis
            role="bold">/dev/</emphasis>. For a backup data file, this field defines the complete pathname, but for suggestions on
            how to name a backup data file, see <link linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping Data to a Backup Data File</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">port_offset</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the port offset number for a specific tape device or backup data file. Each tape device listens for
            backup requests on a different UNIX port. You pick the port indirectly by recording a value in this field. The Backup
            System sets the device's actual port by adding the port offset to a base port number that it determines
            internally.</para>

            <para>Legal values are the integers <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> through <emphasis role="bold">58510</emphasis>
            (the Backup System can track a maximum of 58,511 port offset numbers). Each value must be unique among the cell's Tape
            Coordinators, but you do not have to assign port offset numbers sequentially, and you can associate any number of them
            with a single machine or even tape device. For example, if you plan to use a device in both compression and
            noncompression mode, assign it two different port offsets with appropriate tape capacity and filemark values for the
            different modes.</para>

            <para>Assign port offset <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) to the Tape Coordinator for the tape device or backup
            data file that you use most often for backup operations; doing so enables you to omit the <emphasis
            role="bold">-portoffset</emphasis> argument from the largest possible number of <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
            commands.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para>The following example <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file includes entries for two tape devices, <emphasis
    role="bold">/dev/rmt0h</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/dev/rmt1h</emphasis>. Each one uses tapes with a capacity of 2 GB
    and has a filemark size of 1 MB. Their port offset numbers are <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>1</computeroutput>.</para>

    <programlisting>
   2g 1m /dev/rmt0h 0
   2G 1M /dev/rmt1h 1
</programlisting>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command reports the capacity of the tape you have inserted and the tape device's
    filemark size, both on the standard output stream (stdout) and in its <emphasis role="bold">fms.log</emphasis> file, which it
    writes in the current working directory. The command interpreter must write data to the entire tape, so running the command can
    take from several hours to more than a day, depending on the size of the tape.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ259">
      <title>To run the fms command on a noncompressing tape device</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fms.log file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>files</primary>

        <secondary>fms.log</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>log files</primary>

        <secondary>fms.log</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>fms</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>fms command</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an <emphasis role="bold">fms.log</emphasis> file does not already exist in the current directory, verify that you
          can insert and write to files in the current directory. If the log file already exists, you must be able to write to the
          file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Insert a tape into the drive. Running the command completely overwrites the tape, so use a blank tape or one that
          you want to recycle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape special file</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Must be typed in full.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">tape special file</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the tape device's UNIX device name, such as <emphasis role="bold">/dev/rmt0h</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example output reports that the tape in the device with device name <emphasis
      role="bold">/dev/rmt0h</emphasis> has a capacity of 2136604672 bytes (about 2 GB), and that the device's filemark size is
      1910205 bytes (close to 2 MB).</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fms /dev/rmt0h</emphasis>
   wrote block: 130408
   Finished data capacity test - rewinding
   wrote 1109 blocks, 1109 file marks
   Finished file mark test
   Tape capacity is 2136604672 bytes
   File marks are 1910205 bytes
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ260">
    <title>Granting Administrative Privilege to Backup Operators</title>

    <para>Each person who issues the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> commands in
    your cell must be listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis> file on every database server machine
    that stores the Backup Database and Volume Location Database (VLDB), and every machine that houses a volume included in a volume
    set. By convention, the <emphasis role="bold">UserList</emphasis> file is the same on every server machine in the cell; the
    instructions in this document assume that your cell is configured in this way. To edit the <emphasis
    role="bold">UserList</emphasis> file, use the <emphasis role="bold">bos adduser</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">bos
    removeuser</emphasis> commands as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ592">Administering the UserList File</link>.</para>

    <para>In addition to being listed in the <emphasis role="bold">UserList</emphasis> file, backup operators who issue the
    <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command must be able to write to the files stored in each Tape Coordinator machine's local
    <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory, which are protected by UNIX mode bits. Before configuring your
    cell's first Tape Coordinator machine, decide which local user and group to designate as the owner of the directory and the
    files in it. Among the possible ownership options are the following: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>. With this option, the issuer of the <emphasis
          role="bold">butc</emphasis> command must log onto the local file system as the local superuser <emphasis
          role="bold">root</emphasis>. If the Tape Coordinator is also a server machine, the <emphasis
          role="bold">-localauth</emphasis> flag is used on the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command to construct a server
          ticket from the local <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/KeyFile</emphasis> file. On non-server machine, the issuer must
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command to authenticate as an AFS administrator while logged in as
          <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A single AFS administrator. Logging in and authenticating are a single step if an AFS-modified login utility is
          used. The administrator is the only user who can start the Tape Coordinator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An administrative account for which several operators know the password. This allows them all to start the Tape
          Coordinator.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Another option is to define a group in the local group file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/group</emphasis> or equivalent) to
    which all backup operators belong. Then turn on the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> mode bit (<emphasis
    role="bold">write</emphasis> permission) in the group mode bits rather than the user mode bits of the <emphasis
    role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory and files in it. An advantage over the methods listed previously is that each
    operator can retain an individual administrative account for finer granularity in auditing.</para>

    <para>For instructions on implementing your choice of protection methods, see <link linkend="HDRWQ261">Configuring Tape
    Coordinator Machines and Tape Devices</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ261">
    <title>Configuring Tape Coordinator Machines and Tape Devices</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>configuring</secondary>

      <tertiary>machine</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>configuring</secondary>

      <tertiary>tape device</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>configuring</secondary>

      <tertiary>AIX system</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AIX</primary>

      <secondary>configuring tape device</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>This section explains how to configure a machine as a Tape Coordinator machine, and how to configure or remove the Tape
    Coordinator associated with a single tape device or backup data file.</para>

    <note>
      <para>When configuring a tape device attached to an AIX system, you must set the device's tape block size to <emphasis
      role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) to indicate variable block size. If you do not, it is possible that devices attached to
      machines of other system types cannot read the tapes made on the AIX system. Use the AIX <emphasis role="bold">smit</emphasis>
      program to verify or change the value of the tape block size for a tape device, as instructed in Sep <link
      linkend="LIWQ263">3</link>.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ262">
      <title>To configure a Tape Coordinator machine</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ263" />Install one or more tape devices on the Tape Coordinator machine according to the
          manufacturer's instructions. The Backup System can track a maximum of 58,511 tape devices or backup data files per
          cell.</para>

          <para>If the Tape Coordinator machine is an AIX system, issue the following command to change the tape device's tape block
          size to <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero), which indicates variable block size. Repeat for each tape
          device.</para>

          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chdev -l '</emphasis>device_name<emphasis role="bold">' -a block_size='0'</emphasis>
</programlisting>

          <para>where device_name is the tape device's device name (for example, <emphasis
          role="bold">/dev/rmt0h</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that the binary files for the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis>,
          and <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> commands are available on the local disk. If the machine is an AFS client, the
          conventional location is the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/etc</emphasis> directory. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">ls /usr/afsws/etc</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs</emphasis> directory. (If the Tape Coordinator machine is also configured
          as a file server machine, this directory already exists.) Then create the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis>
          directory. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">mkdir /usr/afs</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">mkdir /usr/afs/backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use a text editor to create the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file. Include a single
          line for each tape device or backup data file, specifying the following information in the indicated order. For syntax
          details and suggestions on the values to use in each field, see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig
          File</link>. <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The capacity of tapes to be used in the device, or the size of the backup data file</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's filemark size</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's device name, starting with the string <emphasis role="bold">/dev/</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's port offset number</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

            <secondary>assigning file ownership</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>usr/afs/backup directory</primary>

            <secondary>ownership, assigning</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>tapeconfig file</primary>

            <secondary>ownership, assigning</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>directories</primary>

            <secondary>/usr/afs/backup</secondary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Decide which user and group are to own the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory and <emphasis
          role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file, based on the suggestions in <link linkend="HDRWQ260">Granting
          Administrative Privilege to Backup Operators</link>. Correct the UNIX mode bits on the directory and file, if necessary.
          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chown</emphasis> admin_owner <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chown</emphasis> admin_owner <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chgrp</emphasis> admin_group <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chgrp</emphasis> admin_group <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chmod 774 /usr/afs/backup</emphasis>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chmod 664 /usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>backup addhost</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>backup commands</primary>

            <secondary>addhost</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

            <secondary>adding to Backup Database</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Backup Database</primary>

            <secondary>Tape Coordinator</secondary>

            <tertiary>adding entry</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LICONFTC-ADDHOST" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis> command to create a Tape
          Coordinator entry in the Backup Database. Repeat the command for each Tape Coordinator. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape machine name</replaceable>&gt; [&lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">addh</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">addhost</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">tape machine name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the Tape Coordinator machine's fully qualified hostname.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">TC port offset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the tape device's port offset number. Provide the same value as you specified for the device in
                  the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file. You must provide this argument unless the default value of 0
                  (zero) is appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_287">
      <title>To configure an additional Tape Coordinator on an existing Tape Coordinator machine</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the tape device on the Tape Coordinator machine according to the manufacturer's instructions.</para>

          <para>If the Tape Coordinator machine is an AIX system, issue the following command to change the tape device's tape block
          size to <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero), which indicates variable block size.</para>

          <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">chdev -l '</emphasis>device_name<emphasis role="bold">' -a block_size='0'</emphasis>
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the port offset number to assign to the tape device. If necessary, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup
          listhosts</emphasis> command to display the port offset numbers that are already used; for a discussion of the output, see
          <link linkend="HDRWQ264">To display the list of configured Tape Coordinators</link>. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">backup listhosts</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <emphasis role="bold">listh</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis
          role="bold">listhosts</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use a text editor to add one or more entries for the device to the <emphasis
          role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file. Specify the following information in the indicated order. For
          syntax details and suggestions on the values to use in each field, see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig
          File</link>. <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The capacity of tapes to be used in the device, or the size of the backup data file</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's filemark size</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's device name, starting with the string <emphasis role="bold">/dev/</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The device's port offset number</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis> command to create an entry in the Backup Database for the
          Tape Coordinator. For complete syntax, see Step <link linkend="LICONFTC-ADDHOST">8</link> in <link linkend="HDRWQ262">To
          configure a Tape Coordinator machine</link>. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape machine name</replaceable>&gt; [&lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>delhost</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup delhost</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>removing from Backup Database</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>Tape Coordinator</secondary>

        <tertiary>removing entry</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_288">
      <title>To unconfigure a Tape Coordinator</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using a text editor, remove each of the Tape Coordinator's entries from the <emphasis
          role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup delhost</emphasis> command to delete the Tape Coordinator's Backup Database
          entry. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup delhost</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape machine name</replaceable>&gt; [&lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">delh</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">delhost</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">tape machine name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the complete Internet host name of the Tape Coordinator machine.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">TC port offset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the same port offset number removed from the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file. You must
                  provide this argument unless the default value of <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) is appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>port offset number</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>port offset numbers</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>listhosts</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup listhosts</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ264">
      <title>To display the list of configured Tape Coordinators</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup listhosts</emphasis> command to list the Tape Coordinators and port offset
          numbers currently configured in the Backup Database. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup listhosts</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">listh</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">listhosts</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The output lists each Tape Coordinator machine and the port offset numbers currently allocated to it in the Backup
      Database. The appearance of a port offset number does not imply that the associated Tape Coordinator is actually running.
      Machine names appear in the format in which they were specified with the <emphasis role="bold">backup addhost</emphasis>
      command.</para>

      <para>The following example output lists the Tape Coordinators currently defined in the Backup Database of the ABC Corporation
      cell:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup listhosts</emphasis>
   Tape hosts:
       Host backup1.abc.com, port offset 0
       Host backup1.abc.com, port offset 2
       Host backup2.abc.com, port offset 1
       Host backup2.abc.com, port offset 3
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ265">
    <title>Defining and Displaying Volume Sets and Volume Entries</title>

    <para>The Backup System handles data at the level of volumes rather than individual files. You must define groups of volumes
    called <emphasis>volume sets</emphasis> before performing backup operations, by using the <emphasis role="bold">backup
    addvolset</emphasis> command. A volume set name can be up to 31 characters long and can include any character other than the
    period (<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>), but avoid using metacharacters that have special meanings to the shell.</para>

    <para>After creating a volume set, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup addvolentry</emphasis> command to place one or more
    <emphasis>volume entries</emphasis> in it. They define the volumes that belong to it in terms of their location (file server
    machine and partition) and name. Use the command's required <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> argument to designate the
    file server machine that houses the volumes of interest and its required <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> argument to
    designate the partition. Two types of values are acceptable: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The fully qualified hostname of one machine or full name of one partition (such as <emphasis
          role="bold">/vicepm</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The regular expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> (period and asterisk), which matches every machine name
          or partition name in the VLDB</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>regular expression</primary>

      <secondary>Backup System</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup System</primary>

      <secondary>regular expressions</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>For the volume name (the required <emphasis role="bold">-volume</emphasis> argument), specify a combination of
    alphanumeric characters and one or more metacharacters to specify part or all of the volume name with a wildcard. You can use
    any of the following metacharacters in the volume name field: <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The period matches any single character.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The asterisk matches zero or more instances of the preceding character. Combine it with any other alphanumeric
            character or metacharacter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">[ ]</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Square brackets around a list of characters match a single instance of any of the characters, but no other
            characters; for example, <emphasis role="bold">[abc]</emphasis> matches a single <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">c</emphasis>, but not <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>. You can combine this expression with the asterisk.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">^</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The caret, when used as the first character in a square-bracketed set, designates a match with any single
            character other than the characters that follow it; for example, <emphasis role="bold">[^a]</emphasis> matches any
            single character except lowercase <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis>. You can combine this expression with the
            asterisk.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">\</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A backslash preceding any of the metacharacters in this list makes it match its literal value only. For example,
            the expression <emphasis role="bold">\.</emphasis> (backslash and period) matches a single period, <emphasis
            role="bold">\*</emphasis> matches a single asterisk, and <emphasis role="bold">\\</emphasis> matches a single backslash.
            You can combine such expressions with the asterisk (for example, <emphasis role="bold">\.*</emphasis> matches any number
            of periods).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>

    <para>Perhaps the most common regular expression is the period followed by an asterisk (<emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis>).
    This expression matches any string of any length, because the period matches any character and the asterisk means any number of
    that character. As mentioned, it is the only acceptable regular expression in the file server and partition fields of a volume
    entry. In the volume name field, it can stand alone (in which case it matches every volume listed in the VLDB), or can combine
    with alphanumeric characters. For example, the string <emphasis role="bold">user.*\.backup</emphasis> matches any volume name
    that begins with the string <emphasis role="bold">user</emphasis> and ends with <emphasis role="bold">.backup</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Issuing the <emphasis role="bold">backup addvolentry</emphasis> command in interactive mode is simplest. If you issue it
    at the shell prompt, you must surround any string that includes a regular expression with double quotes (<emphasis role="bold">"
    "</emphasis>) so that the shell passes them uninterpreted to the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command interpreter
    rather than resolving them.</para>

    <para>To define various combinations of volumes, provide the following types of values for the <emphasis role="bold">backup
    addvolentry</emphasis> command's three arguments. The list uses the notation appropriate for interactive mode; if you issue the
    command at the shell prompt instead, place double quotes around any string that includes a regular expression. To create a
    volume entry that includes: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All volumes listed in the VLDB, use the regular expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> for all three
          arguments (<emphasis role="bold">-server .* -partition .* -volume .*</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Every volume on a specific file server machine, specify its fully qualified hostname as the <emphasis
          role="bold">-server</emphasis> argument and use the regular expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> for the
          <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> and -<emphasis role="bold">volume</emphasis> arguments (for example: <emphasis
          role="bold">-server fs1.abc.com -partition .* -volume .*</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All volumes that reside on a partition with the same name on various file server machines, specify the complete
          partition name as the <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> argument and use the regular expression <emphasis
          role="bold">.*</emphasis> for the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-volume</emphasis>
          arguments (for example: <emphasis role="bold">-server .* -partition /vicepd -volume .*</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Every volume with a common string in its name, use the regular expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> for
          the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> arguments, and provide a
          combination of alphanumeric characters and metacharacters as the <emphasis role="bold">-volume</emphasis> argument (for
          example: <emphasis role="bold">-server .* -partition .* -volume .*\.backup</emphasis> includes all volumes whose names end
          in the string <emphasis role="bold">.backup</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All volumes on one partition, specify the machine's fully qualified hostname as the <emphasis
          role="bold">-server</emphasis> argument and the full partition name as the <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis>
          argument, and use the regular expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> for the <emphasis
          role="bold">-volume</emphasis> argument (for example: <emphasis role="bold">-server fs2.abc.com -partition /vicepb -volume
          .*</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A single volume, specify its complete name as the <emphasis role="bold">-volume</emphasis> argument. To bypass the
          potentially time-consuming search through the VLDB for matching entries, you can specify an actual machine and partition
          name for the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> arguments
          respectively. However, if it is possible that you need to move the volume in future, it is best to use the regular
          expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> for the machine and partition name.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>As you create volume sets, define groups of volumes you want to dump to the same tape at the same time (for example,
    weekly or daily) and in the same manner (fully or incrementally). In general, a volume set that includes volumes with similar
    contents (as indicated by similar names) is more useful than one that includes volumes that share a common location, especially
    if you often move volumes for load-balancing or space reasons. Most often, then, it is appropriate to use the regular expression
    <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> (period followed by a backslash) for the <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> arguments to the <emphasis role="bold">backup addvolentry</emphasis> command.</para>

    <para>It is generally more efficient to include a limited number of volumes in a volume entry. Dumps of a volume set that
    includes a large number of volume can take a long time to complete, increasing the possibility that the operation fails due to a
    service interruption or outage.</para>

    <para>To remove a volume entry from a volume set, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup delvolentry</emphasis> command. To remove
    a volume set and all of its component volume entries from the Backup Database, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup
    delvolset</emphasis> command. To display the volume entries in a volume set, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup
    listvolsets</emphasis> command.</para>

    <para>By default, a Backup Database record is created for the new volume set. Sometimes it is convenient to create volume sets
    without recording them permanently in the Backup Database, for example when using the <emphasis role="bold">backup
    volsetrestore</emphasis> command to restore a group of volumes that were not necessarily backed up together (for further
    discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ312">Using the backup volsetrestore Command</link>). To create a
    <emphasis>temporary</emphasis> volume set, include the <emphasis role="bold">-temporary</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis
    role="bold">backup addvolset</emphasis> command. A temporary volume set exists only during the lifetime of the current
    interactive session, so the flag is effective only when used during an interactive session (opened by issuing the <emphasis
    role="bold">backup (interactive)</emphasis> command). You can use the <emphasis role="bold">backup delvolset</emphasis> command
    to delete a temporary volume set before the interactive session ends, if you wish, but as noted it is automatically deleted when
    you end the session. One advantage of temporary volume sets is that the <emphasis role="bold">backup addvolset</emphasis>
    command, and any <emphasis role="bold">backup addvolentry</emphasis> commands subsequently used to add volume entries to it,
    complete more quickly than for regular volume sets, because you are not creating any Backup Database records.</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup Database</primary>

      <secondary>volume set</secondary>

      <tertiary>creating</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>creating</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>commands</primary>

      <secondary>backup addvolset</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>backup commands</primary>

      <secondary>addvolset</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <sect2 id="Header_291">
      <title>To create a volume set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode. If you are going to define volume entries right away with the <emphasis role="bold">backup
          addvolentry</emphasis> command, this eliminates the need to surround metacharacter expressions with double quotes. You
          must enter interactive mode if creating a temporary volume set. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) addvolset</emphasis> command to create the volume set. You must then issue
          the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) addvolentry</emphasis> command to define volume entries in it. <programlisting>
   backup&gt;  <emphasis role="bold">addvolset</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt; [<emphasis role="bold">-temporary</emphasis>]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">addvols</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">addvolset</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume set name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the volume set. The name can include no more than 31 characters, cannot include periods, and must be
                  unique within the Backup Database. (A temporary volume set can have the same name as an existing permanent volume
                  set, but this is not recommended because of the confusion it can cause.)</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-temporary</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Creates a temporary volume set, which exists only during the current interactive session.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume entry (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>creating</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>volume entry</secondary>

        <tertiary>creating</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup addvolentry</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>addvolentry</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_292">
      <title>To add a volume entry to a volume set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode if you have not already. This makes it simpler to use metacharacter expressions, because you do not need
          to surround them with double quotes. If you are adding entries to a temporary volume set, you must already have entered
          interactive mode before creating the volume set. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) addvolentry</emphasis> command to define volume entries in an existing
          volume set. The Backup System assigns each volume entry an index within the volume set, starting with 1 (one).
          <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addvolentry  -name</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt;  \
                        <emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;  \
                        <emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>partition name</replaceable>&gt;  \
                        <emphasis role="bold">-volumes</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume name (regular expression)</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">addvole</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">addvolentry</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the volume set to which to add the volume entry. It must already exist (use the <emphasis
                  role="bold">backup addvolset</emphasis> command to create it).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-server</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Defines the set of one or more file server machines that house the volumes in the volume entry. Provide
                  either one fully-qualified hostname (such as <emphasis role="bold">fs1.abc.com</emphasis>) or the metacharacter
                  expression <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> (period and asterisk), which matches all machine names in the
                  VLDB.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-partition</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Defines the set of one or more partitions that house the volumes in the volume entry. Provide either one
                  complete partition name (such as <emphasis role="bold">/vicepa</emphasis>) or the metacharacter expression
                  <emphasis role="bold">.*</emphasis> (period and asterisk), which matches all partition names.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-volumes</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Defines the set of one or more volumes included in the volume entry, identifying them by name. This argument
                  can include a combination of alphanumeric characters and one or more of the metacharacter expressions discussed in
                  the introductory material in this section.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>volume set</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>volume entry</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>displaying</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume entry (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>displaying</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>listvolsets</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup listvolsets</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ266">
      <title>To display volume sets and volume entries</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup listvolsets</emphasis> command to display the volume entries in a specific
          volume set or all of them. If you are displaying a temporary volume set, you must still be in the interactive session in
          which you created it. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup listvolsets</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">listv</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">listvolsets</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume set name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the volume set to display. Omit this argument to display all defined volume sets.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>

          <para>The output from the command uses the wildcard notation used when the volume entries were created. The string
          <computeroutput>(temporary)</computeroutput> marks a temporary volume set. The following example displays all three of the
          volume sets defined in a cell's Backup Database, plus a temporary volume set <emphasis role="bold">pat+jones</emphasis>
          created during the current interactive session:</para>

          <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">listv</emphasis>
   Volume set pat+jones (temporary):
     Entry 1: server fs1.abc.com, partition /vicepe, volumes: user.pat.backup
     Entry 2: server fs5.abc.com, partition /viceph, volumes: user.jones.backup
   Volume set user:
     Entry 1: server .*, partition .*, volumes: user.*\.backup
   Volume set sun:
     Entry 1: server .*, partition .*, volumes: sun4x_55\..*
     Entry 2: server .*, partition .*, volumes: sun4x_56\..*
   Volume set rs:
     Entry 1: server .*, partition .*, volumes: rs_aix42\..*
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>volume set</secondary>

        <tertiary>deleting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>deleting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup delvolset</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>delvolset</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_294">
      <title>To delete a volume set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup delvolset</emphasis> command to delete one or more volume sets and all of the
          component volume entries in them. If you are deleting a temporary volume set, you must still be in the interactive session
          in which you created it. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup delvolset</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt;+
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">delvols</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">delvolset</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume set name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names each volume set to delete.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>volume entry</secondary>

        <tertiary>deleting from volume set</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume set (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>deleting volume entry</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>volume entry (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>deleting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup delvolentry</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>delvolentry</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_295">
      <title>To delete a volume entry from a volume set</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter interactive mode. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the volume set includes more than one volume entry, issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup)
          listvolsets</emphasis> command to display the index number associated with each one (if there is only one volume entry,
          its index is 1). For a more detailed description of the command's output, see <link linkend="HDRWQ266">To display volume
          sets and volume entries</link>. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">listvolsets</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">listv</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">listvolsets</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume set name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the volume set for which to display volume entries.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) delvolentry</emphasis> command to delete the volume entry. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">delvolentry</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume set name</replaceable>&gt;  &lt;<replaceable>volume entry index</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">delvole</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">delvolentry</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume set name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the volume set from which to delete a volume entry.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">volume entry index</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the index number of the volume entry to delete.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ267">
    <title>Defining and Displaying the Dump Hierarchy</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>creating</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

      <tertiary>assigning to dump levels</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>A dump hierarchy is a logical structure in the Backup Database that defines the relationship between full and incremental
    dumps; that is, it defines which dump serves as the parent for an incremental dump. Each individual component of a hierarchy is
    a dump level.</para>

    <para>As you define dump levels with the <emphasis role="bold">backup adddump</emphasis> command, keep the following rules and
    suggestions in mind: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each full dump level is the top level of a hierarchy. You can create as many hierarchies as you need to dump
          different volume sets on different schedules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of a full dump level consists of an initial slash (<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>), followed by a
          string of up to 28 alphanumeric characters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of an incremental dump level resembles a pathname, starting with the name of a full dump level, then the
          first incremental level, and so on, down to the final incremental level. Precede each level name with a slash to separate
          it from the preceding level. Like the full level, each component level in the name can have up to 28 alphanumeric
          characters, not including the slash.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A hierarchy can have any have any number of levels, but the maximum length of a complete dump level name is 256
          characters, including the slashes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Before defining a given incremental level, you must define all of the levels above it in the hierarchy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Do not use the period (<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>) in dump level names. The Backup System uses the period as
          the separator between a dump's volume set name and dump level name when it creates the dump name and AFS tape name. Any
          other alphanumeric and punctuation characters are allowed, but it is best to avoid metacharacters. If you include a
          metacharacter, you must precede it with a backslash (<emphasis role="bold">\</emphasis>) or surround the entire dump level
          name with double quotes (<emphasis role="bold">" "</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Naming dump levels for days or other actual time points reminds you when to perform dumps, and makes it easier to
          track the relationship between dumps performed at different levels. However, the names have no meaning to the Backup
          System: it does not automatically create dumps according to the names, and does not prevent you from, for example, using
          the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday</emphasis> level when creating a dump on a Tuesday.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It is best not to use the same name for more than one component level in a hierarchy, because it means the resulting
          dump name no longer indicates which level was used. For example, if you name a dump level <emphasis
          role="bold">/full/incr/incr</emphasis>, then the dump name and AFS tape name that result from dumping a volume set at the
          first incremental level (<emphasis role="bold">/full/incr</emphasis>) look the same as the names that result from dumping
          at the second incremental level (<emphasis role="bold">/full/incr/incr</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Individual levels in different hierarchies can have the same name, but the complete pathnames must be unique. For
          example, <emphasis role="bold">/sunday1/monday</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/sunday2/monday</emphasis> share the
          same name at the final level, but are unique because they have different names at the full level (belong to different
          hierarchies). However, using the same name in multiple hierarchies means that dump and AFS tape names do not unambiguously
          indicate which hierarchy was used.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The following example shows three hierarchies. Each begins with a full dump at the top: <emphasis
    role="bold">sunday1</emphasis> for the first hierarchy, <emphasis role="bold">sunday2</emphasis> for the second hierarchy, and
    <emphasis role="bold">sunday_bin</emphasis> for the third hierarchy. In all three hierarchies, each of the other dump levels is
    an incremental level.</para>

    <programlisting>
   /sunday1
           /monday
           /tuesday
           /wednesday
           /thursday
           /friday
   /sunday2
           /monday
                  /tuesday
                          /wednesday
                                    /thursday
                                             /friday
    /sunday_bin
               /monday
                      /wednesday
                                /friday
</programlisting>

    <para>In the first hierarchy, each incremental dump level refers to the full level <emphasis role="bold">/sunday1</emphasis> as
    its parent. When (for example) you dump a volume set at the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday1/wednesday</emphasis> level, it
    includes data that has changed since the volume set was dumped at the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday1</emphasis> level.</para>

    <para>In contrast, each incremental dump level in the second hierarchy refers to the immediately preceding dump level as its
    parent. When you dump a volume set at the corresponding level in the second hierarchy (<emphasis
    role="bold">/sunday2/monday/tuesday/wednesday</emphasis>), the dump includes only data that has changed since the volume set was
    dumped at the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday2/monday/tuesday</emphasis> level (presumably the day before). Assuming you create
    dumps on the indicated days, an incremental dump made using this hierarchy contains less data than an incremental dump made at
    the corresponding level in the first hierarchy.</para>

    <para>The third hierarchy is more appropriate for dumping volumes for which a daily backup is excessive because the data does
    not change often (for example, system binaries).</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ268">
      <title>Creating a Tape Recycling Schedule</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>expiration dates</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>expiration dates</primary>

        <secondary>absolute</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>expiration dates</primary>

        <secondary>relative</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>recycling schedule for tapes</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tape recycling schedules</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>If your cell is like most cells, you have a limited amount of room for storing backup tapes and a limited budget for new
      tapes. The easiest solution is to recycle tapes by overwriting them when you no longer need the backup data on them. The
      Backup System helps you implement a recycling schedule by enabling you to associate an expiration date with each dump level.
      The expiration date defines when a dump created at that level expires. Until that time the Backup System refuses to overwrite
      a tape that contains the dump. Thus, assigning expiration dates automatically determines how you recycle tapes.</para>

      <para>When designing a tape-recycling schedule, you must decide how far in the past and to what level of precision you want to
      guarantee access to backed up data. For instance, if you decide to guarantee that you can restore a user's home volume to its
      state on any given day in the last two weeks, you cannot recycle the tape that contains a given daily dump for at least two
      weeks after you create it. Similarly, if you decide to guarantee that you can restore home volumes to their state at the
      beginning of any given week in the last month, you cannot recycle the tapes in a dump set containing a weekly dump for at
      least four weeks. The following example dump hierarchy implements this recycling schedule by setting the expiration date for
      each daily incremental dump to 13 days and the expiration date of the weekly full dumps to 27 days.</para>

      <para>The tapes used to store dumps created at the daily incremental levels in the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday1</emphasis>
      hierarchy expire just in time to be recycled for daily dumps in the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday3</emphasis> hierarchy (and
      vice versa), and there is a similar relationship between the <emphasis role="bold">/sunday2</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">/sunday4</emphasis> hierarchies. Similarly, the tape that houses a full dump at the <emphasis
      role="bold">/sunday1</emphasis> level expires just in time to be used for a full dump on the first Sunday of the following
      month.</para>

      <programlisting>
   /sunday1   expires in 27d
           /monday1  expires in 13d
           /tuesday1  expires in 13d
           /wednesday1  expires in 13d
           /thursday1  expires in 13d
           /friday1  expires in 13d
   /sunday2   expires in 27d
           /monday2  expires in 13d
           /tuesday2  expires in 13d
           /wednesday2  expires in 13d
           /thursday2  expires in 13d
           /friday2  expires in 13d
   /sunday3   expires in 27d
           /monday1  expires in 13d
           /tuesday1  expires in 13d
           /wednesday1  expires in 13d
           /thursday1  expires in 13d
           /friday1  expires in 13d
   /sunday4   expires in 27d
           /monday2  expires in 13d
           /tuesday2  expires in 13d
           /wednesday2  expires in 13d
           /thursday2  expires in 13d
           /friday2  expires in 13d
</programlisting>

      <para>If you use appended dumps in your cell, keep in mind that all dumps in a dump set are subject to the latest (furthest
      into the future) expiration date associated with any of the constituent dumps. You cannot recycle any of the tapes that
      contain a dump set until all of the dumps have reached their expiration date. See also <link linkend="HDRWQ299">Appending
      Dumps to an Existing Dump Set</link>.</para>

      <para>Most tape manufacturers recommend that you write to a tape a limited number of times, and it is best not to exceed this
      limit when recycling tapes. To help you track tape usage, the Backup System records a
      <computeroutput>useCount</computeroutput> counter on the tape's label. It increments the counter each time the tape's label is
      rewritten (each time you use the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">backup
      dump</emphasis> command). To display the <computeroutput>useCount</computeroutput> counter, use the <emphasis
      role="bold">backup readlabel</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">backup scantape</emphasis> command or include the <emphasis
      role="bold">-id</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis> options when you issue the <emphasis
      role="bold">backup dumpinfo</emphasis> command. For instructions see <link linkend="HDRWQ272">Writing and Reading Tape
      Labels</link> or <link linkend="HDRWQ302">Displaying Backup Dump Records</link>.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>useCount counter on tape label (Backup System)</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>useCount counter on tape label</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>recycling</primary>

        <secondary>useCounts of tapes (Backup System)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tape labels</primary>

        <secondary>useCounts of tapes</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ269">
      <title>Archiving Tapes</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>archiving</primary>

        <secondary>tapes in Backup System</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>archiving</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Even if you make extensive use of tape recycling, there is probably some backup data that you need to archive for a long
      (or even an indefinite) period of time. You can use the Backup System to archive data on a regular schedule, and you can also
      choose to archive data on tapes that you previously expected to recycle.</para>

      <para>If you want to archive data on a regular basis, you can create date-specific dump levels in the dump hierarchy. For
      example, if you decide to archive a full dump of all data in your cell at the beginning of each quarter in the year 2000, you
      can define the following levels in the dump hierarchy:</para>

      <programlisting>
   /1Q2000
   /2Q2000
   /3Q2000
   /4Q2000
</programlisting>

      <para>If you decide to archive data that is on tapes you previously planned to recycle, you must gather all of the tapes that
      contain the relevant dumps, both full and incremental. To avoid accidental erasure, it is best to set the switch on the tapes
      that makes them read-only, before placing them in your archive storage area. If the tapes also contain a large amount of
      extraneous data that you do not want to archive, you can restore just the relevant data into a new temporary volume, and back
      up that volume to the smallest number of tapes possible. One reason to keep a dump set small is to minimize the amount of
      irrelevant data in a dump set you end up needing to archive.</para>

      <para>If you do not expect to restore archived data to the file system, you can consider using the <emphasis
      role="bold">backup deletedump</emphasis> command to remove the associated dump records from the Backup Database, which helps
      keep it to an efficient size. If you ever need to restore the data, you can use the <emphasis role="bold">-dbadd</emphasis>
      flag to the <emphasis role="bold">backup scantape</emphasis> command to reinsert the dump records into the database. For
      instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ305">To scan the contents of a tape</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ270">
      <title>Defining Expiration Dates</title>

      <para>To associate an expiration date with a dump level as you create it, use the <emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis>
      argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup adddump</emphasis> command. To change an existing dump level's expiration date,
      use the <emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup setexp</emphasis> command.
      (Note that it is not possible to change the expiration date of an actual dump that has already been created at that level).
      With both commands, you can define an expiration date either in absolute terms (for example, 13 January 2000) or relative
      terms (for example, 30 days from when the dump is created). <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To define an absolute expiration date, provide a value for the <emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis> argument
            with the following format: <programlisting>
   [<emphasis role="bold">at</emphasis>] mm<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>dd<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>yyyy [hh<emphasis
                  role="bold">:</emphasis>MM]
</programlisting></para>

            <para>where mm indicates the month, dd the day, and yyyy the year when the dump expires. Valid values for the year fall
            in the range <emphasis role="bold">1970</emphasis> through <emphasis role="bold">2037</emphasis> (the latest possible
            date that the UNIX time representation can express is in early 2038). If you provide a time, it must be in 24-hour
            format with hh the hours and MM the minutes (for example, <emphasis role="bold">21:50</emphasis> is 9:50 p.m.). If you
            omit the time, the default is 00:00 hours (12:00 midnight) on the indicated date.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To define a relative expiration date, provide a value for the <emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis> argument
            with the following format: <programlisting>
   [<emphasis role="bold">in</emphasis>] [years<emphasis role="bold">y</emphasis>] [months<emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis>] [days<emphasis
                  role="bold">d</emphasis>]
</programlisting></para>

            <para>where each of years, months, and days is an integer. Provide at least one of them together with the corresponding
            units letter (<emphasis role="bold">y</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis>, or <emphasis
            role="bold">d</emphasis> respectively), with no intervening space. If you provide more than one of the three, list them
            in the indicated order.</para>

            <para>The Backup System calculates a dump's actual expiration date by adding the indicated relative value to the start
            time of the dump operation. For example, it assigns an expiration date 1 year, 6 months, and 2 days in the future to a
            dump created at a dump level with associated expiration date <emphasis role="bold">in 1y 6m 2d</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To indicate that a dump backed up at the corresponding dump level never expires, provide the value <emphasis
            role="bold">NEVER</emphasis> instead of a date and time. To recycle tapes that contain dumps created at such a level,
            you must use the <emphasis role="bold">backup readlabel</emphasis> command to overwrite the tape's label.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If you omit the <emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup
      adddump</emphasis> command, then the expiration date is set to UNIX time zero (00:00 hours on 1 January 1970). The Backup
      System considers dumps created at such a dump level to expire at their creation time. If no dumps in a dump set have an
      expiration date, then the Backup System does not impose any restriction on recycling the tapes that contain the dump set. If
      you need to prevent premature recycling of the tapes that contain the dump set, you must use a manual tracking system.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>dump levels</secondary>

        <tertiary>adding</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>in Backup Database</secondary>

        <tertiary>adding</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>dump levels</secondary>

        <tertiary>adding</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>expiration dates</primary>

        <secondary>setting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>adddump</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup adddump</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_300">
      <title>To add a dump level to the dump hierarchy</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup adddump</emphasis> command to define one or more dump levels. If you are
          defining an incremental level, then all of the parent levels that precede it in its pathname must either already exist or
          precede it on the command line. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">adddump -dump</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>dump level name</replaceable>&gt;+ [<emphasis
                role="bold">-expires</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>expiration date</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">addd</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">adddump</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-dump</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names each dump level to added. If you specify more than one dump level name, you must include the <emphasis
                  role="bold">-dump</emphasis> switch.</para>

                  <para>Provide the entire pathname of the dump level, preceding each level in the pathname with a slash (<emphasis
                  role="bold">/</emphasis>). Each component level can be up to 28 characters in length, and the pathname can include
                  up to 256 characters including the slashes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sets the expiration date associated with each dump level. Specify either a relative or absolute expiration
                  date, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ270">Defining Expiration Dates</link>, or omit this argument to assign
                  no expiration date to the dump levels.</para>

                  <note>
                    <para>A plus sign follows this argument in the command's syntax statement because it accepts a multiword value
                    which does not need to be enclosed in double quotes or other delimiters, not because it accepts multiple dates.
                    Provide only one date (and optionally, time) definition to be associated with each dump level specified by the
                    <emphasis role="bold">-dump</emphasis> argument.</para>
                  </note>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>expiration dates</primary>

        <secondary>changing</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>changing</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>changing</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>expiration dates</secondary>

        <tertiary>changing</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>setexp</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup setexp</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_301">
      <title>To change a dump level's expiration date</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) setexp</emphasis> command to change the expiration date associated with one
          or more dump levels. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">setexp -dump</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>dump level name</replaceable>&gt;+ [<emphasis
                role="bold">-expires</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>expiration date</replaceable>&gt;+]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">se</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">setexp</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-dump</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names each existing dump level for which to change the expiration date.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-expires</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sets the expiration date associated with each dump level. Specify either a relative or absolute expiration
                  date, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ270">Defining Expiration Dates</link>; omit this argument to remove the
                  expiration date currently associated with each dump level.</para>

                  <note>
                    <para>A plus sign follows this argument in the command's syntax statement because it accepts a multiword value
                    which does not need to be enclosed in double quotes or other delimiters, not because it accepts multiple dates.
                    Provide only one date (and optionally, time) definition to be associated with each dump level specified by the
                    <emphasis role="bold">-dump</emphasis> argument.</para>
                  </note>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>dump levels</secondary>

        <tertiary>deleting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>in Backup Database</secondary>

        <tertiary>deleting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>dump levels</secondary>

        <tertiary>deleting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>deldump</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup deldump</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_302">
      <title>To delete a dump level from the dump hierarchy</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) deldump</emphasis> command to delete the dump level. Note that the command
          automatically removes all incremental dump levels for which the specified level serves as parent, either directly or
          indirectly. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">deldump</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>dump level name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">deld</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">deldump</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">dump level name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the complete pathname of the dump level to delete.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>dump hierarchy</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup Database</primary>

        <secondary>dump levels</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump hierarchy (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>displaying</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>dump levels</primary>

        <secondary>in Backup Database</secondary>

        <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>listdumps</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup listdumps</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ271">
      <title>To display the dump hierarchy</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup listdumps</emphasis> command to display the dump hierarchy. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup listdumps</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <emphasis role="bold">listd</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis
          role="bold">listdumps</emphasis>.</para>

          <para>The output from this command displays the dump hierarchy, reporting the expiration date associated with each dump
          level, as in the following example.</para>

          <programlisting>
    % <emphasis role="bold">backup listdumps</emphasis>
   /week1  expires in  27d
         /tuesday  expires in  13d
                 /thursday  expires in  13d
         /sunday  expires in  13d
                /tuesday expires in  13d
                        /thursday expires in  13d
   /week3  expires in  27d
         /tuesday  expires in  13d
                 /thursday  expires in  13d
         /sunday  expires in  13d
                /tuesday  expires in  13d
                        /thursday  expires in  13d
   sunday1   expires in  27d
          /monday1  expires in  13d
          /tuesday1  expires in  13d 
          /wednesday1  expires in  13d
          /thursday1  expires in  13d
          /friday1  expires in  13d
   sunday2   expires in  27d
          /monday2  expires in  13d
          /tuesday2  expires in  13d
          /wednesday2  expires in  13d
          /thursday2  expires in  13d
          /friday2  expires in  13d
   sunday3   expires in  27d
          /monday1  expires in  13d
          /tuesday1  expires in  13d 
          /wednesday1  expires in  13d
          /thursday1  expires in  13d
          /friday1  expires in  13d
   sunday4   expires in  27d
          /monday2  expires in  13d
          /tuesday2  expires in  13d
          /wednesday2  expires in  13d
          /thursday2  expires in  13d
          /friday2  expires in  13d
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ272">
    <title>Writing and Reading Tape Labels</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>label</secondary>

      <tertiary>creating</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>label</secondary>

      <tertiary>displaying</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>capacity</secondary>

      <tertiary>recording on label</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

      <secondary>names</secondary>

      <tertiary>assigning</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>tape label (Backup System)</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>displaying</primary>

      <secondary>tape label (Backup System)</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>As described in <link linkend="HDRWQ253">Dump Names and Tape Names</link> and <link linkend="HDRWQ254">Tape Labels, Dump
    Labels, and EOF Markers</link>, you can assign either a permanent name or an AFS tape name to a tape that you use in the Backup
    System. The names are recorded on the tape's magnetic label, along with an indication of the tape's capacity (size).</para>

    <para>You can assign either a permanent name or an AFS tape name, but not both. In general, assigning permanent names rather
    than AFS tape names simplifies the backup process, because the Backup System does not dictate the format of permanent names. If
    a tape does not have a permanent name, then by default the Backup System accepts only three strictly defined values in the AFS
    tape name field, and refuses to write a dump to a tape with an inappropriate AFS tape name. The acceptable values are a name
    that matches the volume set and dump level of the initial dump, the value <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>, and no
    value in the field at all.</para>

    <para>If a tape has a permanent name, the Backup System does not check the AFS tape name, and as part of the dump operation
    constructs the appropriate AFS tape name itself and records it on the label. This means that if you assign a permanent name, the
    Backup System assigns an AFS tape name itself and the tape has both types of name. In contrast, if a tape has an AFS tape name
    but not a permanent name, you cannot assign a permanent name without first erasing the AFS tape name.</para>

    <para>(You can also suppress the Backup System's check of a tape's AFS tape name, even it does not have a permanent name, by
    assigning the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="bold">NAME_CHECK</emphasis> instruction in the
    <emphasis>device configuration file</emphasis>. See <link linkend="HDRWQ280">Eliminating the AFS Tape Name Check</link>.)</para>

    <para>Because the Backup System accepts unlabeled tapes, you do not have to label a tape before using it for the first time.
    After the first use, there are a couple of cases in which you must relabel a tape in order to write a dump to it: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The tape does not have a permanent name, and the AFS tape name on it does not match the new initial dump set you
          want to create (the volume set and dump level names are different, or the index is incorrect).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You want to recycle a tape before all of the dumps on it have expired. The Backup System does not overwrite a tape
          with any unexpired dumps. Keep in mind, though, that if you relabel the tape to making recycling possible, you erase all
          the dump records for the tape from the Backup Database, which makes it impossible to restore any data from the
          tape.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <note>
      <para>Labeling a tape that contains dump data makes it impossible to use that data in a restore operation, because the
      labeling operation removes the dump's records from the Backup Database. If you want to record a permanent name on a tape
      label, you must do it before dumping any data to the tape.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="Header_305">
      <title>Recording a Name on the Label</title>

      <para>To write a permanent name on a tape's label, include the <emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument to specify a
      string of up to 32 characters. Check that no other tape used with the Backup System in your cell already has the permanent
      name you are assigning, because the Backup System does not prevent you from assigning the same name to multiple tapes. The
      Backup System overwrites the existing AFS tape name, if any, with the value <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>.
      When a tape has a permanent name, the Backup System uses it instead of the AFS tape name in most prompts and when referring to
      the tape in output from <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> commands. The permanent name persists until you again include
      the <emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command,
      regardless of the tape's contents and of how often you recycle the tape or use the <emphasis role="bold">backup
      labeltape</emphasis> command without the <emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument.</para>

      <para>To write an AFS tape name on the label, provide a value for the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument that
      matches the volume set name and the final element in the dump level pathname of the initial dump that you plan to write to the
      tape, and an index that indicates the tape's place in the sequence of tapes for the dump set. The format is as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>
   volume_set_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>dump_level_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>tape_index
</programlisting>

      <para>If you omit the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument, the Backup System sets the AFS tape name to
      <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>. The Backup System automatically constructs and records the appropriate name
      when you later write an initial dump to the tape by using the <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="bold">backup savedb</emphasis> command.</para>

      <para>You cannot use the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument if the tape already has a permanent name. To erase a
      tape's permanent name, provide a null value to the <emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument by issuing the following
      command:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape -pname ""</emphasis>
</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_306">
      <title>Recording a Capacity on the Label</title>

      <para>To record the tape's capacity on the label, specify a number of kilobytes as the <emphasis role="bold">-size</emphasis>
      argument. If you omit this argument the first time you label a tape, the Backup System records the default tape capacity
      associated with the specified port offset in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file on the Tape
      Coordinator machine. If the tape's capacity is different (in particular, larger) than the capacity recorded in the <emphasis
      role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file, it is best to record a capacity on the label before using the tape. Once set, the
      value in the label's capacity field persists until you again use the <emphasis role="bold">-size</emphasis> argument to the
      <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command. For a discussion of the appropriate capacity to record for tapes,
      see <link linkend="HDRWQ258">Configuring the tapeconfig File</link>.</para>

      <para>To read a tape's label, use the <emphasis role="bold">backup readlabel</emphasis> command.</para>

      <para>Most tapes also come with an adhesive label you can apply to the exterior casing. To help you easily identify a tape,
      record at least the tape's permanent and AFS tape names on the adhesive label. Depending on the recycling scheme you use, it
      can be useful to record other information, such as the dump ID, dump creation date, and expiration date of each dump you write
      to the tape.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>labeltape</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup labeltape</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ273">
      <title>To label a tape</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Tape Coordinator for the tape device that is to perform the operation is not already running, open a
          connection to the appropriate Tape Coordinator machine and issue the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command, for
          which complete instructions appear in <link linkend="HDRWQ292">To start a Tape Coordinator process</link>.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>port offset</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis>]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Place the tape in the device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode, if you want to label multiple tapes or issue additional commands after labeling the tape. The
          interactive prompt appears in the following step. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) labeltape</emphasis> command to label the tape. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">labeltape</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape name, defaults to NULL</replaceable>&gt;]  \
      [<emphasis role="bold">-size</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape size in Kbytes, defaults to size in tapeconfig</replaceable>&gt;]  \
      [<emphasis role="bold">-portoffset</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>permanent tape name</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">la</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">labeltape</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the AFS tape name to record on the label. Include this argument or the <emphasis
                  role="bold">-pname</emphasis> argument, but not both. If you omit this argument, the AFS tape name is set to
                  &lt;<replaceable>NULL</replaceable>&gt;. If you provide it, it must have the following format. <programlisting>
volume_set_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>dump_level_name<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>tape_index
</programlisting></para>

                  <para>for the tape to be acceptable for use in a future <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> operation.
                  The volume_set_name must match the volume set name of the initial dump to be written to the tape, dump_level_name
                  must match the last element of the dump level pathname at which the volume set is to be dumped, and tape_index
                  must correctly indicate the tape's place in the sequence of tapes that house the dump set; indexing begins with
                  the number 1 (one).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-size</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the tape capacity to record on the label. If you are labeling the tape for the first time, you
                  need to include this argument only if the tape's capacity differs from the capacity associated with the specified
                  port offset in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file on the Tape Coordinator
                  machine.</para>

                  <para>If you provide a value, it is an integer value followed by a letter that indicates units, with no
                  intervening space. A unit value of <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis>
                  indicates kilobytes, <emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> indicates megabytes,
                  and <emphasis role="bold">g</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis> indicates gigabytes. If you omit the
                  units letter, the default is kilobytes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-portoffset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the port offset number of the Tape Coordinator handling the tape or backup data file for this
                  operation. You must provide this argument unless the default value of <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) is
                  appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-pname</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the permanent name to record on the label. It can be up to 32 characters in length, and include
                  any alphanumeric characters. Avoid metacharacters that have a special meaning to the shell, to avoid having to
                  mark them as literal in commands issued at the shell prompt.</para>

                  <para>Include this argument or the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument, but not both. When you provide
                  this argument, the AFS tape name is set to <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>. If you omit this
                  argument, any existing permanent name is retained.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you did not include the <emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis> flag when you issued the <emphasis
          role="bold">butc</emphasis> command, or if the device's device configuration file includes the instruction <emphasis
          role="bold">AUTOQUERY YES</emphasis>, then the Tape Coordinator prompts you to place the tape in the device's drive. You
          have already done so, but you must now press <emphasis role="bold">&lt;Return&gt;</emphasis> to indicate that the tape is
          ready for labeling.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>backup commands</primary>

        <secondary>readlabel</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>backup readlabel</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ274">
      <title>To read the label on a tape</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Tape Coordinator for the tape device that is to perform the operation is not already running, open a
          connection to the appropriate Tape Coordinator machine and issue the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command, for
          which complete instructions appear in <link linkend="HDRWQ292">To start a Tape Coordinator process</link>.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>port offset</replaceable>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis>]
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Place the tape in the device.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode, if you want to label multiple tapes or issue additional commands after labeling the tape. The
          interactive prompt appears in the following step. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) readlabel</emphasis> command to read the label on the tape.
          <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">readlabel</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">rea</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">readlabel</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">TC port offset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the port offset number of Tape Coordinator handling the tape or backup data file for this
                  operation. You must provide this argument unless the default value of <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) is
                  appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you did not include the <emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis> flag when you issued the <emphasis
          role="bold">butc</emphasis> command, or the device's device configuration file includes the instruction <emphasis
          role="bold">AUTOQUERY YES</emphasis> instruction, then the Tape Coordinator prompts you to place the tape in the device's
          drive. You have already done so, but you must now press <emphasis role="bold">&lt;Return&gt;</emphasis> to indicate that
          the tape is ready for reading.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Information from the tape label appears both in the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command window and in the
      Tape Coordinator window. The output in the command window has the following format:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Tape read was labelled: tape_name (initial_dump_ID)
        size: size KBytes
</programlisting>

      <para>where tape_name is the tape's permanent name (if it has one) or AFS tape name, initial_dump_ID is the dump ID of the
      initial dump on the tape, and size is the capacity recorded on the label, in kilobytes.</para>

      <para>The information in the Tape Coordinator window is more extensive. The tape's permanent name appears in the
      <computeroutput>tape name</computeroutput> field and its AFS tape name in the <computeroutput>AFS tape name</computeroutput>
      field. If either name is undefined, a value of <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput> appears in the field instead. The
      capacity recorded on the label appears in the <computeroutput>size</computeroutput> field. Other fields in the output report
      the creation time, dump level name, and dump ID of the initial dump on the tape
      (<computeroutput>creationTime</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>dump path</computeroutput>, and <computeroutput>dump
      id</computeroutput> respectively). The <computeroutput>cell</computeroutput> field reports the cell in which the dump
      operation was performed, and the <computeroutput>useCount</computeroutput> field reports the number of times the tape has been
      relabeled, either with the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command or during a dump operation. For further
      details, see the command's reference page in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Reference</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>If the tape has no label, or if the drive is empty, the following message appears at the command shell:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Failed to read tape label.
</programlisting>

      <para>The following example illustrates the output in the command shell for a tape in the device with port offset 1:</para>

      <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">backup readlabel 1</emphasis>
   Tape read was labelled: monthly_guest (917860000)
        size: 2150000 KBytes
</programlisting>

      <para>The following output appears in the Tape Coordinator window at the same time:</para>

      <programlisting>
   Tape label
   ----------
   tape name = monthly_guest
   AFS tape name = guests.monthly.3
   creationTime =  Mon Feb  1 04:06:40 1999
   cell = abc.com
   size = 2150000 Kbytes
   dump path = /monthly
   dump id = 917860000
   useCount = 44
   -- End of tape label --
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ275">
    <title>Automating and Increasing the Efficiency of the Backup Process</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup System</primary>

      <secondary>automating operations</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Backup System</primary>

      <secondary>reducing operator intervention</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The Backup System includes several optional features to help you automate the backup process in your cell and make it more
    efficient. By combining several of the features, you can dump volume data to tape with minimal human intervention in most cases.
    To take advantage of many of the features, you create a device configuration file in the <emphasis
    role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory for each tape device that participates in automated operations. For general
    instructions on creating the device configuration file, see <link linkend="HDRWQ276">Creating a Device Configuration
    File</link>. The following list refers you to sections that describe each feature in greater detail. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can use tape stackers and jukeboxes to perform backup operations. These are tape drives with an attached unit
          that stores several tapes and can physically insert and remove them from the tape reader (tape drive) without human
          intervention, meaning that no operator has to be present even for backup operations that require several tapes. To use a
          stacker or jukebox with the Backup System, include the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instructions in its device configuration file. See <link linkend="HDRWQ277">Invoking a
          Device's Tape Mounting and Unmounting Routines</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can suppress the Tape Coordinator's default prompt for the initial tape that it needs for a backup operation,
          again eliminating the need for a human operator to be present when a backup operation begins. (You must still insert the
          correct tape in the drive at some point before the operation begins.) To suppress the initial prompt, include the
          <emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis> flag on the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command, or assign the
          value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="bold">AUTOQUERY</emphasis> instruction in the device
          configuration file. See <link linkend="HDRWQ278">Eliminating the Search or Prompt for the Initial Tape</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can suppress the prompts that the Tape Coordinator otherwise generates when it encounters several types of
          errors. When you use this feature, the Tape Coordinator instead responds to the errors in a default manner, which
          generally allows the operation to continue without human intervention. To suppress prompts about error conditions, assign
          the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="bold">ASK</emphasis> instruction in the device
          configuration file. See <link linkend="HDRWQ279">Enabling Default Responses to Error Conditions</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can suppress the Backup System's default verification that the AFS tape name on a tape that has no permanent
          name matches the name derived from the volume set and dump level names of the initial dump the Backup System is writing to
          the tape. This enables you to recycle a tape without first relabeling it, as long as all dumps on it are expired. To
          suppress name checking, assign the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis> to the <emphasis
          role="bold">NAME_CHECK</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file. See <link linkend="HDRWQ280">Eliminating
          the AFS Tape Name Check</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can promote tape streaming (the most efficient way for a tape device to operate) by setting the size of the
          memory buffer the Tape Coordinator uses when transferring volume data between the file system and the device. To set the
          buffer size, include the <emphasis role="bold">BUFFERSIZE</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file. See
          <link linkend="HDRWQ281">Setting the Memory Buffer Size to Promote Tape Streaming</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can write dumps to a <emphasis>backup data file</emphasis> on the local disk of the Tape Coordinator machine,
          rather than to tape. You can then transfer the backup data file to a data-archiving system, such as a hierarchical storage
          management (HSM) system, that you use in conjunction with AFS and the Backup System. Writing a dump to a file is usually
          more efficient that issuing the equivalent <emphasis role="bold">vos dump</emphasis> commands individually. To write dumps
          to a file, include the <emphasis role="bold">FILE</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file. See <link
          linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping Data to a Backup Data File</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>There are two additional ways to increase backup automation and efficiency that do not involve the device configuration
    file: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can schedule one or more <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> commands to run at specified times. This
          enables you to create backups at times of low system usage, without requiring a human operator to be present. You can
          schedule a single dump operation for a future time, or multiple operations to run at various future times. See <link
          linkend="HDRWQ300">Scheduling Dumps</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can append dumps to a tape that already has other dumps on it. This enables you to use as much of a tape's
          capacity as possible. The appended dumps do not have be related in any way to one another or to the initial dump on the
          tape, but grouping dumps appropriately can reduce the number of necessary tape changes during a restore operation. To
          append a dump, include the <emphasis role="bold">-append</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup
          dump</emphasis> command. See <link linkend="HDRWQ299">Appending Dumps to an Existing Dump Set</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ276">
      <title>Creating a Device Configuration File</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>files</primary>

        <secondary>CFG_&lt;device_name&gt;</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>device configuration file (CFG)</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>configuration file</primary>

        <secondary></secondary>

        <see>CFG_&lt;device_name&gt; configuration file</see>
      </indexterm>

      <para>To use many of the features that automate backup operations, create a configuration file for each tape device in the
      <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory on the local disk of the Tape Coordinator machine that drives the
      device. The filename has the following form:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">CFG_</emphasis>device_name</para>

      <para>where device_name represents the name of the tape device or backup data file (see <link linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping Data
      to a Backup Data File</link> to learn about writing dumps to a file rather than to tape).</para>

      <para>For a tape device, construct the device_name portion of the name by stripping off the initial <emphasis
      role="bold">/dev/</emphasis> string with which all UNIX device names conventionally begin, and replacing any other slashes in
      the name with underscores. For example, <emphasis role="bold">CFG_rmt_4m</emphasis> is the appropriate filename for a device
      called <emphasis role="bold">/dev/rmt/4m</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>For a backup data file, construct the device_name portion by stripping off the initial slash (<emphasis
      role="bold">/</emphasis>) and replacing any other slashes (<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>) in the name with underscores.
      For example, <emphasis role="bold">CFG_var_tmp_FILE</emphasis> is the appropriate filename for a backup data file called
      <emphasis role="bold">/var/tmp/FILE</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Creating a device configuration file is optional. If you do not want to take advantage of any of the features that the
      file provides, you do not have to create it.</para>

      <para>You can include one of each of the following instructions in any order in a device configuration file. All are optional.
      Place each instruction on its own line, but do not include any newline (<emphasis role="bold">&lt;Return&gt;</emphasis>)
      characters within an instruction. <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">MOUNT and UNMOUNT</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Identify a script of routines for mounting and unmounting tapes in a tape stacker or jukebox's drive as needed.
              See <link linkend="HDRWQ277">Invoking a Device's Tape Mounting and Unmounting Routines</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">AUTOQUERY</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Controls whether the Tape Coordinator prompts for the first tape it needs for a backup operation. See <link
              linkend="HDRWQ278">Eliminating the Search or Prompt for the Initial Tape</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">ASK</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Controls whether the Tape Coordinator asks you how to respond to certain error conditions. See <link
              linkend="HDRWQ279">Enabling Default Responses to Error Conditions</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">NAME_CHECK</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Controls whether the Tape Coordinator verifies that an AFS tape name matches the initial dump you are writing to
              the tape. See <link linkend="HDRWQ280">Eliminating the AFS Tape Name Check</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">BUFFERSIZE</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sets the size of the memory buffer the Tape Coordinator uses when transferring data between a tape device and a
              volume. See <link linkend="HDRWQ281">Setting the Memory Buffer Size to Promote Tape Streaming</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">FILE</emphasis></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Controls whether the Tape Coordinator writes dumps to, and restores data from, a tape device or a backup data
              file. See <link linkend="HDRWQ282">Dumping Data to a Backup Data File</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>UNMOUNT instruction in CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>MOUNT instruction in CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>automating tape mounting and unmounting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tape (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>automating mounting and unmounting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>automating tape mounting and unmounting</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>automating</primary>

        <secondary>tape mounting and unmounting by Backup System</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ277">
      <title>Invoking a Device's Tape Mounting and Unmounting Routines</title>

      <para>A tape stacker or jukebox helps you automate backup operations because it can switch between multiple tapes during an
      operation without human intervention. To take advantage of this feature, include the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis>
      and optionally <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instructions in the device configuration file that you write for the
      stacker or jukebox. The instructions share the same syntax:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> filename
   <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> filename
</programlisting>

      <para>where filename is the pathname on the local disk of a script or program you have written that invokes the routines
      defined by the device's manufacturer for mounting or unmounting a tape in the device's tape drive. (For convenience, the
      following discussion uses the term <emphasis>script</emphasis> to refers to both scripts and programs.) The script usually
      also contains additional logic that handles error conditions or modifies the script's behavior depending on which backup
      operation is being performed.</para>

      <para>You can refer to different scripts with the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instructions, or to a single script that invokes both mounting and unmounting routines. The
      scripts inherit the local identity and AFS tokens associated with to the issuer of the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis>
      command.</para>

      <para>You need to include a <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file for all tape
      devices, but the need for an <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instruction depends on the tape-handling routines that
      the device's manufacturer provides. Some devices, usually stackers, have only a single routine for mounting tapes, which also
      automatically unmounts a tape whose presence prevents insertion of the required new tape. In this case, an <emphasis
      role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instruction is not necessary. For devices that have separate mounting and unmounting routines,
      you must include an <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instruction to remove a tape when the Tape Coordinator is
      finished with it; otherwise, subsequent attempts to run the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction fail with an
      error.</para>

      <para>When the device configuration file includes a <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction, you must stock the
      stacker or jukebox with the necessary tapes before running a backup operation. Many jukeboxes are able to search for the
      required tape by reading external labels (such as barcodes) on the tapes, but many stackers can only switch between tapes in
      sequence and sometimes only in one direction. In the latter case, you must also stock the tapes in the correct order.</para>

      <para>To obtain a list of the tapes required for a restore operation so that you can prestock them in the tape device, include
      the <emphasis role="bold">-n</emphasis> flag on the appropriate <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command (<emphasis
      role="bold">backup diskrestore</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">backup volrestore</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">backup
      volsetrestore</emphasis>). For a dump operation, it is generally sufficient to stock the device with more tapes than the
      operation is likely to require. You can prelabel the tapes with permanent names or AFS tape names, or not prelabel them at
      all. If you prelabel the tapes for a dump operation with AFS tape names, then it is simplest to load them into the stacker in
      sequential order by tape index. But it is probably simpler still to prelabel tapes with permanent tape names or use unlabeled
      tapes, in which case the Backup System generates and applies the appropriately indexed AFS tape name itself during the dump
      operation.</para>

      <sect3 id="Header_312">
        <title>How the Tape Coordinator Uses the MOUNT and UNMOUNT Instructions</title>

        <para>When you issue the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis> command to initialize the Tape Coordinator for a given tape
        device, the Tape Coordinator looks for the device configuration file called <emphasis
        role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/CFG_</emphasis>device_name on its local disk, where device_name has the format described in
        <link linkend="HDRWQ276">Creating a Device Configuration File</link>. If the file exists and contains a <emphasis
        role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction, then whenever the Tape Coordinator needs a tape, it executes the script named by
        the instruction's filename argument.</para>

        <para>If the device configuration file does not exist, or does not include a <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis>
        instruction, then whenever the Tape Coordinator needs a tape, it generates a prompt in its window instructing the operator
        to insert the necessary tape. The operator must insert the tape and press <emphasis role="bold">&lt;Return&gt;</emphasis>
        before the Tape Coordinator continues the backup operation.</para>

        <para>Note, however, that you can modify the Tape Coordinator's behavior with respect to the first tape needed for an
        operation, by setting the <emphasis role="bold">AUTOQUERY</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file to
        <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis>, or including the <emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis
        role="bold">butc</emphasis> command. In this case, the Tape Coordinator does not execute the <emphasis
        role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction or prompt for a tape at the start of an operation, because it expects to find the
        required first tape in the drive. See <link linkend="HDRWQ278">Eliminating the Search or Prompt for the Initial
        Tape</link>.</para>

        <para>If there is an <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file, then whenever
        the Tape Coordinator closes the tape device, it executes the script named by the instruction's filename argument. It
        executes the script only once, and regardless of whether the <emphasis role="bold">close</emphasis> operation on the device
        succeeded or not. If the device configuration file does not include an <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> instruction,
        then the Tape Coordinator takes no action.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Header_313">
        <title>The Available Parameters and Required Exit Codes</title>

        <para>When the Tape Coordinator executes the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> script, it passes in five parameters,
        ordered as follows. You can use the parameters in your script to refine its response to varying circumstances that can arise
        during a backup operation. <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The tape device or backup data file's pathname, as recorded in the <emphasis
              role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The tape operation, which (except for the exceptions noted in the following list) matches the <emphasis
              role="bold">backup</emphasis> command operation code used to initiate the operation: <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">appenddump</emphasis> (when a <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> command
                    includes the <emphasis role="bold">-append</emphasis> flag)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">dump</emphasis> (when a <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> command does
                    not include the <emphasis role="bold">-append</emphasis> flag)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">labeltape</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">readlabel</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">restore</emphasis> (for a <emphasis role="bold">backup diskrestore</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis role="bold">backup volrestore</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">backup volsetrestore</emphasis>
                    command)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">restoredb</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">savedb</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">scantape</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The number of times the Tape Coordinator has attempted to open the tape device or backup data file. If the open
              attempt returns an error, the Tape Coordinator increments this value by one and again invokes the <emphasis
              role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The tape name. For some operations, the Tape Coordinator passes the string
              <computeroutput>none</computeroutput>, because it does not know the tape name (when running the <emphasis
              role="bold">backup scantape</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">backup readlabel</emphasis>, for example), or because
              the tape does not necessarily have a name (when running the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command,
              for example).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The tape ID recorded in the Backup Database. As with the tape name, the Backup System passes the string
              <computeroutput>none</computeroutput> for operations where it does not know the tape ID or the tape does not
              necessarily have an ID.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>

        <para>Your <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> script must return one of the following exit codes to tell the Tape
        Coordinator whether or not it mounted the tape successfully: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) indicates a successful mount, and the Tape Coordinator continues
              the backup operation. If the script or program called by the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction does
              not return this exit code, the Tape Coordinator never calls the <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis>
              instruction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> indicates that mount attempt failed. The Tape Coordinator terminates the
              backup operation.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Any other code indicates that the script was unable to access the correct tape. The Tape Coordinator prompts the
              operator to insert it.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>When the Tape Coordinator executes the <emphasis role="bold">UNMOUNT</emphasis> script, it passes in two parameters in
        the following order. <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The tape device's pathname (as specified in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis>
              file)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The tape operation, which is always <emphasis role="bold">unmount</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>

        <para>The following example script uses two of the parameters passed to it by the Backup System:
        <computeroutput>tries</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>operation</computeroutput>. It follows the recommended practice
        of exiting if the value of the <computeroutput>tries</computeroutput> parameter exceeds one, because that implies that the
        stacker is out of tapes.</para>

        <para>For a <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">backup savedb</emphasis> operation, the
        routine calls the example <emphasis role="bold">stackerCmd_NextTape</emphasis> function provided by the stacker's
        manufacturer. Note that the final lines in the file return the exit code that prompts the operator to insert a tape; these
        lines are invoked when either the stacker cannot load a tape or a the operation being performed is not one of those
        explicitly mentioned in the file (is a restore operation, for example).</para>

        <programlisting>
   #! /bin/csh -f
   set devicefile = $1
   set operation = $2
   set tries = $3
   set tapename = $4
   set tapeid = $5
   set exit_continue = 0
   set exit_abort = 1
   set exit_interactive = 2
   #--------------------------------------------
   if (${tries} &gt; 1) then
      echo "Too many tries"
      exit ${exit_interactive}
   endif
   if (${operation} == "unmount") then
      echo "UnMount: Will leave tape in drive"
      exit ${exit_continue}
   endif
   if ((${operation} == "dump")     |\
       (${operation} == "appenddump")     |\
       (${operation} == "savedb"))  then
       stackerCmd_NextTape ${devicefile}
       if (${status} != 0)exit${exit_interactive}
       echo "Will continue"
       exit ${exit_continue}
   endif
   if ((${operation} == "labeltape")    |\
       (${operation} == "readlabel")) then
      echo "Will continue"
      exit ${exit_continue}
   endif
   echo "Prompt for tape"
   exit ${exit_interactive}
</programlisting>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>Backup System</primary>

          <secondary>eliminating search/prompt for initial tape</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

          <secondary>eliminating search/prompt for initial tape</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>tapes (Backup System)</primary>

          <secondary>eliminating search/prompt for initial</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>AUTOQUERY instruction in CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ278">
      <title>Eliminating the Search or Prompt for the Initial Tape</title>

      <para>By default, the Tape Coordinator obtains the first tape it needs for a backup operation by reading the device
      configuration file for the appropriate tape device. If there is a <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction in the
      file, the Tape Coordinator executes the referenced script. If the device configuration file does not exist or does not have a
      <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction in it, the Tape Coordinator prompts you to insert the correct tape and
      press <emphasis role="bold">&lt;Return&gt;</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>If you know in advance that an operation requires a tape, you can increase efficiency by placing the required tape in
      the drive before issuing the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command and telling the Tape Coordinator's to skip its
      initial tape-acquisition steps. This both enables the operation to begin more quickly and eliminates that need for you to be
      present to insert a tape.</para>

      <para>There are two ways to bypass the Tape Coordinator's initial tape-acquisition steps: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Include the instruction <emphasis role="bold">AUTOQUERY NO</emphasis> in the device configuration file</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Include the <emphasis role="bold">-noautoquery</emphasis> flag to the <emphasis role="bold">butc</emphasis>
            command</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>To avoid any error conditions that require operator attention, be sure that the tape you are placing in the drive does
      not contain any unexpired dumps and is not write protected. If there is no permanent name on the tape's label and you are
      creating an initial dump, make sure that the AFS tape name either matches the volume set and dump set names or is
      <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput>. Alternatively, suppress the Tape Coordinator's name verification step by
      assigning the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="bold">NAME_CHECK</emphasis> instruction in the
      device configuration file, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ280">Eliminating the AFS Tape Name Check</link>.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>ASK instruction in CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>using default responses to errors</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>using default responses to errors</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ279">
      <title>Enabling Default Responses to Error Conditions</title>

      <para>By default, the Tape Coordinator asks you how to respond when it encounters certain error conditions. To suppress the
      prompts and cause the Tape Coordinator to handle the errors in a predetermined manner, include the instruction <emphasis
      role="bold">ASK NO</emphasis> in the device configuration file. If you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">YES</emphasis>,
      or omit the <emphasis role="bold">ASK</emphasis> instruction completely, the Tape Coordinator prompts you for direction when
      it encounters one of the errors.</para>

      <para>The following list describes the error conditions and the Tape Coordinator's response to them. <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Backup System is unable to dump a volume while running the <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis>
            command. When you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis>, the Tape Coordinator omits the volume from the
            dump and continues the operation. When you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">YES</emphasis>, it prompts to ask if
            you want to try to dump the volume again immediately, to omit the volume from the dump but continue the operation, or to
            terminate the operation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Backup System is unable to restore a volume while running the <emphasis role="bold">backup
            diskrestore</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">backup volrestore</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">backup
            volsetrestore</emphasis> command. When you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis>, the Tape Coordinator
            continues the operation, omitting the problematic volume but restoring the remaining ones. When you assign the value
            <emphasis role="bold">YES</emphasis>, it prompts to ask if you want to omit the volume and continue the operation, or to
            terminate the operation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Backup System cannot determine if the dump set includes any more tapes while running the <emphasis
            role="bold">backup scantape</emphasis> command (the command's reference page in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
            Reference</emphasis> discusses possible reasons for this problem). When you assign the value <emphasis
            role="bold">NO</emphasis>, the Tape Coordinator proceeds as though there are more tapes and invokes the <emphasis
            role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> script named in the device configuration file, or prompts the operator to insert the next
            tape. When you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">YES</emphasis>, it prompts to ask if there are more tapes to
            scan.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Backup System determines that the tape contains an unexpired dump while running the <emphasis
            role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command. When you assign the value <emphasis role="bold">NO</emphasis>, it
            terminates the operation without relabeling the tape. With a <emphasis role="bold">YES</emphasis> value, the Tape
            Coordinator prompts to ask if you want to relabel the tape anyway.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>NAME_CHECK instruction in CFG_<emphasis>device_name</emphasis> file</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Backup System</primary>

        <secondary>eliminating check for proper tape name</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>tape (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>eliminating check for proper name</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Tape Coordinator (Backup System)</primary>

        <secondary>eliminating check for proper tape name</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ280">
      <title>Eliminating the AFS Tape Name Check</title>

      <para>If a tape does not have a permanent name and you are writing an initial dump to it, then by default the Backup System
      verifies that the tape's AFS tape name is acceptable. It accepts three types of values: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A name that reflects the volume set and dump level of the initial dump and the tape's place in the sequence of
            tapes for the dump set, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ253">Dump Names and Tape Names</link>. If the tape does not
            already have a permanent name, you can assign the AFS tape name by using the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis>
            argument to the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A <computeroutput>&lt;NULL&gt;</computeroutput> value, which results when you assign a permanent name, or provide
            no value for the <emphasis role="bold">backup labeltape</emphasis> command's <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis>
            argument.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>No AFS tape name at all, indicating that you have never labeled the tape or written a dump to it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>To bypass the name check, include the <emphasis role="bold">NAME_CHECK NO</emphasis> instruction in the device
      configuration file. This enables you to recycle a tape without first relabeling it, as long as all dumps on it are expired.
      (If a tape has unexpired dumps on it but you want to recycle it anyway, you must use the <emphasis role="bold">backup
      labeltape</emphasis> command to relabel it first. For this to work, the <emphasis role="bold">ASK NO</emphasis> instruction
      cannot appear in the device configuration file.)</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ281">
      <title>Setting the Memory Buffer Size to Promote Tape Streaming</title>

      <para>By default, the Tape Coordinator uses a 16-KB memory buffer during dump operations. As it receives volume data from the
      Volume Server, the Tape Coordinator gathers 16 KB of data in the buffer before transferring the entire 16 KB to the tape
      device. Similarly, during a restore operation the Tape Coordinator by default buffers 32 KB of data from the tape device
      before transferring the entire 32 KB to the Volume Server for restoration into the file system. Buffering makes the volume of
      data flowing to and from a tape device more even and so promotes tape streaming, which is the most efficient way for a tape
      device to operate.</para>

      <para>In a normal network configuration, the default buffer sizes are usually large enough to promote tape streaming. If the
      network between the Tape Coordinator machine and file server machines is slow, it can help to increase the buffer size.</para>

      <para>To determine if altering the buffer size is helpful for your configuration, observe the tape device in operation to see
      if it is streaming, or consult the manufacturer. To set the buffer size, include the <emphasis
      role="bold">BUFFERSIZE</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file. It takes an integer value, and optionally
      units, in the following format:</para>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">BUFFERSIZE</emphasis> size[{<emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> | <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis> | <emphasis
          role="bold">m</emphasis> | <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> | <emphasis role="bold">g</emphasis> | <emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis>}]
</programlisting>

      <para>where size specifies the amount of memory the Tape Coordinator allocates to use as a buffer during both dump and restore
      operations. The default unit is bytes, but use <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis> to
      specify kilobytes, <emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> for megabytes, and <emphasis
      role="bold">g</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis> for gigabytes. There is no space between the size value and the
      units letter.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ282">
      <title>Dumping Data to a Backup Data File</title>

      <para>You can write dumps to a <emphasis>backup data file</emphasis> rather than to tape. This is useful if, for example, you
      want to transfer the data to a data-archiving system, such as a hierarchical storage management (HSM) system, that you use in
      conjunction with AFS and the Backup System. You can restore data from a backup data file into the file system as well. Using a
      backup data file is usually more efficient than issuing the equivalent <emphasis role="bold">vos dump</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">vos restore</emphasis> commands individually for multiple volumes.</para>

      <para>Writing to a backup data file is simplest if it is on the local disk of the Tape Coordinator machine, but you can also
      write the file to an NFS-mounted partition that resides on a remote machine. It is even acceptable to write to a file in AFS,
      provided that the access control list (ACL) on its parent directory grants the necessary permissions, but it is somewhat
      circular to back up AFS data into AFS itself.</para>

      <para>If the backup data file does not already exist when the Tape Coordinator attempts to write a dump to it, the Tape
      Coordinator creates it. For a restore operation to succeed, the file must exist and contain volume data previously written to
      it during a <emphasis role="bold">backup dump</emphasis> operation.</para>

      <para>When writing to a backup data file, the Tape Coordinator writes data at 16 KB offsets. If a given block of data (such as
      the marker that signals the beginning or end of a volume) does not fill the entire 16 KB, the Tape Coordinator still skips to
      the next offset before writing the next block. In the output of a <emphasis role="bold">backup dumpinfo</emphasis> command
      issued with the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> option, the value in the <computeroutput>Pos</computeroutput> column is
      the ordinal of the 16-KB offset at which the volume data begins, and so is not generally only one higher than the position
      number on the previous line, as it is for dumps to tape.</para>

      <para>Before writing to a backup data file, you need to configure the file as though it were a tape device.</para>

      <note>
        <para>A file pathname, rather than a tape device name, must appear in the third field of the <emphasis
        role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file when the <emphasis role="bold">FILE YES</emphasis> instruction
        appears in the device configuration file, and vice versa. If the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file instead
        refers to a tape device, dump operations appear to succeed but are inoperative. You cannot restore data that you accidently
        dumped to a tape device while the <emphasis role="bold">FILE</emphasis> instruction was set to <emphasis
        role="bold">YES</emphasis>. In the same way, if the <emphasis role="bold">FILE</emphasis> instruction is set to <emphasis
        role="bold">NO</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> entry must refer to an actual tape device.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_319">
      <title>To configure a backup data file</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that you are authenticated as a user listed in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis>
          file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Become the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> on the machine, if you are not already, by issuing
          the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">su root</emphasis>
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>root_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>. Issue the <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> command to enter
          interactive mode. <programlisting>
   # <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the port offset number to assign to the file. If necessary, display previously assigned port offsets by
          issuing the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) listhosts</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link
          linkend="HDRWQ264">To display the list of configured Tape Coordinators</link>. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">listhosts</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>

          <para>As for a tape device, acceptable values are the integers <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) through <emphasis
          role="bold">58510</emphasis> (the Backup System can track a maximum of 58,511 port offset numbers). Each port offset must
          be unique in the cell, but you can associate any number them with a single Tape Coordinator machine. You do not have to
          assign port offset numbers sequentially.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(backup) addhost</emphasis> command to register the backup data file's port offset
          in the Backup Database. <programlisting>
   backup&gt; <emphasis role="bold">addhost</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>tape machine name</replaceable>&gt; [&lt;<replaceable>TC port offset</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">addh</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">addhost</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">tape machine name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the fully qualified hostname of the Tape Coordinator machine you invoke to write to the backup
                  data file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">TC port offset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the file's port offset number. You must provide this argument unless the default value of
                  <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) is appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LITAPECONFIG-FILE" />Using a text editor, create an entry for the backup data file in the local
          <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</emphasis> file, using the standard syntax: <programlisting>
   [capacity  filemark_size]  device_name   port_offset
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">capacity</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the amount of space on the partition that houses the backup data file that you want to make
                  available for the file. To avoid the complications that arise from filling up the partition, it is best to provide
                  a value somewhat smaller than the actual amount of space you expect to be available when the dump operation runs,
                  and never larger than the maximum file size allowed by the operating system.</para>

                  <para>Specify a numerical value followed by a letter that indicates units, with no intervening space. The letter
                  <emphasis role="bold">k</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis> indicates kilobytes, <emphasis
                  role="bold">m</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> indicates megabytes, and <emphasis
                  role="bold">g</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis> indicates gigabytes. If you omit the units letter,
                  the default is kilobytes. If you leave this field empty, the Tape Coordinator uses the maximum acceptable value
                  (2048 GB or 2 TB). Also leave the filemark_size field empty in that case.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">filemark_size</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify the value <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero) or leave both this field and the capacity field
                  empty. In the latter case, the Tape Coordinator also uses the value zero.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">device_name</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the complete pathname of the backup data file. Rather than specifying an actual file pathname,
                  however, the recommended configuration is to create a symbolic link in the <emphasis role="bold">/dev</emphasis>
                  directory that points to the actual file pathname, and record the symbolic link in this field. This configuration
                  provides these advantages: <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>It makes the device_name portion of the <emphasis role="bold">CFG_</emphasis>device_name, of the
                        <emphasis role="bold">TE_</emphasis>device_name, and of the <emphasis role="bold">TL_</emphasis>device_name
                        filenames as short as possible. Because the symbolic link is in the <emphasis role="bold">/dev</emphasis>
                        directory as though it is a tape device, you strip off the entire <emphasis role="bold">/dev/</emphasis>
                        prefix when forming the filename, instead of just the initial slash (<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>).
                        If, for example, the symbolic link is called <emphasis role="bold">/dev/FILE</emphasis>, the device
                        configuration file's name is <emphasis role="bold">CFG_FILE</emphasis>, whereas if the actual pathname
                        /<emphasis role="bold">var/tmp/FILE</emphasis> appears in the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis>
                        file, the configuration file's name must be <emphasis role="bold">CFG_var_tmp_FILE</emphasis>.</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>It provides for a more graceful, and potentially automated, recovery if the Tape Coordinator cannot
                        write a complete dump into the backup data file (for example, because the partition housing the backup data
                        file becomes full). The Tape Coordinator's reaction to this problem is to invoke the <emphasis
                        role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> script, or to prompt you if the <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis>
                        instruction does not appear in the configuration file. <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                              <para>If there is a <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> script, you can prepare for this situation
                              by adding a subroutine to the script that changes the symbolic link to point to another backup data
                              file on a partition where there is space available.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                              <para>If there is no <emphasis role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction, the prompt enables you
                              manually to change the symbolic link to point to another backup data file and then press &lt;<emphasis
                              role="bold">Return</emphasis>&gt; to signal that the Tape Coordinator can continue the
                              operation.</para>
                            </listitem>
                          </itemizedlist></para>

                        <para>If this field names the actual file, there is no way to recover from exhausting the space on the
                        partition. You cannot change the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file in the middle of an
                        operation.</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">port_offset</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the port offset number that you chose for the backup data file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the device configuration file <emphasis role="bold">CFG_</emphasis>device_name in the Tape Coordinator
          machine's <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/backup</emphasis> directory. Include the <emphasis role="bold">FILE
          YES</emphasis> instruction in the file.</para>

          <para>Construct the device_name portion of the name based on the device name you recorded in the <emphasis
          role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file in Step <link linkend="LITAPECONFIG-FILE">6</link>. If, as recommended, you
          recorded a symbolic link name, strip off the <emphasis role="bold">/dev/</emphasis> string and replace any other slashes
          (<emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis>) in the name with underscores (<emphasis role="bold">_</emphasis>). For example,
          <emphasis role="bold">CFG_FILE</emphasis> is the appropriate name if the symbolic link is <emphasis
          role="bold">/dev/FILE</emphasis>. If you recorded the name of an actual file, then strip off the initial slash only and
          replace any other slashes in the name with underscores. For a backup data file called <emphasis
          role="bold">/var/tmp/FILE</emphasis>, the appropriate device configuration filename is <emphasis
          role="bold">CFG_var_tmp_FILE</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you chose in Step <link linkend="LITAPECONFIG-FILE">6</link> to record a symbolic link name in the device_name
          field of the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> entry, then you must do one of the following: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use the <emphasis role="bold">ln -s</emphasis> command to create the appropriate symbolic link in the
                <emphasis role="bold">/dev</emphasis> directory</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Write a script that initializes the backup data file in this way, and include a <emphasis
                role="bold">MOUNT</emphasis> instruction in the device configuration file to invoke the script. An example script
                appears following these instructions.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>You do not need to create the backup data file itself, because the Tape Coordinator does so if the file does not exist
      when the dump operation begins.</para>

      <para>The following example script illustrates how you can automatically create a symbolic link to the backup data file during
      the preparation phase for writing to the file. When the Tape Coordinator is executing a <emphasis role="bold">backup
      dump</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">backup restore</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">backup savedb</emphasis>, or <emphasis
      role="bold">backup restoredb</emphasis> operation, the routine invokes the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">ln -s</emphasis> command
      to create a symbolic link from the backup data file named in the <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file to the
      actual file to use (this is the recommended method). It uses the values of the <computeroutput>tapename</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>tapeid</computeroutput> parameters passed to it by the Backup System when constructing the filename.</para>

      <para>The routine makes use of two other parameters as well: <computeroutput>tries</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>operation</computeroutput>. The <computeroutput>tries</computeroutput> parameter tracks how many times the
      Tape Coordinator has attempted to access the file. A value greater than one indicates that the Tape Coordinator cannot access
      it, and the routine returns exit code 2 (<computeroutput>exit_interactive</computeroutput>), which results in a prompt for the
      operator to load a tape. The operator can use this opportunity to change the name of the backup data file specified in the
      <emphasis role="bold">tapeconfig</emphasis> file.</para>

      <programlisting>
   #! /bin/csh -f
   set devicefile = $1
   set operation = $2
   set tries = $3
   set tapename = $4
   set tapeid = $5
   set exit_continue = 0
   set exit_abort = 1
   set exit_interactive = 2
   #--------------------------------------------
   if (${tries} &gt; 1) then
      echo "Too many tries"
      exit ${exit_interactive}
   endif
   if (${operation} == "labeltape") then
      echo "Won't label a tape/file"
      exit ${exit_abort}
   endif
   if ((${operation} == "dump")   |\
       (${operation} == "appenddump")   |\
       (${operation} == "restore")   |\
       (${operation} == "savedb")    |\
       (${operation} == "restoredb")) then
      /bin/rm -f ${devicefile}
      /bin/ln -s /hsm/${tapename}_${tapeid} ${devicefile}
      if (${status} != 0) exit ${exit_abort}
   endif
   exit ${exit_continue}
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>