<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="HDRWQ491">
  <title>Administering User Accounts</title>

  <para><indexterm>
      <primary>administering</primary>

      <secondary>user accounts</secondary>
    </indexterm></para>

  <para>This chapter explains how to create and maintain user accounts in your cell.</para>

  <para>The preferred method for creating user accounts is the <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> program, which enables you to
  create multiple accounts with a single command. See <link linkend="HDRWQ449">Creating and Deleting User Accounts with the uss
  Command Suite</link>. If you prefer to create each account component individually, follow the instructions in <link
  linkend="HDRWQ502">Creating AFS User Accounts</link>.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ492">
    <title>Summary of Instructions</title>

    <para>This chapter explains how to perform the following tasks by using the indicated commands:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="57*" />

        <colspec colwidth="43*" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Create Protection Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">pts createuser</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Create Authentication Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas create</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Create volume</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">vos create</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Mount volume</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs mkmount</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Create entry on ACL</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Examine Protection Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">pts examine</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Change directory ownership</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">/etc/chown</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Limit failed authentication attempts</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> with <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> and <emphasis
            role="bold">-locktime</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Unlock Authentication Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Set password lifetime</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> with <emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Prohibit password reuse</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> with <emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Change AFS password</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>List groups owned by user</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Rename Protection Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Delete Authentication Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">kas delete</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Rename volume</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">vos rename</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Remove mount point</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Delete Protection Database entry</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">pts delete</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>List volume location</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">vos listvldb</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Remove volume</entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">vos remove</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>local password file</primary>

      <secondary>creating entry for AFS user</secondary>

      <tertiary>with manual account creation</tertiary>
    </indexterm>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ494">
    <title>The Components of an AFS User Account</title>

    <para>The differences between AFS and the UNIX file system imply that a complete AFS user account is not the same as a UNIX user
    account. The following list describes the components of an AFS account. The same information appears in a corresponding section
    of <link linkend="HDRWQ449">Creating and Deleting User Accounts with the uss Command Suite</link>, but is repeated here for your
    convenience. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>Protection Database entry</emphasis> defines the username (the name provided when authenticating with
          AFS), and maps it to an AFS user ID (AFS UID), a number that the AFS servers use internally when referencing users. The
          Protection Database also tracks the groups to which the user belongs. For details, see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ531">Administering the Protection Database</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An <emphasis>Authentication Database entry</emphasis> records the user's AFS password in a scrambled form suitable
          for use as an encryption key.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A home <emphasis>volume</emphasis> stores all the files in the user's home directory together on a single partition
          of a file server machine. The volume has an associated quota that limits its size. For a complete discussion of volumes,
          see <link linkend="HDRWQ174">Managing Volumes</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>mount point</emphasis> makes the contents of the user's volume visible and accessible in the AFS
          filespace, and acts as the user's home directory. For more details about mount points, see <link linkend="HDRWQ183">About
          Mounting Volumes</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full access permissions on the home directory's <emphasis>access control list (ACL)</emphasis> and ownership of the
          directory (as displayed by the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> command) enable the user to manage his or her
          files. For details on AFS file protection, see <link linkend="HDRWQ562">Managing Access Control Lists</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <emphasis>local password file entry</emphasis> (in the <emphasis role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> file or
          equivalent) of each AFS client machine enables the user to log in and access AFS files through the Cache Manager. A
          subsequent section in this chapter further discusses local password file entries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Other optional <emphasis>configuration files</emphasis> make the account more convenient to use. Such files help the
          user log in and log out more easily, receive electronic mail, print, and so on.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AFS UID</primary>

      <secondary>matching with UNIX UID</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>UNIX UID</primary>

      <secondary>matching with AFS UID</secondary>
    </indexterm>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ495">
    <title>Creating Local Password File Entries</title>

    <para>To obtain authenticated access to a cell's AFS filespace, a user must not only have a valid AFS token, but also an entry
    in the local password file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> or equivalent) of the machine whose Cache Manager is
    representing the user. This section discusses why it is important for the user's AFS UID to match to the UNIX UID listed in the
    local password file, and describes the appropriate value to put in the file's password field.</para>

    <para>One reason to use <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> commands is that they enable you to generate local password file
    entries automatically as part of account creation. See <link linkend="HDRWQ458">Creating a Common Source Password
    File</link>.</para>

    <para>Information similar to the information in this section appears in a corresponding section of <link
    linkend="HDRWQ449">Creating and Deleting User Accounts with the uss Command Suite</link>, but is repeated here for your
    convenience</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ496">
      <title>Assigning AFS and UNIX UIDs that Match</title>

      <para>A user account is easiest to administer and use if the AFS user ID number (AFS UID) and UNIX UID match. All instructions
      in the AFS documentation assume that they do.</para>

      <para>The most basic reason to make AFS and UNIX UIDs the same is so that the owner name reported by the UNIX <emphasis
      role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> commands makes sense for AFS files and directories.
      Following standard UNIX practice, the File Server records a number rather than a username in an AFS file or directory's owner
      field: the owner's AFS UID. When you issue the <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command, it translates the UID to a
      username according to the mapping in the local password file, not the AFS Protection Database. If the AFS and UNIX UIDs do not
      match, the <emphasis role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> command reports an unexpected (and incorrect) owner. The output can even
      vary on different client machines if their local password files map the same UNIX UID to different names.</para>

      <para>Follow the recommendations in the indicated sections to make AFS and UNIX UIDs match when creating accounts for various
      types of users: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If creating an AFS account for a user who already has a UNIX UID, see <link linkend="HDRWQ499">Making UNIX and AFS
            UIDs Match</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If some users in your cell have existing UNIX accounts but the user for whom you are creating an AFS account does
            not, then it is best to allow the Protection Server to allocate an AFS UID automatically. To avoid overlap of AFS UIDs
            with existing UNIX UIDs, set the Protection Database's <computeroutput>max user id</computeroutput> counter higher than
            the largest UNIX UID, using the instructions in <link linkend="HDRWQ560">Displaying and Setting the AFS UID and GID
            Counters</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If none of your users have existing UNIX accounts, allow the Protection Server to allocate AFS UIDs automatically,
            starting either at its default or at the value you have set for the <computeroutput>max user id</computeroutput>
            counter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>password</primary>

        <secondary>setting in local password file</secondary>

        <tertiary>with manual account creation</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>local password file</primary>

        <secondary>setting password in</secondary>

        <tertiary>with manual account creation</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ497">
      <title>Specifying Passwords in the Local Password File</title>

      <para>Authenticating with AFS is easiest for your users if you install and configure an AFS-modified login utility, which logs
      a user into the local file system and obtains an AFS token in one step. In this case, the local password file no longer
      controls a user's ability to login in most circumstances, because the AFS-modified login utility does not consult the local
      password file if the user provides the correct AFS password. You can nonetheless use a password file entry's password field
      (usually, the second field) in the following ways to control login and authentication: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To prevent both local login and AFS authentication, place an asterisk ( * ) in the field. This is useful mainly in
            emergencies, when you want to prevent a certain user from logging into the machine.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To prevent login to the local file system if the user does not provide the correct AFS password, place a character
            string of any length other than the standard thirteen characters in the field. This is appropriate if you want to allow
            only people with local AFS accounts to log into to your machines. A single <emphasis role="bold">X</emphasis> or other
            character is the most easily recognizable way to do this.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To enable a user to log into the local file system even after providing an incorrect AFS password, record a
            standard UNIX encrypted password in the field by issuing the standard UNIX password-setting command (<emphasis
            role="bold">passwd</emphasis> or equivalent).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If you do not use an AFS-modified login utility, you must place a standard UNIX password in the local password file of
      every client machine the user will use. The user logs into the local file system only, and then must issue the <emphasis
      role="bold">klog</emphasis> command to authenticate with AFS. It is simplest if the passwords in the local password file and
      the Authentication Database are the same, but this is not required. <indexterm>
          <primary>converting</primary>

          <secondary>existing UNIX accounts to AFS accounts</secondary>

          <tertiary>with manual account creation</tertiary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
          <primary>user account</primary>

          <secondary>converting existing UNIX to AFS</secondary>

          <tertiary>with manual account creation</tertiary>
        </indexterm></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ498">
    <title>Converting Existing UNIX Accounts</title>

    <para>This section discusses the three main issues you need to consider if your cell has existing UNIX accounts that you wish to
    convert to AFS accounts.</para>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ499">
      <title>Making UNIX and AFS UIDs Match</title>

      <para>As previously mentioned, AFS users must have an entry in the local password file on every client machine from which they
      access the AFS filespace as an authenticated user. Both administration and use are much simpler if the UNIX UID and AFS UID
      match. When converting existing UNIX accounts, you have two alternatives: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make the AFS UIDs match the existing UNIX UIDs. In this case, you need to assign the AFS UID yourself by including
            the <emphasis role="bold">-id</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">pts createuser</emphasis> command as you
            create the AFS account.</para>

            <para>Because you are retaining the user's UNIX UID, you do not need to alter the UID in the local password file entry.
            However, if you are using an AFS-modified login utility, you possibly need to change the password field in the entry.
            For a discussion of how the value in the password field affects login with an AFS-modified login utility, see <link
            linkend="HDRWQ497">Specifying Passwords in the Local Password File</link>.</para>

            <para>If now or in the future you need to create AFS accounts for users who do not have an existing UNIX UID, then you
            must guarantee that new AFS UIDs do not conflict with any existing UNIX UIDs. The simplest way is to set the
            <computeroutput>max user id</computeroutput> counter in the Protection Database to a value higher than the largest
            existing UNIX UID. See <link linkend="HDRWQ560">Displaying and Setting the AFS UID and GID Counters</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Change the existing UNIX UIDs to match the new AFS UIDs that the Protection Server assigns automatically.</para>

            <para>Allow the Protection Server to allocate the AFS UIDs automatically as you create AFS accounts. You must then alter
            the user's entry in the local password file on every client machine to include the new UID.</para>

            <para>There is one drawback to changing the UNIX UID: any files and directories that the user owned in the local file
            system before becoming an AFS user still have the former UID in their owner field. If you want the <emphasis
            role="bold">ls -l</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">ls -ld</emphasis> commands to display the correct owner, you must
            use the <emphasis role="bold">chown</emphasis> command to change the value to the user's new UID, whether you are
            leaving the file in the local file system or moving it to AFS. See <link linkend="HDRWQ501">Moving Local Files into
            AFS</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ500">
      <title>Setting the Password Field Appropriately</title>

      <para>Existing UNIX accounts already have an entry in the local password file, probably with a (scrambled) password in the
      password field. You possibly need to change the value in the field, depending on the type of login utility you use:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If the login utility is not modified for use with AFS, the actual password must appear (in scrambled form) in the
            local password file entry.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the login utility is modified for use with AFS, choose one of the values discussed in <link
            linkend="HDRWQ497">Specifying Passwords in the Local Password File</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ501">
      <title>Moving Local Files into AFS</title>

      <para>New AFS users with existing UNIX accounts probably already own files and directories stored in a machine's local file
      system, and it usually makes sense to transfer them into the new home volume. The easiest method is to move them onto the
      local disk of an AFS client machine, and then use the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">mv</emphasis> command to transfer them into
      the user's new AFS home directory.</para>

      <para>As you move files and directories into AFS, keep in mind that the meaning of their mode bits changes. AFS ignores the
      second and third sets of mode bits (group and other), and does not use the first set (the owner bits) directly, but only in
      conjunction with entries on the ACL (for details, see <link linkend="HDRWQ580">How AFS Interprets the UNIX Mode Bits</link>).
      Be sure that the ACL protects the file or directory at least as securely as the mode bits.</para>

      <para>If you have chosen to change a user's UNIX UID to match a new AFS UID, you must change the ownership of UNIX files and
      directories as well. Only members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group can issue the <emphasis
      role="bold">chown</emphasis> command on files and directories once they reside in AFS.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ502">
    <title>Creating AFS User Accounts</title>

    <para>There are two methods for creating user accounts. The preferred method--using the <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis>
    commands--enables you to create multiple accounts with a single command. It uses a template to define standard values for the
    account components that are the same for each user (such as quota), but provide differing values for more variable components
    (such as username). See <link linkend="HDRWQ449">Creating and Deleting User Accounts with the uss Command Suite</link>.</para>

    <para>The second method involves issuing a separate command to create each component of the account. It is best suited to
    creation of one account at a time, since some of the commands can create only one instance of the relevant component. To review
    the function of each component, see <link linkend="HDRWQ494">The Components of an AFS User Account</link>.</para>

    <para>Use the following instructions to create any of the three types of user account, which differ in their levels of
    functionality. For a description of the types, see <link linkend="HDRWQ57">Configuring AFS User Accounts</link>. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To create an authentication-only account, perform Step <link linkend="LIWQ504">1</link> through Step <link
          linkend="LIWQ507">4</link> and also Step <link linkend="LIWQ514">14</link>. This type of account consists only of entries
          in the Authentication Database and Protection Database.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To create a basic account, perform Step <link linkend="LIWQ504">1</link> through Step <link
          linkend="LIWQ510">8</link> and Step <link linkend="LIWQ512">11</link> through Step <link linkend="LIWQ514">14</link>. In
          addition to Authentication Database and Protection Database entries, this type of account includes a volume mounted at the
          home directory with owner and ACL set appropriately.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To create a full account, perform all steps in the following instructions. This type of account includes
          configuration files for basic functions such as logging in, printing, and mail delivery, making it more convenient and
          useful. For a discussion of some useful types of configuration files, see <link linkend="HDRWQ60">Creating Standard Files
          in New AFS Accounts</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>user account</secondary>

      <tertiary>with individual commands</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>user account</primary>

      <secondary>creating</secondary>

      <tertiary>with individual commands</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>Protection Database user entry</secondary>

      <tertiary>with pts createuser command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>creating</primary>

      <secondary>Authentication Database entry</secondary>

      <tertiary>with kas create command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Protection Database</primary>

      <secondary>user entry</secondary>

      <tertiary>creating with pts createuser command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Authentication Database</primary>

      <secondary>entry</secondary>

      <tertiary>creating with kas create command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>username</primary>

      <secondary>assigning</secondary>

      <tertiary>with pts createuser command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>AFS UID</primary>

      <secondary>assigning</secondary>

      <tertiary>with pts createuser command</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>user</primary>

      <secondary>AFS UID, assigning</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>assigning</primary>

      <secondary>AFS UID to user</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <sect2 id="HDRWQ503">
      <title>To create one user account with individual commands</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ504" />Decide on the value to assign to each of the following account components. If you are
          creating an authentication-only account, you need to pick only a username, AFS UID, and initial password. <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The username. By convention, the names of many components of the user account incorporate this name. For a
                discussion of restrictions and suggested naming schemes, see <link linkend="HDRWQ58">Choosing Usernames and Naming
                Other Account Components</link>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The AFS UID, if you want to assign a specific one. It is generally best to have the Protection Server allocate
                one instead, except when you are creating an AFS account for a user who already has an existing UNIX account. In
                that case, migrating the user's files into AFS is simplest if you set the AFS UID to match the existing UNIX UID.
                See <link linkend="HDRWQ498">Converting Existing UNIX Accounts</link>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The initial password. Advise the user to change this at the first login, using the password changing
                instructions in the <emphasis>IBM AFS User Guide</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The name of the user's home volume. The conventional name is <emphasis role="bold">user.</emphasis>username
                (for example, <emphasis role="bold">user.smith</emphasis>).</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The volume's site (disk partition on a file server machine). Some cells designate certain machines or
                partitions for user volumes only, or it possibly makes sense to place the volume on the emptiest partition that
                meets your other criteria. To display the size and available space on a partition, use the <emphasis role="bold">vos
                partinfo</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ185">Creating Read/write
                Volumes</link>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The name of the user's home directory (the mount point for the home volume). The conventional location is a
                directory (or one of a set of directories) directly under the cell directory, such as <emphasis
                role="bold">/afs/</emphasis>cellname<emphasis role="bold">/usr</emphasis>. For suggestions on how to avoid the
                slowed directory lookup that can result from having large numbers of user home directories in a single <emphasis
                role="bold">usr</emphasis> directory, see <link linkend="HDRWQ472">Evenly Distributing User Home Directories with
                the G Instruction</link>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The volume's space quota. Include the <emphasis role="bold">-maxquota</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis
                role="bold">vos create</emphasis> command, or accept the default quota of 5000 KB.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The ACL on the home directory. By default, the ACL on every new volume grants all seven permissions to the
                <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. After volume creation, use the <emphasis
                role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to remove the entry if desired, and to grant all seven permissions to the
                user.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ505" />Authenticate as an AFS identity with all of the following privileges. In the conventional
          configuration, the <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis> user account has them, or you possibly have a personal
          administrative account. (To increase cell security, it is best to create special privileged accounts for use only while
          performing administrative procedures; for further discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ584">An Overview of Administrative
          Privilege</link>.) If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command to authenticate. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> admin_user
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>The following list specifies the necessary privileges and indicates how to check that you have them.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Membership in the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. If necessary, issue the
              <emphasis role="bold">pts membership</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ587">To
              display the members of the system:administrators group</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts membership system:administrators</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Inclusion in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis> file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the
              users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on your Authentication Database entry. However, the
              Authentication Server performs its own authentication, so in Step <link linkend="LIWQ507">4</link> you specify an
              administrative identity on the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command line itself.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">insert</emphasis>) and <emphasis
              role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) permissions on the ACL of the directory where
              you are mounting the user's volume. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command, which
              is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

              <para>Members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group always implicitly have the <emphasis
              role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) and by default also the <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on every ACL and can use the <emphasis
              role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to grant other rights as necessary.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Knowledge of the password for the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>pts commands</primary>

            <secondary>createuser</secondary>

            <tertiary>user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>pts createuser</secondary>

            <tertiary>user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ506" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts createuser</emphasis> command to create an entry in the
          Protection Database. For a discussion of setting AFS UIDs, see <link linkend="HDRWQ496">Assigning AFS and UNIX UIDs that
          Match</link>. If you are converting an existing UNIX account into an AFS account, also see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ498">Converting Existing UNIX Accounts</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts createuser</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user name</replaceable>&gt; [&lt;<replaceable>user id</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">cu</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">createuser</emphasis> (and <emphasis
                role="bold">createu</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">user name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the user's username (the character string typed at login). It is best to limit the name to eight or
                fewer lowercase letters, because many application programs impose that limit. The AFS servers themselves accept
                names of up to 63 lowercase letters. Also avoid the following characters: colon (<emphasis
                role="bold">:</emphasis>), semicolon (<emphasis role="bold">;</emphasis>), comma (<emphasis
                role="bold">,</emphasis>), at sign (<emphasis role="bold">@</emphasis>), space, newline, and the period (<emphasis
                role="bold">.</emphasis>), which is conventionally used only in special administrative names.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">user id</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is optional and appropriate only if the user already has a UNIX UID that the AFS UID must match. If you do not
                provide this argument, the Protection Server assigns one automatically based on the counter described in <link
                linkend="HDRWQ560">Displaying and Setting the AFS UID and GID Counters</link>. If the ID you specify is less than
                <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> (one) or is already in use, an error results.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>kas commands</primary>

            <secondary>create</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>kas create</secondary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ507" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas create</emphasis> command to create an entry in the
          Authentication Database. To avoid having the user's temporary initial password echo visibly on the screen, omit the
          <emphasis role="bold">-initial_password</emphasis> argument; instead enter the password at the prompts that appear when
          you omit the argument, as shown in the following syntax specification.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas create</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt; \
                <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis>  &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt;  
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
   initial_password: &lt;<replaceable>initial_password</replaceable>&gt;
   Verifying, please re-enter initial_password: &lt;<replaceable>initial_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">cr</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">create</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the same username as in Step <link linkend="LIWQ506">3</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as
                  admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">initial_password</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the initial password as a string of eight characters or less, to comply with the length
                  restriction that some applications impose. Possible choices for an initial password include the username, a string
                  of digits from a personal identification number such as the Social Security number, or a standard string such as
                  <emphasis role="bold">changeme</emphasis>. Instruct the user to change the string to a truly secret password as
                  soon as possible by using the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> command as described in the <emphasis>IBM
                  AFS User Guide</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>vos commands</primary>

            <secondary>create</secondary>

            <tertiary>when creating user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>vos create</secondary>

            <tertiary>when creating user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ508" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos create</emphasis> command to create the user's volume.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos create</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>partition name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>volume name</replaceable>&gt;  \
                [<emphasis role="bold">-maxquota</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>initial quota (KB)</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">cr</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">create</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">machine name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the file server machine on which to place the new volume.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">partition name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the partition on which to place the new volume.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">volume name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the new volume. The name can include up to 22 characters. By convention, user volume names have the form
                <emphasis role="bold">user.</emphasis>username, where username is the name assigned in Step <link
                linkend="LIWQ506">3</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-maxquota</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Sets the volume's quota, as a number of kilobyte blocks. If you omit this argument, the default is 5000
                KB.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>fs commands</primary>

            <secondary>mkmount</secondary>

            <tertiary>when creating user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>fs mkmount</secondary>

            <tertiary>when creating user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ509" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs mkmount</emphasis> command to mount the volume in the
          filespace and create the user's home directory. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs mkmount</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>volume name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">mk</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">mkmount</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">directory</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the mount point to create. A directory of the same name must not already exist. Partial pathnames are
                interpreted relative to the current working directory. By convention, user home directories are mounted in a
                directory called something like <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.</emphasis>cellname<emphasis
                role="bold">/usr</emphasis>, and the home directory name matches the username assigned in Step <link
                linkend="LIWQ506">3</link>.</para>

                <para>Specify the read/write path to the mount point, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to create
                the new mount point in a read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period
                before the cell name at the pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>).
                For further discussion of the concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link
                linkend="HDRWQ209">The Rules of Mount Point Traversal</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">volume name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the name of the volume created in Step <link linkend="LIWQ508">5</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setvol</emphasis> command with the
          <emphasis role="bold">-offlinemsg</emphasis> argument to record auxiliary information about the volume in its volume
          header. For example, you can record who owns the volume or where you have mounted it in the filespace. To display the
          information, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis> command. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setvol</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-offlinemsg</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>offline message</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">sv</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setvol</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="bold">setv</emphasis>
                the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">dir/file path</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the mount point of the volume with which to associate the message. Partial pathnames are interpreted
                relative to the current working directory.</para>

                <para>Specify the read/write path to the mount point, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to change a
                read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period before the cell name at the
                pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>). For further discussion of the
                concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link linkend="HDRWQ209">The Rules of Mount
                Point Traversal</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">-offlinemsg</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies up to 128 characters of auxiliary information to record in the volume header.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ510" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to set the ACL on the new home
          directory. At the least, create an entry that grants all permissions to the user, as shown.</para>

          <para>You can also use the command to edit or remove the entry that the <emphasis role="bold">vos create</emphasis>
          command automatically places on the ACL for a new volume's root directory, which grants all permissions to the <emphasis
          role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. Keep in mind that even if you remove the entry, the members of the
          group by default have implicit <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) and by
          default <emphasis role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permissions on every ACL, and can
          grant themselves other permissions as required.</para>

          <para>For detailed instructions for the <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command, see <link
          linkend="HDRWQ573">Setting ACL Entries</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-acl</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user name</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis
              role="bold">all</emphasis> \
               [<emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> desired_permissions]
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ511" /><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> Create configuration files and subdirectories in
          the new home directory. Possibilities include <emphasis role="bold">.login</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="bold">.logout</emphasis> files, a shell-initialization file such as <emphasis role="bold">.cshrc</emphasis>, files
          to help with printing and mail delivery, and so on.</para>

          <para>If you are converting an existing UNIX account into an AFS account, you possibly wish to move some files and
          directories into the user's new AFS home directory. See <link linkend="HDRWQ498">Converting Existing UNIX
          Accounts</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> In the new <emphasis role="bold">.login</emphasis> or shell
          initialization file, define the user's $PATH environment variable to include the directories where AFS binaries are kept
          (for example, the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/bin</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afsws/etc</emphasis>
          directories).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ512" />In Step <link linkend="LIWQ513">12</link> and Step <link linkend="LIWQ514">14</link>, you
          must know the user's AFS UID. If you had the Protection Server assign it in Step <link linkend="LIWQ506">3</link>, you
          probably do not know it. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts examine</emphasis> command to display it.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts examine</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user or group name or id</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">e</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">examine</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">user or group name or id</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the username that you assigned in Step <link linkend="LIWQ506">3</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>The first line of the output displays the username and AFS UID. For further discussion and an example of the output,
          see <link linkend="HDRWQ536">Displaying Information from the Protection Database</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ513" />Designate the user as the owner of the home directory and any files and subdirectories
          created or moved in Step <link linkend="LIWQ511">9</link>. Specify the owner by the AFS UID you learned in Step <link
          linkend="LIWQ512">11</link> rather than by username. This is necessary for new accounts because the user does not yet have
          an entry in your local machine's password file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> or equivalent). If you are
          converting an existing UNIX account, an entry possibly already exists, but the UID is possibly incorrect. In that case,
          specifying a username means that the corresponding (possibly incorrect) UID is recorded as the owner.</para>

          <para>Some operating systems allow only the local superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis> to issue the <emphasis
          role="bold">chown</emphasis> command. If necessary, issuing the <emphasis role="bold">su</emphasis> command before the
          <emphasis role="bold">chown</emphasis> command.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">chown</emphasis> new_owner_ID  directory
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">new_owner_ID</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the user's AFS UID, which you learned in Step <link linkend="LIWQ512">11</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">directory</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the home directory you created in Step <link linkend="LIWQ509">6</link>, plus each subdirectory or
                  file you created in Step <link linkend="LIWQ511">9</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the new user home directory resides in a replicated volume, use the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis>
          command to release the volume, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ194">To replicate a read/write volume (create a
          read-only volume)</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume name or ID</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <note>
            <para>This step can be necessary even if the home directory's parent directory is not itself a mount point for a
            replicated volume (and is easier to overlook in that case). Suppose, for example, that the ABC Corporation puts the
            mount points for user volumes in the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr</emphasis> directory. Because that is a
            regular directory rather than a mount point, it resides in the <emphasis role="bold">root.cell</emphasis> volume mounted
            at the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com</emphasis> directory. That volume is replicated, so after changing it by
            creating a new mount point the administrator must issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> command.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ514" />Create or modify an entry for the new user in the local password file (<emphasis
          role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> or equivalent) of each machine the user can log onto. Remember to make the UNIX UID the
          same as the AFS UID you learned in Step <link linkend="LIWQ512">11</link>, and to fill the password field appropriately
          (for instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ497">Specifying Passwords in the Local Password File</link>).</para>

          <para>If you use the <emphasis role="bold">package</emphasis> utility to distribute a common version of the password file
          to all client machines, then you need to make the change only in the common version. See <link
          linkend="HDRWQ419">Configuring Client Machines with the package Program</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>password</primary>

        <secondary>improving security</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>authentication</primary>

        <secondary>improving security</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>login</primary>

        <secondary>limiting failed attempts</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>klog command</primary>

        <secondary>limiting failed attempts</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ515">
    <title>Improving Password and Authentication Security</title>

    <para>AFS provides several optional features than can help to protect your cell's filespace against unauthorized access. The
    following list summarizes them, and instructions follow. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Limit the number of consecutive failed login attempts.</para>

          <para>One of the most common ways for an unauthorized user to access your filespace is to guess an authorized user's
          password. This method of attack is most dangerous if the attacker can use many login processes in parallel or use the RPC
          interfaces directly.</para>

          <para>To protect against this type of attack, use the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis
          role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command to limit the number of times that a user can consecutively fail to enter the
          correct password when using either an AFS-modified login utility or the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command.
          When the limit is exceeded, the Authentication Server locks the user's Authentication Database entry (disallows
          authentication attempts) for a period of time that you define with the <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument
          to the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command. If desired, system administrators can use the <emphasis
          role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command to unlock the entry before the complete lockout time passes.</para>

          <para>In certain circumstances, the mechanism used to enforce the number of failed authentication attempts can cause a
          lockout even though the number of failed attempts is less than the limit set by the <emphasis
          role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument. Client-side authentication programs such as <emphasis
          role="bold">klog</emphasis> and an AFS-modified login utility normally choose an Authentication Server at random for each
          authentication attempt, and in case of a failure are likely to choose a different Authentication Server for the next
          attempt. The Authentication Servers running on the various database server machines do not communicate with each other
          about how many times a user has failed to provide the correct password to them. Instead, each Authentication Server
          maintains its own separate copy of the auxiliary database file <emphasis role="bold">kaserverauxdb</emphasis> (located in
          the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/local</emphasis> directory by default), which records the number of consecutive
          authentication failures for each user account and the time of the most recent failure. This implementation means that on
          average each Authentication Server knows about only a fraction of the total number of failed attempts. The only way to
          avoid allowing more than the number of attempts set by the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument is to have
          each Authentication Server allow only some fraction of the total. More specifically, if the limit on failed attempts is
          <emphasis>f</emphasis>, and the number of Authentication Servers is <emphasis>S</emphasis>, then each Authentication
          Server can only permit a number of attempts equal to <emphasis>f</emphasis> divided by <emphasis>S</emphasis> (the Ubik
          synchronization site for the Authentication Server tracks any remainder, <emphasis>f mod S</emphasis>).</para>

          <para>Normally, this implementation does not reduce the number of allowed attempts to less than the configured limit
          (<emphasis>f</emphasis>). If one Authentication Server refuses an attempt, the client contacts another instance of the
          server, continuing until either it successfully authenticates or has contacted all of the servers. However, if one or more
          of the Authentication Server processes is unavailable, the limit is effectively reduced by a percentage equal to the
          quantity <emphasis>U</emphasis> divided by <emphasis>S</emphasis>, where <emphasis>U</emphasis> is the number of
          unavailable servers and <emphasis>S</emphasis> is the number normally available.</para>

          <para>To avoid the undesirable consequences of setting a limit on failed authentication attempts, note the following
          recommendations: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Do not set the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument (the limit on failed authentication
                attempts) too low. A limit of nine failed attempts is recommended for regular user accounts, to allow three failed
                attempts per Authentication Server in a cell with three database server machines.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Set fairly short lockout times when including the <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument.
                Although guessing passwords is a common method of attack, it is not a very sophisticated one. Setting a lockout time
                can help discourage attackers, but excessively long times are likely to be more of a burden to authorized users than
                to potential attackers. A lockout time of 25 minutes is recommended for regular user accounts.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Do not assign an infinite lockout time on an account (by setting the <emphasis
                role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument to <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> [zero]) unless there is a highly
                compelling reason. Such accounts almost inevitably become locked at some point, because each Authentication Server
                never resets the account's failure counter in its copy of the <emphasis role="bold">kaauxdb</emphasis> file (in
                contrast, when the lockout time is not infinite, the counter resets after the specified amount of time has passed
                since the last failed attempt to that Authentication Server). Furthermore, the only way to unlock an account with an
                infinite lockout time is for an administrator to issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command. It
                is especially dangerous to set an infinite lockout time on an administrative account; if all administrative accounts
                become locked, the only way to unlock them is to shut down all instances of the Authentication Server and remove the
                <emphasis role="bold">kaauxdb</emphasis> file on each.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>

          <para>In summary, the recommended limit on authentication attempts is nine and lockout time 25 minutes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Limit password lifetime.</para>

          <para>The longer a password is in use, the more time an attacker has to try to learn it. To protect against this type of
          attack, use the <emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis>
          command to limit how many days a user's password is valid. The user becomes unable to authenticate with AFS after the
          password expires, but has up to 30 days to use the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> command to set a new password.
          After the 30 days pass, only an administrator who has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on the
          Authentication Database entry can change the password.</para>

          <para>If you set a password lifetime, many AFS-modified login utilities (but not the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis>
          command) set the PASSWORD_EXPIRES environment variable to the number of days remaining until the password expires. A
          setting of zero means that the password expires today. If desired, you can customize your users' login scripts to display
          the number of days remaining before expiration and even prompt for a password change when a small number of days remain
          before expiration.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Prohibit reuse of passwords.</para>

          <para>Forcing users to select new passwords periodically is not effective if they simply set the new password to the
          current value. To prevent a user from setting a new password to a string similar to any of the last 20 passwords, use the
          <emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command.</para>

          <para>If you prohibit password reuse and the user specifies an excessively similar password, the Authentication Server
          generates the following message to reject it:</para>

          <programlisting>
   Password was not changed because it seems like a reused password
</programlisting>

          <para>A persistent user can try to bypass this restriction by changing the password 20 times in quick succession (or
          running a script to do so). If you believe this is likely to be a problem, you can include the <emphasis
          role="bold">-minhours</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> initialization command (for
          details, see the command's reference page in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Reference</emphasis>. If the user
          attempts to change passwords too frequently, the following message appears.</para>

          <programlisting>
   Password was not changed because you changed it too recently; see 
   your systems administrator
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Check the quality of new passwords.</para>

          <para>You can impose a minimum quality standard on passwords by writing a script or program called <emphasis
          role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis>. If the <emphasis role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> file exists, the <emphasis
          role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis> command interpreters invoke it to
          check a new password. If the password does not comply with the quality standard, the <emphasis
          role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> program returns an appropriate code and the command interpreter rejects the
          password.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> file must be executable, must reside in the same AFS directory as the
          <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> binaries, and its directory's ACL must
          grant the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">write</emphasis>) permission only to the <emphasis
          role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group.</para>

          <para>If you choose to write a <emphasis role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> program, consider imposing standards such as the
          following. <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>A minimum length</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Words found in the dictionary are prohibited</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Numbers, punctuation, or both must appear along with letters</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>

          <para>The AFS distribution includes an example <emphasis role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> program. See the <emphasis
          role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> reference page in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Reference</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>kas commands</primary>

      <secondary>setfields</secondary>

      <tertiary>limiting failed authentication attempts</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>commands</primary>

      <secondary>kas setfields</secondary>

      <tertiary>limiting failed authentication attempts</tertiary>
    </indexterm>

    <sect2 id="Header_585">
      <title>To limit the number of consecutive failed authentication attempts</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis>
          and <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> arguments.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>maximum successive failed login tries ([0..254])</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>failure penalty [hh:mm or minutes]</replaceable>&gt;
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the Authentication Database entry to edit.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as the <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis> account. The password prompt
                  echoes it as admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the maximum consecutive number of times that a user can fail to provide the correct password
                  during authentication (via the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command or an AFS-modified login utility)
                  before the Authentication Server refuses further attempts for the amount of time specified by the <emphasis
                  role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument. The range of valid values is <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero)
                  through <emphasis role="bold">254</emphasis>. If you omit this argument or specify <emphasis
                  role="bold">0</emphasis>, the Authentication Server allows an unlimited number of failures.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies how long the Authentication Server refuses authentication attempts after the user exceeds the
                  failure limit specified by the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument.</para>

                  <para>Specify a time in either hours and minutes (hh:mm) or minutes only (mm), from the range <emphasis
                  role="bold">01</emphasis> (one minute) through <emphasis role="bold">36:00</emphasis> (36 hours). The <emphasis
                  role="bold">kas</emphasis> command interpreter automatically reduces any larger value to 36:00 and also rounds up
                  each nonzero value to the next-higher multiple of 8.5 minutes.</para>

                  <para>It is best not to provide a value of <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis> (zero), especially on administrative
                  accounts, because it sets an infinite lockout time. An administrator must always issue the <emphasis
                  role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command to unlock such an account.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_586">
      <title>To unlock a locked user account</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command to enter interactive mode.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas -admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt;  
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
   ka&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> names an administrative account that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis
          role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as
          admin_password.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(kas) examine</emphasis> command to verify that the user's account is in fact
          locked, as indicated by the message shown: <programlisting>
   ka&gt; <emphasis role="bold">examine</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;
   User is locked until time
</programlisting> <indexterm>
              <primary>kas commands</primary>

              <secondary>unlock</secondary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>kas unlock</secondary>
            </indexterm></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(kas) unlock</emphasis> command to unlock the account. <programlisting>
   ka&gt; <emphasis role="bold">unlock</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>authentication ID</replaceable>&gt; 
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">u</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">unlock</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">authentication ID</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the Authentication Database entry to unlock.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>kas commands</primary>

        <secondary>setfields</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting password lifetime</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>kas setfields</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting password lifetime</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Authentication Database</primary>

        <secondary>password lifetime, setting</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_587">
      <title>To set password lifetime</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command with the <emphasis
          role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> argument.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>number days password is valid  [0..254])</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt; 
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the Authentication Database entry on which to impose a password expiration.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sets the number of days after the user's password was last changed that it remains valid. Provide an integer
                  from the range <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> through <emphasis role="bold">254</emphasis> to specify the
                  number of days until expiration.</para>

                  <para>When the password becomes invalid (expires), the user is unable to authenticate, but has 30 more days in
                  which to issue the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis>
                  command to change the password (after that, only an administrator can change it). Note that the clock starts at
                  the time the password was last changed, not when the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command is
                  issued. To avoid retroactive expiration, have the user change the password just before issuing the command.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as
                  admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>kas commands</primary>

        <secondary>setfields</secondary>

        <tertiary>prohibiting password reuse</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>kas setfields</secondary>

        <tertiary>prohibiting password reuse</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Header_588">
      <title>To prohibit reuse of passwords</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command with the <emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis>
          argument.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt; <emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable> permit password reuse (yes/no)</replaceable>&gt;  \
                   <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt; 
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the Authentication Database entry for which to set the password reuse policy.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies whether the Authentication Server allows reuse of passwords similar to any of the user's last 20
                  passwords. Specify the value <emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis> to prohibit reuse, or the value <emphasis
                  role="bold">yes</emphasis> to reinstate the default of allowing password reuse.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as
                  admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>password</primary>

        <secondary>setting in Authentication Database</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>setting</primary>

        <secondary>password</secondary>

        <tertiary>in Authentication Database</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Authentication Database</primary>

        <secondary>password</secondary>

        <tertiary>setting</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ516">
    <title>Changing AFS Passwords</title>

    <para>After setting an initial password during account creation, you normally do not need to change user passwords, since they
    can use the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> command themselves by following the instructions in the <emphasis>IBM AFS
    User Guide</emphasis>. In the rare event that a user forgets the password or otherwise cannot log in, you can use the <emphasis
    role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis> command to set a new password.</para>

    <para>If entries in the local password file (<emphasis role="bold">/etc/passwd</emphasis> or equivalent) have actual scrambled
    passwords in their password field, remember to change the password there also. For further discussion, see <link
    linkend="HDRWQ497">Specifying Passwords in the Local Password File</link>. <indexterm>
        <primary>kas commands</primary>

        <secondary>setpassword</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>commands</primary>

        <secondary>kas setpassword</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <sect2 id="Header_590">
      <title>To change an AFS password</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis> command to change the password. To avoid having the new
          password echo visibly on the screen, omit the <emphasis role="bold">-new_password</emphasis> argument; instead enter the
          password at the prompts that appear when you omit the argument, as shown.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;  \
                     <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt; 
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
   new_password: &lt;<replaceable>new_password</replaceable>&gt;
   Verifying, please re-enter new_password: &lt;<replaceable>new_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">sp</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is an acceptable alias for <emphasis role="bold">setpassword</emphasis> (<emphasis
                  role="bold">setp</emphasis> is the shortest acceptable abbreviation).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the Authentication Database entry for which to set the password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as
                  admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">new_password</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specifies the user's new password. It is subject to the restrictions imposed by the <emphasis
                  role="bold">kpwvalid</emphasis> program, if you use it.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ517">
    <title>Displaying and Setting the Quota on User Volumes</title>

    <para>User volumes are like all other volumes with respect to quota. Each new AFS volume has a default quota of 5000 KB, unless
    you use the <emphasis role="bold">-maxquota</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">vos create</emphasis> command to
    set a different quota. You can also use either of the following commands to change quota at any time: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">fs setquota</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">fs setvol</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>You can use any of the three following commands to display a volume's quota: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">fs quota</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">fs listquota</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">fs examine</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>For instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ234">Setting and Displaying Volume Quota and Current Size</link>. <indexterm>
        <primary>username</primary>

        <secondary>changing</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>changing</primary>

        <secondary>username</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>renaming</primary>

        <secondary>user account components</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>Protection Database</primary>

        <secondary>changing username</secondary>
      </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>Authentication Database</primary>

        <secondary>changing username</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ518">
    <title>Changing Usernames</title>

    <para>By convention, many components of a user account incorporate the username, including the Protection and Authentication
    Database entries, the volume name and the home directory name. When changing a username, it is best to maintain consistency by
    changing the names of all components, so the procedure for changing a username has almost as many steps as the procedure for
    creating a new user account.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_593">
      <title>To change a username</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>pts commands</primary>

          <secondary>rename</secondary>

          <tertiary>username</tertiary>
        </indexterm>

        <indexterm>
          <primary>commands</primary>

          <secondary>pts rename</secondary>

          <tertiary>username</tertiary>
        </indexterm>

        <listitem>
          <para>Authenticate as an AFS identity with all of the following privileges. In the conventional configuration, the
          <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis> user account has them, or you possibly have a personal administrative account. (To
          increase cell security, it is best to create special privileged accounts for use only while performing administrative
          procedures; for further discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ584">An Overview of Administrative Privilege</link>.) If
          necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command to authenticate. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> admin_user
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>The following list specifies the necessary privileges and indicates how to check that you have them.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Membership in the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. If necessary, issue the
              <emphasis role="bold">pts membership</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ587">To
              display the members of the system:administrators group</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts membership system:administrators</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Inclusion in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis> file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the
              users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on the Authentication Database entry. However, the
              Authentication Server performs its own authentication, so the following instructions direct you to specify an
              administrative identity on the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command line itself.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>), <emphasis
              role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>), and <emphasis role="bold">i</emphasis> (<emphasis
              role="bold">insert</emphasis>) permissions on the ACL of the directory where you are removing the current mount point
              and creating a new one. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> command, which is fully
              described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

              <para>Members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group always implicitly have the <emphasis
              role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) and by default also the <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on every ACL and can use the <emphasis
              role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to grant other rights as necessary.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ519" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> command to display the names of the
          groups the user owns. After you change the username in the Protection Database in Step <link linkend="LIWQ520">3</link>,
          you must issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> command to change each group's owner prefix to match the
          new name, because the Protection Server does not automatically make this change. For a complete description of the
          <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> command, see <link linkend="HDRWQ536">Displaying Information from the
          Protection Database</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user or group name or id</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ520" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> command to change the user's name in
          the Protection Database. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>old name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>new name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> command to change the group names you noted in Step <link
          linkend="LIWQ519">2</link>, so that their owner prefix (the part of the group name before the colon) accurately reflects
          the owner's new name.</para>

          <para>Repeat the command for each group. Step <link linkend="LIWQ520">3</link> details its syntax.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts rename</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>old name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>new name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command to enter interactive mode.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas -admin</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt;  
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
   ka&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> names an administrative account that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis
          role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as
          admin_password. <indexterm>
              <primary>kas commands</primary>

              <secondary>delete</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>kas delete</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(kas) delete</emphasis> command to delete the user's existing Authentication
          Database entry. <programlisting>
   ka&gt; <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">del</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>, or you can use the alias
                <emphasis role="bold">rm</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the Authentication Database entry to delete.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>kas commands</primary>

            <secondary>create</secondary>

            <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>kas create</secondary>

            <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">(kas) create</emphasis> command to create an Authentication Database entry for the
          new username. To avoid having the user's password echo visibly on the screen, do not include the <emphasis
          role="bold">-initial_password</emphasis> argument; instead enter the password at the prompts that appear in that case, as
          shown in the following syntax specification. <programlisting>
   ka&gt; <emphasis role="bold">create</emphasis>  &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;
   initial_password: &lt;<replaceable>password</replaceable>&gt;
   Verifying, please re-enter initial_password: &lt;<replaceable>password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">cr</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">create</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the new username.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">password</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the password for the new user account. If the user is willing to tell you his or her current
                password, you can retain it. Otherwise, provide a string of eight characters or less to comply with the length
                restriction that some applications impose. Possible choices for an initial password include the username, a string
                of digits from a personal identification number such as the Social Security number, or a standard string such as
                <emphasis role="bold">changeme</emphasis>. Instruct the user to change the string to a truly secret password as soon
                as possible by using the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> command as instructed in the <emphasis>IBM AFS
                User Guide</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">quit</emphasis> command to leave interactive mode. <programlisting>
   ka&gt; <emphasis role="bold">quit</emphasis>
</programlisting> <indexterm>
              <primary>vos commands</primary>

              <secondary>rename</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>vos rename</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>volume name</primary>

              <secondary>changing</secondary>

              <tertiary>when renaming user</tertiary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>renaming</primary>

              <secondary>volume when changing username</secondary>
            </indexterm> <indexterm>
              <primary>changing</primary>

              <secondary>volume name when renaming user</secondary>
            </indexterm></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ521" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos rename</emphasis> command to change the name of the
          user's volume. For complete syntax, see <link linkend="HDRWQ246">To rename a volume</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos rename</emphasis>  &lt;<replaceable>old volume name</replaceable>&gt;  &lt;<replaceable>new volume name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting><indexterm>
              <primary>fs commands</primary>

              <secondary>rmmount</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>fs rmmount</secondary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>mount point</primary>

              <secondary>changing when renaming user</secondary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>removing</primary>

              <secondary>mount point</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>changing</primary>

              <secondary>mount point when renaming user</secondary>
            </indexterm></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ522" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis> command to remove the existing mount
          point. For the directory argument, specify the read/write path to the mount point, to avoid the failure that results when
          you attempt to delete a mount point from a read-only volume. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting><indexterm>
              <primary>fs commands</primary>

              <secondary>mkmount</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>commands</primary>

              <secondary>fs mkmount</secondary>

              <tertiary>when changing username</tertiary>
            </indexterm><indexterm>
              <primary>creating</primary>

              <secondary>mount point when changing username</secondary>
            </indexterm></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ523" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs mkmount</emphasis> command to create a mount point for the
          volume's new name. Specify the read/write path to the mount point for the directory argument, as in the previous step. For
          complete syntax, see Step <link linkend="LIWQ509">6</link> in <link linkend="HDRWQ503">To create one user account with
          individual commands</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs mkmount</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>volume name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the changes you made in Step <link linkend="LIWQ522">10</link> and Step <link linkend="LIWQ523">11</link> are to
          a mount point that resides in a replicated volume, use the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> command to release
          the volume, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ194">To replicate a read/write volume (create a read-only volume)</link>.
          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume name or ID</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <note>
            <para>This step can be necessary even if the home directory's parent directory is not itself a mount point for a
            replicated volume (and is easier to overlook in that case). For example, the ABC Corporation template puts the mount
            points for user volumes in the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr</emphasis> directory. Because that is a regular
            directory rather than a mount point, it resides in the <emphasis role="bold">root.cell</emphasis> volume mounted at the
            <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com</emphasis> directory. That volume is replicated, so after changing it the
            administrator must issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> command.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ524">
    <title>Removing a User Account</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>removing</primary>

      <secondary>user account components</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>user account</primary>

      <secondary>removing from system</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Before removing an account, it is best to make a backup copy of the user's home volume on a permanent storage medium such
    as tape. If you need to remove several accounts, it is probably more efficient to use the <emphasis role="bold">uss
    delete</emphasis> command instead; see <link linkend="HDRWQ486">Deleting Individual Accounts with the uss delete
    Command</link>.</para>

    <sect2 id="Header_595">
      <title>To remove a user account</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Authenticate as an AFS identity with all of the following privileges. In the conventional configuration, the
          <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis> user account has them, or you possibly have a personal administrative account. (To
          increase cell security, it is best to create special privileged accounts for use only while performing administrative
          procedures; for further discussion, see <link linkend="HDRWQ584">An Overview of Administrative Privilege</link>.) If
          necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command to authenticate. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> admin_user
   Password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>The following list specifies the necessary privileges and indicates how to check that you have them.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Membership in the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group. If necessary, issue the
              <emphasis role="bold">pts membership</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ587">To
              display the members of the system:administrators group</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts membership system:administrators</emphasis>
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Inclusion in the <emphasis role="bold">/usr/afs/etc/UserList</emphasis> file. If necessary, issue the <emphasis
              role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ593">To display the
              users in the UserList file</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on the Authentication Database entry. However, the
              Authentication Server performs its own authentication, so the following instructions direct you to specify an
              administrative identity on the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command line itself.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>) permission on the ACL of the
              directory where you are removing the user volume's mount point. If necessary, issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs
              listacl</emphasis> command, which is fully described in <link linkend="HDRWQ572">Displaying ACLs</link>.
              <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs listacl</emphasis> [&lt;<replaceable>dir/file path</replaceable>&gt;]
</programlisting></para>

              <para>Members of the <emphasis role="bold">system:administrators</emphasis> group always implicitly have the <emphasis
              role="bold">a</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">administer</emphasis>) and by default also the <emphasis
              role="bold">l</emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">lookup</emphasis>) permission on every ACL and can use the <emphasis
              role="bold">fs setacl</emphasis> command to grant other rights as necessary.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> If it is possible you need to restore the user's account someday, note
          the username and AFS UID, possibly in a file designated for that purpose. You can later restore the account with its
          original AFS UID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> Copy the contents of the user's volume to tape. You can use the
          <emphasis role="bold">vos dump</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ240">Dumping and Restoring
          Volumes</link> or the AFS Backup System as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ296">Backing Up Data</link>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ525" /><emphasis role="bold">(Optional)</emphasis> If you intend to remove groups that the user owns
          from the Protection Database after removing the user's entry, issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis>
          command to display them. For complete instructions, see <link linkend="HDRWQ536">Displaying Information from the
          Protection Database</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts listowned</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user or group name or id</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ526" />(<emphasis role="bold">Optional)</emphasis> Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts
          delete</emphasis> command to remove the groups the user owns. However, if it is likely that other users have placed the
          groups on the ACLs of directories they own, it is best not to remove them. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts delete</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user or group name or id</replaceable>&gt;+
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">del</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">user or group name or id</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the name or AFS UID of each group displayed in the output from Step <link
                linkend="LIWQ525">4</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>kas commands</primary>

            <secondary>delete</secondary>

            <tertiary>when removing user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>kas delete</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Authentication Database</primary>

            <secondary>entry</secondary>

            <tertiary>removing</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas delete</emphasis> command to remove the user's Authentication Database
          entry.</para>

          <para>The Authentication Server performs its own authentication rather than accepting your existing AFS token. By default,
          it authenticates your local (UNIX) identity, which possibly does not correspond to an AFS-privileged administrator.
          Include the <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> argument to name an identity that has the
          <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its Authentication Database entry. To verify that an entry has the flag,
          issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ590">To check if the
          ADMIN flag is set</link>.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">kas delete</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>name of user</replaceable>&gt;  \
                <emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis>  &lt;<replaceable>admin principal to use for authentication</replaceable>&gt;  
   Administrator's (admin_user) password: &lt;<replaceable>admin_password</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">d</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">name of user</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the Authentication Database entry to delete.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names an administrative account that has the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag on its
                  Authentication Database entry, such as <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis>. The password prompt echoes it as
                  admin_user. Enter the appropriate password as admin_password.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ527" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos listvldb</emphasis> command to display the site of the
          user's home volume in preparation for removing it. By convention, user volumes are named <emphasis
          role="bold">user</emphasis>.username. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos listvldb</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume name or ID</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">listvl</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">listvldb</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">volume name or ID</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the volume's name or volume ID number.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>vos commands</primary>

            <secondary>remove</secondary>

            <tertiary>when removing user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>vos remove</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>volume</primary>

            <secondary>removing</secondary>

            <tertiary>when removing user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>removing</primary>

            <secondary>volume when removing user account</secondary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ528" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos remove</emphasis> command to remove the user's volume. It
          automatically removes the backup version of the volume, if it exists. It is not conventional to replicate user volumes, so
          the command usually also completely removes the volume's entry from the Volume Location Database (VLDB). If there are
          ReadOnly replicas of the volume, you must repeat the <emphasis role="bold">vos remove</emphasis> command to remove each
          one individually. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos remove</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>machine name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>partition name</replaceable>&gt; &lt;<replaceable>volume name or ID</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <para>where</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">remo</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">remove</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">machine name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the file server machine that houses the volume, as specified in the output from Step <link
                linkend="LIWQ527">7</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">partition name</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Names the partition that houses the volume, as specified in the output from Step <link
                linkend="LIWQ527">7</link>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">volume name or ID</emphasis></term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Specifies the volume's name or ID number.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>fs commands</primary>

            <secondary>rmmount</secondary>

            <tertiary>when removing user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>fs rmmount</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>mount point</primary>

            <secondary>removing when removing user account</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>removing</primary>

            <secondary>mount point when removing user account</secondary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ529" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis> command to remove the volume's mount
          point.</para>

          <para>If you mounted the user's backup volume as a subdirectory of the home directory, then this command is sufficient to
          unmount the backup version as well. If you mounted the backup version at an unrelated location in the filespace, repeat
          the <emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis> command for it.</para>

          <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">fs rmmount</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>directory</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting>

          <para>where <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">rmm</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Is the shortest acceptable abbreviation of <emphasis role="bold">rmmount</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">directory</emphasis></term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Names the mount point for the volume's previous name (the former home directory). Partial pathnames are
                  interpreted relative to the current working directory.</para>

                  <para>Specify the read/write path to the mount point, to avoid the failure that results when you attempt to delete
                  a mount point from a read-only volume. By convention, you indicate the read/write path by placing a period before
                  the cell name at the pathname's second level (for example, <emphasis role="bold">/afs/.abc.com</emphasis>). For
                  further discussion of the concept of read/write and read-only paths through the filespace, see <link
                  linkend="HDRWQ208">Mounting Volumes</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>pts commands</primary>

            <secondary>delete</secondary>

            <tertiary>when removing user account</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>commands</primary>

            <secondary>pts delete</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Protection Database</primary>

            <secondary>user entry</secondary>

            <tertiary>deleting</tertiary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>removing</primary>

            <secondary>Protection Database entry</secondary>
          </indexterm>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><anchor id="LIWQ530" />Issue the <emphasis role="bold">pts delete</emphasis> command to remove the user's Protection
          Database entry. A complete description of this command appears in Step <link linkend="LIWQ526">5</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">pts delete</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>user or group name or id</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the deleted user home directory resided in a replicated volume, use the <emphasis role="bold">vos
          release</emphasis> command to release the volume, as described in <link linkend="HDRWQ194">To replicate a read/write
          volume (create a read-only volume)</link>. <programlisting>
   % <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> &lt;<replaceable>volume name or ID</replaceable>&gt;
</programlisting></para>

          <note>
            <para>This step can be necessary even if the home directory's parent directory is not itself a mount point for a
            replicated volume (and is easier to overlook in that case). For example, the ABC Corporation template puts the mount
            points for user volumes in the <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com/usr</emphasis> directory. Because that is a regular
            directory rather than a mount point, it resides in the <emphasis role="bold">root.cell</emphasis> volume mounted at the
            <emphasis role="bold">/afs/abc.com</emphasis> directory. That volume is replicated, so after changing it by deleting a
            mount point the administrator must issue the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> command.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>