<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="HDRWQ1">
  <title>About This Guide</title>

  <para>This section describes the purpose, organization, and conventions
  of this document.</para>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ2">
    <title>Audience and Purpose</title>

    <para>This guide explains how to install and configure OpenAFS
    server and client machines. It
    assumes that the reader is familiar with <trademark
    class="registered">UNIX</trademark> system administration, but not
    AFS.</para>

    <para>The instructions explain how to issue 
    <trademark class="registered">AFS</trademark> commands in the
    context of specific tasks, but do not describe a command's function or
    arguments in detail. Refer to the <citetitle>OpenAFS Administration
    Reference</citetitle> as necessary.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ3">
    <title>Organization of the Document</title>

    <para>See <link linkend="HDRWQ7">The Procedures Described in this
    Guide</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ4">
    <title>How to Use This Document</title>

    <para>See <link linkend="HDRWQ7">The Procedures Described in this
    Guide</link> and <link linkend="HDRWQ16">How to
    Continue</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRWQ5">
    <title>Related Documents</title>

    <para>The OpenAFS documentation set also includes the following
    documents.
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><citetitle>OpenAFS Administration Guide</citetitle></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This guide describes the concepts and procedures that a
            system administrator must know to manage an AFS cell.  It
            assumes familiarity with UNIX, but requires no previous
            knowledge of AFS.</para>

            <para>The first chapters of the <citetitle>OpenAFS
            Administration Guide</citetitle> present basic concepts and
            guidelines.  Understanding them is crucial to successful
            administration of an AFS cell.  The remaining chapters in the
            guide provide step-by-step instructions for specific
            administrative tasks, along with discussions of the concepts
            important to that particular task.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><citetitle>OpenAFS Administration
          Reference</citetitle></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This reference manual details the syntax and effect of
            each AFS command.  It is intended for the experienced AFS
            administrator, programmer, or user.</para>

            <para>The <citetitle>OpenAFS Administration
            Reference</citetitle> lists AFS files and commands in
            alphabetical order.  The reference page for each command
            specifies its syntax, including the acceptable aliases and
            abbreviations.  It then describes the command's function,
            arguments, and output if any.  Examples and a list of related
            commands are provided, as are warnings where
            appropriate.</para>

            <para>This manual complements the <citetitle>OpenAFS
            Administration Guide</citetitle>: it does not include
            procedural information, but describes commands in more detail
            than the <citetitle>OpenAFS Administration
            Guide</citetitle>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><citetitle>OpenAFS User Guide</citetitle></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This guide presents the basic concepts and procedures
            necessary for using AFS effectively.  It assumes that the
            reader has some experience with UNIX, but does not require
            familiarity with networking or AFS.</para>

            <para>The guide explains how to perform basic functions,
            including authenticating, changing a password, protecting AFS
            data, creating groups, and troubleshooting.  It provides
            illustrative examples for each function and describes some of
            the differences between the UNIX file system and AFS.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><citetitle>OpenAFS Release Notes</citetitle></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This document provides information specific to each
            release of AFS, such as a list of new features and commands, a
            list of requirements and limitations, and instructions for
            upgrading server and client machines.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="HDRTYPO_CONV">
    <title>Typographical Conventions</title>

    <para>This document uses the following typographical conventions:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Command and option names appear
          in <emphasis role="bold">bold type</emphasis> in syntax
          definitions, examples, and running text.  Names of directories,
          files, machines, partitions, volumes, and users also appear
          in <emphasis role="bold">bold type</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Variable information appears in <emphasis>italic
          type</emphasis>.  This includes user-supplied information on
          command lines and the parts of prompts that differ depending on
          who issues the command.  New terms also appear
          in <emphasis>italic type</emphasis>.</para>
	</listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Examples of screen output and file contents appear
          in <computeroutput>monospace type</computeroutput>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>In addition, the following symbols appear in command syntax
    definitions, both in the documentation and in AFS online help
    statements. When issuing a command, do not type these
    symbols.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Square brackets <emphasis role="bold">[ ]</emphasis>
          surround optional items.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Angle brackets <emphasis role="bold">&lt; &gt;</emphasis>
          surround user-supplied values in AFS commands.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A superscripted plus
          sign <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> follows an argument that
          accepts more than one value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The percent sign <computeroutput>%</computeroutput>
          represents the regular command shell prompt. Some operating
          systems possibly use a different character for this
          prompt.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The number sign <computeroutput>#</computeroutput>
          represents the command shell prompt for the local
          superuser <emphasis role="bold">root</emphasis>. Some operating
          systems possibly use a different character for this
          prompt.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The pipe symbol <emphasis role="bold">|</emphasis> in a
          command syntax statement separates mutually exclusive values for
          an argument.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>For additional information on AFS commands, including a
    description of command string components, acceptable abbreviations and
    aliases, and how to get online help for commands, see the appendix to
    the <citetitle>OpenAFS Administration Guide</citetitle>.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>
