<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="buserver8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>buserver</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>buserver</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the Backup Server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>database directory</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-cellservdb</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell configuration directory</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-resetdb</emphasis>]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-smallht</emphasis>] [-servers &lt;<emphasis>list of ubik database servers</emphasis>&gt;+]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis>]  [-enable_process_stats] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> command initializes the Backup Server, which runs on
    database server machines and maintains the Backup Database. In the
    conventional configuration, the binary file is located in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file server machine.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> command is not normally issued at the command shell
    prompt, but rather placed into a database server machine's
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable> file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is
    ever issued at the command shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a
    file server machine as the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>As it initializes, the Backup Server process creates the two files that
    constitute the Backup Database, <replaceable>bdb.DB0</replaceable> and <replaceable>bdb.DBSYS1</replaceable>, in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory if they do not already exist. The Backup Database
    houses information about volume sets and entries, the dump hierarchy, Tape
    Coordinators, and previously performed dump sets. Use the commands in the
    <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> suite to administer the database.</para>

    <para>The Backup Server records a trace of its activity in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/logs/BackupLog</replaceable> file. Use the <emphasis role="bold">bos getlog</emphasis> command to display
    the contents of the file.</para>

    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> process reserves port 7021 for its use. Unexpected
    behavior can occur if another process tries to reserve this port while the
    <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> process is running.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>database directory</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the pathname of an alternate directory for the Backup Database
          files, ending in a final slash (<computeroutput>/</computeroutput>). If this argument is not provided,
          the default is the <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-cellservdb</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell configuration directory</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the pathname of the directory from which the Backup Server reads
          in an alternate version of the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file. This argument is
          mandatory for correct functioning when the Backup Server is running on a
          subset of the cell's database server machines that is not a majority of
          the machines listed in the standard <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc/CellServDB</replaceable> file (which
          the Backup Server consults if this argument is not provided). It is not
          appropriate in any other circumstances.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-resetdb</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Removes all of the information in the Backup Database files in the
          <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory, leaving zero-length versions of them.  The
          backup operator must recreate the configuration entries in the database
          (for volume sets, the dump hierarchy and so on) before performing backup
          operations.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Establishes an unauthenticated connection between the issuer and the
          Backup Server, in which the Backup Server treats the issuer as the
          unprivileged user <computeroutput>anonymous</computeroutput>. It is useful only when authorization
          checking is disabled on the database server machine. In normal
          circumstances, the Backup Server allows only authorized (privileged) users
          to issue commands that affect or contact the Backup Database, and refuses
          to perform such an action even if the <emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis> flag is used.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-smallht</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Directs the Backup Server to use smaller internal hash tables for the
          Backup Database, which reduces memory requirements but can make data
          access take longer.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-servers</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>list of ubik database servers</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the database server machines on which to start the Backup
          Server. Use this argument if running the Backup Server on a subset of the
          database server machines that is not a majority of the machines listed in
          the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc/CellServDB</replaceable> file.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. For each connection with a specific UDP port on another machine,
          a separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile, GetStatus, and
          so on) sent or received. To display or otherwise access the records, use
          the Rx Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. A separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile,
          GetStatus, and so on) sent or received, aggregated over all connections to
          other machines. To display or otherwise access the records, use the Rx
          Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following example <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command creates a <computeroutput>buserver</computeroutput> process
    on the file server machine <computeroutput>fs3.abc.com</computeroutput>. It appears here on two lines
    only for legibility.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create -server fs3.abc.com -instance buserver \
                -type simple -cmd /usr/afs/bin/buserver

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="BackupLog5">BackupLog(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="CellServDB5">CellServDB(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bdb_DB05">bdb.DB0(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="backup8">backup(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
