<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="kas_noauthentication8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kas noauthentication</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kas noauthentication</refname>
    <refpurpose>Discards an authenticated identity in interactive mode</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">noauthentication</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">n</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kas noauthentication</emphasis> command closes the (presumably authenticated)
    connection that the issuer established with one or more Authentication
    Server processes when entering interactive mode. It opens a new
    unauthenticated connection to each server, assigning the issuer the
    unprivileged identity <emphasis role="bold">anonymous</emphasis>. It does not actually discard the
    user's tokens from the Cache Manager's memory (as the <emphasis role="bold">unlog</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">kas
    forgetticket</emphasis> command does). Unless authorization checking is disabled on
    each Authentication Server machine, it becomes impossible to perform any
    privileged operations within the session established by this command.</para>

    <para>This command is operative only during interactive mode, so omit the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis>
    command suite name from the command line.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following example command discards the authentication information with
    which the user entered interactive mode.</para>

<programlisting>
   ka&amp;gt; noauthentication

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>None, and no password is required.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="kas_forgetticket8">kas_forgetticket(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="kas_interactive8">kas_interactive(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="unlog1">unlog(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
