<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="kas_setfields8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kas setfields</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kas setfields</refname>
    <refpurpose>Sets fields in an Authentication Database entry</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>name of user</emphasis>&gt;
        [<emphasis role="bold">-flags</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>hex flag value or flag name expression</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-expiration</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>date of account expiration</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-lifetime</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum ticket lifetime</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number days password is valid ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>permit password reuse (yes/no)</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum successive failed login tries ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>failure penalty [hh:mm or minutes]</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-admin_username</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin principal to use for authentication</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-password_for_admin</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin password</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-servers</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>explicit list of authentication servers</emphasis>&gt;+]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">kas setf</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-na</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>name of user</emphasis>&gt;
        [<emphasis role="bold">-f</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>hex flag value or flag name expression</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-e</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>date of account expiration</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-li</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum ticket lifetime</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-pw</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number days password is valid ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-r</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>permit password reuse (yes/no)</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-at</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum successive failed login tries ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-lo</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>failure penalty [hh:mm or minutes]</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-ad</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin principal to use for authentication</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-pa</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin password</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-c</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-s</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>explicit list of authentication servers</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-no</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">kas sf</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">-na</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>name of user</emphasis>&gt;
        [<emphasis role="bold">-f</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>hex flag value or flag name expression</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-e</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>date of account expiration</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-li</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum ticket lifetime</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-pw</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number days password is valid ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-r</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>permit password reuse (yes/no)</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-at</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum successive failed login tries ([0..254])</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-lo</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>failure penalty [hh:mm or minutes]</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-ad</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin principal to use for authentication</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-pa</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin password</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-c</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-s</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>explicit list of authentication servers</emphasis>&gt;+] [<emphasis role="bold">-no</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-h</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command changes the Authentication Database entry for
    the user named by the <emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> argument in the manner specified by the
    various optional arguments, which can occur singly or in combination:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set the flags that determine whether the user has administrative
        privileges to the Authentication Server, can obtain a ticket, can change
        his or her password, and so on, include the <emphasis role="bold">-flags</emphasis> argument.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set when the Authentication Database entry expires, include the
        <emphasis role="bold">-expiration</emphasis> argument.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set the maximum ticket lifetime associated with the entry, include the
        <emphasis role="bold">-lifetime</emphasis> argument. <link linkend="klog1">klog(1)</link> explains how this value interacts with
        others to determine the actual lifetime of a token.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set when the user's password expires, include the <emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis>
        argument.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set whether the user can reuse any of the previous twenty passwords
        when creating a new one, include the <emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis> argument.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set the maximum number of times the user can provide an incorrect
        password before the Authentication Server refuses to accept any more
        attempts (locks the issuer out), include the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument.  After
        the sixth failed authentication attempt, the Authentication Server logs a
        message in the UNIX system log file (the <replaceable>syslog</replaceable> file or equivalent, for
        which the standard location varies depending on the operating system).</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To set how long the Authentication Server refuses to process
        authentication attempts for a locked-out user, set the <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis>
        argument.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command displays the settings made with this command.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>The password lifetime set with the <emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> argument begins at the
    time the user's password was last changed, rather than when this command
    is issued. It can therefore be retroactive. If, for example, a user
    changed her password 100 days ago and the password lifetime is set to 100
    days or less, the password effectively expires immediately.  To avoid
    retroactive expiration, instruct the user to change the password just
    before setting a password lifetime.</para>

    <para>Administrators whose authentication accounts have the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag enjoy
    complete access to the sensitive information in the Authentication
    Database. To prevent access by unauthorized users, use the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis>
    argument to impose a fairly strict limit on the number of times that a
    user obtaining administrative tokens can provide an incorrect
    password. Note, however, that there must be more than one account in the
    cell with the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag. The <emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command requires the
    <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> privilege, so it is important that the locked-out administrator
    (or a colleague) can access another <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput>-privileged account to unlock
    the current account.</para>

    <para>In certain circumstances, the mechanism used to enforce the number of
    failed authentication attempts can cause a lockout even though the number
    of failed attempts is less than the limit set by the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis>
    argument. Client-side authentication programs such as <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> and an
    AFS-modified login utility normally choose an Authentication Server at
    random for each authentication attempt, and in case of a failure are
    likely to choose a different Authentication Server for the next
    attempt. The Authentication Servers running on the various database server
    machines do not communicate with each other about how many times a user
    has failed to provide the correct password to them. Instead, each
    Authentication Server maintains its own separate copy of the auxiliary
    database file <replaceable>kaserverauxdb</replaceable> (located in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local</replaceable> directory
    by default), which records the number of consecutive authentication
    failures for each user account and the time of the most recent
    failure. This implementation means that on average each Authentication
    Server knows about only a fraction of the total number of failed
    attempts. The only way to avoid allowing more than the number of attempts
    set by the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument is to have each Authentication Server
    allow only some fraction of the total. More specifically, if the limit on
    failed attempts is <emphasis>f</emphasis>, and the number of Authentication Servers is <emphasis>S</emphasis>,
    then each Authentication Server can only permit a number of attempts equal
    to <emphasis>f</emphasis> divided by <emphasis>S</emphasis> (the Ubik synchronization site for the
    Authentication Server tracks any remainder, <emphasis>f</emphasis> mod <emphasis>S</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>Normally, this implementation does not reduce the number of allowed
    attempts to less than the configured limit (<emphasis>f</emphasis>). If one Authentication
    Server refuses an attempt, the client contacts another instance of the
    server, continuing until either it successfully authenticates or has
    contacted all of the servers. However, if one or more of the
    Authentication Server processes is unavailable, the limit is effectively
    reduced by a percentage equal to the quantity <emphasis>U</emphasis> divided by <emphasis>S</emphasis>, where
    <emphasis>U</emphasis> is the number of unavailable servers and <emphasis>S</emphasis> is the number normally
    available.</para>

    <para>To avoid the undesirable consequences of setting a limit on failed
    authentication attempts, note the following recommendations:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do not set the <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument (the limit on failed authentication
        attempts) too low. A limit of nine failed attempts is recommended for
        regular user accounts, to allow three failed attempts per Authentication
        Server in a cell with three database server machines.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set fairly short lockout times when including the <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis>
        argument. Although guessing passwords is a common method of attack, it is
        not a very sophisticated one. Setting a lockout time can help discourage
        attackers, but excessively long times are likely to be more of a burden to
        authorized users than to potential attackers. A lockout time of 25 minutes
        is recommended for regular user accounts.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do not assign an infinite lockout time on an account (by setting the
        <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument to <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> [zero]) unless there is a highly compelling
        reason. Such accounts almost inevitably become locked at some point,
        because each Authentication Server never resets the account's failure
        counter in its copy of the <replaceable>kaauxdb</replaceable> file (in contrast, when the lockout
        time is not infinite, the counter resets after the specified amount of
        time has passed since the last failed attempt to that Authentication
        Server). Furthermore, the only way to unlock an account with an infinite
        lockout time is for an administrator to issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis>
        command. It is especially dangerous to set an infinite lockout time on an
        administrative account; if all administrative accounts become locked, the
        only way to unlock them is to shut down all instances of the
        Authentication Server and remove the <replaceable>kaauxdb</replaceable> file on each.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-name</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>name of user</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names the Authentication Database account for which to change settings.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-flags</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>hex flag or flag name expression</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets one or more of four toggling flags, adding them to any flags
          currently set. Either specify one or more of the following strings, or
          specify a hexidecimal number that combines the indicated values. To return
          all four flags to their defaults, provide a value of <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> (zero). To set
          more than one flag at once using the strings, connect them with plus signs
          (example: <computeroutput>NOTGS+ADMIN+CPW</computeroutput>). To remove all the current flag settings
          before setting new ones, precede the list with an equal sign (example:
          <computeroutput>=NOTGS+ADMIN+CPW</computeroutput>).</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>ADMIN</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The user is allowed to issue privileged kas commands (hexadecimal
                equivalent is <computeroutput>0x004</computeroutput>, default is <computeroutput>NOADMIN</computeroutput>).</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NOTGS</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The Authentication Server's Ticket Granting Service (TGS) refuses to issue
                tickets to the user (hexadecimal equivalent is <computeroutput>0x008</computeroutput>, default is
                <computeroutput>TGS</computeroutput>).</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NOSEAL</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The Ticket Granting Service cannot use the contents of this entry's key
                field as an encryption key (hexadecimal equivalent is <computeroutput>0x020</computeroutput>, default is
                <computeroutput>SEAL</computeroutput>).</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NOCPW</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The user cannot change his or her own password or key (hexadecimal
                equivalent is <computeroutput>0x040</computeroutput>, default is <computeroutput>CPW</computeroutput>).</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-expiration</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>date of account expiration</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Determines when the entry itself expires. When a user entry expires, the
          user becomes unable to log in; when a server entry such as <computeroutput>afs</computeroutput> expires,
          all server processes that use the associated key become inaccessible.
          Provide one of the three acceptable values:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>never</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The account never expires (the default).</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis>mm/dd/yyyy</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sets the expiration date to 12:00 a.m. on the indicated date
                (month/day/year). Examples: <computeroutput>01/23/1999</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>10/07/2000</computeroutput>.</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>"<emphasis>mm/dd/yyyy hh:MM</emphasis>"</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sets the expiration date to the indicated time (hours:minutes) on the
                indicated date (month/day/year). Specify the time in 24-hour format (for
                example, <computeroutput>20:30</computeroutput> is 8:30 p.m.) Date format is the same as for a date
                alone. Surround the entire instance with quotes because it contains a
                space. Examples: <computeroutput>"01/23/1999 22:30"</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>"10/07/2000 3:45"</computeroutput>.</para>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>Acceptable values for the year range from <computeroutput>1970</computeroutput> (1 January 1970 is time
          0 in the standard UNIX date representation) through <computeroutput>2037</computeroutput> (2037 is the
          maximum because the UNIX representation cannot accommodate dates later
          than a value in February 2038).</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-lifetime</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum ticket lifetime</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the maximum lifetime that the Authentication Server's Ticket
          Granting Service (TGS) can assign to a ticket. If the account belongs to a
          user, this value is the maximum lifetime of a token issued to the user. If
          the account corresponds to a server such as <computeroutput>afs</computeroutput>, this value is the
          maximum lifetime of a ticket that the TGS issues to clients for
          presentation to the server during mutual authentication.</para>

          <para>Specify an integer that represents a number of seconds (3600 equals one
          hour), or include a colon in the number to indicate a number of hours and
          minutes (<computeroutput>10:00</computeroutput> equals 10 hours). If this argument is omitted, the
          default setting is 100:00 hours (360000 seconds).</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-pwexpires</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number of days password is valid</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the number of days after the user's password was last changed that it
          remains valid. Provide an integer from the range <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> through <computeroutput>254</computeroutput> to
          specify the number of days until expiration, or the value <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to indicate
          that the password never expires (the default).</para>

          <para>When the password expires, the user is unable to authenticate, but has 30
          days after the expiration date in which to use the <emphasis role="bold">kpasswd</emphasis> command to
          change the password (after that, only an administrator can change it by
          using the <emphasis role="bold">kas setpassword</emphasis> command). Note that the clock starts at the
          time the password was last changed, not when the <emphasis role="bold">kas setfields</emphasis> command
          is issued. To avoid retroactive expiration, have the user change the
          password just before issuing a command that includes this argument.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-reuse</emphasis> (yes | no)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies whether or not the user can reuse any of his or her last 20
          passwords. The acceptable values are <computeroutput>yes</computeroutput> to allow reuse of old
          passwords (the default) and <computeroutput>no</computeroutput> to prohibit reuse of a password that is
          similar to one of the previous 20 passwords.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>maximum successive failed login tries</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the number of consecutive times the user can provide an incorrect
          password during authentication (using the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command or a login
          utility that grants AFS tokens). When the user exceeds the limit, the
          Authentication Server rejects further attempts (locks the user out) for
          the amount of time specified by the <emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> argument. Provide an
          integer from the range <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> through <computeroutput>254</computeroutput> to specify the number of
          failures allowed, or <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to indicate that there is no limit on
          authentication attempts (the default value).</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-locktime</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>failure penalty</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies how long the Authentication Server refuses authentication
          attempts from a user who has exceeded the failure limit set by the
          <emphasis role="bold">-attempts</emphasis> argument.</para>

          <para>Specify a number of hours and minutes (<emphasis>hh:mm</emphasis>) or minutes only (<emphasis>mm</emphasis>),
          from the range <computeroutput>01</computeroutput> (one minute) through <computeroutput>36:00</computeroutput> (36 hours). The <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis>
          command interpreter automatically reduces any larger value to <computeroutput>36:00</computeroutput> and
          also rounds up any non-zero value to the next higher multiple of 8.5
          minutes. A value of <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> (zero) sets an infinite lockout time; an
          administrator must issue the <emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command to unlock the account.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin_username</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin principal</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the user identity under which to authenticate with the
          Authentication Server for execution of the command. For more details, see
          <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-password_for_admin</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>admin password</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the password of the command's issuer. If it is omitted (as
          recommended), the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> command interpreter prompts for it and does not
          echo it visibly. For more details, see <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names the cell in which to run the command. For more details, see
          <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-servers</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>authentication servers</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names each machine running an Authentication Server with which to
          establish a connection. For more details, see <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigns the unprivileged identity <computeroutput>anonymous</computeroutput> to the issuer. For more
          details, see <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>In the following example, an administrator using the <computeroutput>admin</computeroutput> account
    grants administrative privilege to the user <computeroutput>smith</computeroutput>, and sets the
    Authentication Database entry to expire at midnight on 31 December 2000.</para>

<programlisting>
   % kas setfields -name smith -flags ADMIN -expiration 12/31/2000
   Password for admin:

</programlisting>
      <para>In the following example, an administrator using the <computeroutput>admin</computeroutput> account sets
      the user <computeroutput>pat</computeroutput>'s password to expire in 60 days from when it last changed,
      and prohibits reuse of passwords.</para>

<programlisting>
   % kas setfields -name pat -pwexpires 60 -reuse no
   Password for admin:

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Privilege Required</title>
        <para>The issuer must have the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput> flag set on his or her Authentication
        Database entry.</para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para><link linkend="kaserverauxdb5">kaserverauxdb(5)</link>,
        <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>,
        <link linkend="kas_examine8">kas_examine(8)</link>,
        <link linkend="kas_setpassword8">kas_setpassword(8)</link>,
        <link linkend="kas_unlock8">kas_unlock(8)</link>,
        <link linkend="klog1">klog(1)</link>,
        <link linkend="kpasswd1">kpasswd(1)</link></para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Copyright</title>
        <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
        converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
        Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
