<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="kaserver8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kaserver</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kaserver</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the Authentication Server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-noAuth</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-fastKeys</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dbpath</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-localfiles</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>lclpath</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-minhours</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>n</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-servers</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>serverlist</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis>]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> command initializes the Authentication Server, which runs
    on every database server machine. In the conventional configuration, its
    binary file is located in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file server
    machine.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> command is not normally issued at the command shell prompt
    but rather placed into a file server machine's <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable>
    file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is ever issued at the command
    shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a database server machine as
    the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>As it initializes, the Authentication Server process creates the two files
    that constitute the Authentication Database, <replaceable>kaserver.DB0</replaceable> and
    <replaceable>kaserver.DBSYS1</replaceable>, in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory if they do not already
    exist. Use the commands in the <emphasis role="bold">kas</emphasis> suite to administer the database.</para>

    <para>The Authentication Server is responsible for several aspects of AFS
    security, including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maintenance of all AFS server encryption keys and user passwords in the
        Authentication Database.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Creation of the tickets and tokens that users and servers use to establish
        secure connections. Its Ticket Granting Service (TGS) component performs
        this function.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The Authentication Server records a trace of its activity in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/logs/AuthLog</replaceable> file. Use the <emphasis role="bold">bos getlog</emphasis> command to display
    the contents of the file. Use the <emphasis role="bold">kdb</emphasis> command to read the protected
    files associated with the <replaceable>AuthLog</replaceable> file, <replaceable>AuthLog.dir</replaceable> and
    <replaceable>AuthLog.pag</replaceable>.</para>

    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-noAuth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigns the unprivileged identity <computeroutput>anonymous</computeroutput> to the issuer. Thus, it
          establishes an unauthenticated connection between the issuer and the
          Authentication Server. It is useful only when authorization checking is
          disabled on the database server machine. In normal circumstances, the
          Authentication Server allows only authorized (privileged) users to issue
          commands that affect or contact the Authentication Database and will
          refuse to perform such an action even if the <emphasis role="bold">-noAuth</emphasis> flag is used.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-fastKeys</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Is a test flag for use by the AFS Development staff; it serves no
          functional purpose.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>dbpath</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the pathname of an alternate directory in which the
          Authentication Database files reside. Provide the complete pathname,
          ending in the base filename to which the <computeroutput>.DB0</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>.DBSYS1</computeroutput> extensions
          are appended. For example, the appropriate value for the default database
          files is <replaceable>/usr/afs/db/kaserver</replaceable>.</para>

          <para>Provide the <emphasis role="bold">-localfiles</emphasis> argument along with this one; otherwise, the
          <emphasis role="bold">-localfiles</emphasis> argument is also set to the value of this argument, which
          is probably inappropriate.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-localfiles</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>lclpath</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the pathname of an alternate directory in which the auxiliary
          Authentication Database file resides. Provide the complete pathname,
          ending in the base filename to which the <computeroutput>auxdb</computeroutput> suffix is appended. For
          example, the appropriate value for the default auxiliary database file is
          <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/kaserver</replaceable>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-minhours</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>n</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the minimum number of hours that must pass between password
          changes made by any regular user. System administrators (with the <computeroutput>ADMIN</computeroutput>
          flag in their Authentication Database entry) can change passwords as often
          as desired. Setting a minimum time between password changes is not
          recommended.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-servers</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>authentication servers</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names each database server machine running an Authentication Server with
          which the local Authentication Server is to synchronize its copy of the
          Authentication Database, rather than with the machines listed in the local
          <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc/CellServDB</replaceable> file.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. For each connection with a specific UDP port on another machine,
          a separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile, GetStatus, and
          so on) sent or received. To display or otherwise access the records, use
          the Rx Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. A separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile,
          GetStatus, and so on) sent or received, aggregated over all connections to
          other machines. To display or otherwise access the records, use the Rx
          Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command creates a <computeroutput>kaserver</computeroutput> process on
    <computeroutput>fs3.abc.com</computeroutput> (the command appears on two lines here only for
    legibility):</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create -server fs3.abc.com -instance kaserver \
                -type simple -cmd /usr/afs/bin/kaserver

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="AuthLog5">AuthLog(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="CellServDB5">CellServDB(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="kaserver_DB05">kaserver.DB0(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="kaserverauxdb5">kaserverauxdb(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos8">bos(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="kdb8">kdb(8)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
