<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="ptserver8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>ptserver</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>ptserver</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the Protection Server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">ptserver</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>db path</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number of processes</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-rebuildDB</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis>]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">ptserver</emphasis> command initializes the Protection Server, which must run
    on every database server machine. In the conventional configuration, its
    binary file is located in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file server
    machine.</para>

    <para>The ptserver command is not normally issued at the command shell prompt,
    but rather placed into a database server machine's
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable> file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is
    ever issued at the command shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a
    file server machine as the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>The Protection Server performs the following tasks:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maintains the Protection Database, which contains entries for every user
        and group in the cell. Use the <emphasis role="bold">pts</emphasis> commands to administer the database.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allocates AFS IDs for new user, machine and group entries and maps each ID
        to the corresponding name.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Generates a current protection subgroup (CPS) at the File Server's
        request. The CPS lists all groups to which a user or machine belongs.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-database</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>db path</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the pathname of an alternate directory in which the Protection
          Database files reside. Provide the complete pathname, ending in the base
          filename to which the <computeroutput>.DB0</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>.DBSYS1</computeroutput> extensions are appended. For
          example, the appropriate value for the default database files is
          <replaceable>/usr/afs/db/prdb</replaceable>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number of processes</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the number of server lightweight processes (LWPs) to run.  Provide a
          positive integer from the range <computeroutput>3</computeroutput> to <computeroutput>16</computeroutput>. The default value is <computeroutput>3</computeroutput>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-rebuildDB</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Rebuilds the Protection Database at the beginning of Protection Server
          initialization. Use this argument only in consultation with AFS
          Development or Product Support.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. For each connection with a specific UDP port on another machine,
          a separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile, GetStatus, and
          so on) sent or received. To display or otherwise access the records, use
          the Rx Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. A separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile,
          GetStatus, and so on) sent or received, aggregated over all connections to
          other machines. To display or otherwise access the records, use the Rx
          Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command creates a <computeroutput>ptserver</computeroutput> process on the
    machine <computeroutput>fs3.abc.com</computeroutput>. The command appears here on multiple lines only
    for legibility.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create -server fs3.abc.com -instance ptserver \
                -type simple -cmd /usr/afs/bin/ptserver

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="prdb_DB05">prdb.DB0(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="pts1">pts(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
