<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="upclient8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>upclient</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>upclient</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the client portion of the Update Server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">upclient</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>&gt; [<emphasis role="bold">-crypt</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-t</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>retry time</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis>]* &lt;<emphasis>dir</emphasis>&gt;+ [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The upclient command initializes the client portion of the Update
    Server. In the conventional configuration, its binary file is located in
    the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file server machine.</para>

    <para>The upclient command is not normally issued at the command shell prompt
    but rather placed into a file server machine's <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable>
    file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is ever issued at the command
    shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a database server machine as
    the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>The upclient process periodically checks that all files in each local
    directory named by the <emphasis>dir</emphasis> argument match the files in the
    corresponding directory on the source machine named by the <emphasis>hostname</emphasis>
    argument. If a file does not match, the <emphasis role="bold">upclient</emphasis> process requests the
    source copy from the <emphasis role="bold">upserver</emphasis> process running on the source machine.</para>

    <para>By default, the <emphasis role="bold">upclient</emphasis> process requests that the <emphasis role="bold">upserver</emphasis> process
    encrypt the data before transferring it.  Use the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag to
    request unencrypted transfer if appropriate. (The <emphasis role="bold">-crypt</emphasis> flag
    explicitly sets the default.)</para>

    <para>In the conventional configuration, separate instances of the <emphasis role="bold">upclient</emphasis>
    process request data from the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> and <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable>
    directories, except on machines for which the system control machine is
    also the binary distribution machine for the machine's system type. The
    conventional names for the separate instances are <computeroutput>upclientbin</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>upclientetc</computeroutput> respectively.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">upclient</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">upserver</emphasis> processes always mutually authenticate,
    whether or not the data they pass is encrypted; they use the key with the
    highest key version number in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc/KeyFile</replaceable> file to
    construct a server ticket for mutual authentication.</para>

    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>Do not use the Update Server to distribute the contents of the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory using the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> option.  The contents of
    this directory are sensitive.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>&lt;<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names either the cell's system control machine (if the requested directory
          is <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable>), or the binary distribution machine for the local
          machine's CPU and operating system type (if the requested directory is
          <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable>).</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-crypt</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Requests the transfer of data from the upserver process in encrypted
          form. This is the default; this flag just sets the default explicitly.
          Do not use this flag with the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Requests transfer of data from the <emphasis role="bold">upserver</emphasis> process in unencrypted
          form. Provide this flag or the <emphasis role="bold">-crypt</emphasis> flag, but not both.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-t</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>retry time</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies how often to check for changes in each specified directory, as a
          number of seconds. If this argument is omitted, the default is <computeroutput>300</computeroutput> (5
          minutes). This argument determines the maximum amount of time it takes for
          a change made on the source machine to propagate to this machine.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis>*</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Writes a trace of the upclient process's operations on the standard output
          stream, which usually corresponds to the machine console. Provide one,
          two, or three instances of the flag; each additional instance generates
          increasingly numerous and detailed messages.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>&lt;<emphasis>dir</emphasis>&gt;+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names each directory to check for modified files. The conventional choices
          are the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable>, in which case the recommended name for the process
              (assigned with the <emphasis role="bold">-instance</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command) is
              <computeroutput>upclientbin</computeroutput>. The <emphasis>hostname</emphasis> is the binary distribution machine for the
              local machine's system type. You may wish to use the <emphasis role="bold">-clear</emphasis> flag for
              the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory, since binaries are not particularly
              sensitive and encrypting them takes system resources.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable>, in which case the recommended name for the process
              (assigned with the <emphasis role="bold">-instance</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command) is
              <computeroutput>upclientetc</computeroutput>. The <emphasis>hostname</emphasis> is the cell's system control machine. Use
              the <emphasis role="bold">-crypt</emphasis> flag for the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory, since it contains
              the <replaceable>KeyFile</replaceable> file and other data vital to cell security.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following bos create command creates an <computeroutput>upclientbin</computeroutput> process on the
    machine <computeroutput>fs4.abc.com</computeroutput> that refers to the machine <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput> as the
    source for the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory (thus <computeroutput>fs1.abc.com</computeroutput> is the
    binary distribution machine for machines of <computeroutput>fs4.abc.com</computeroutput>'s type). The
    files in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory are distributed every 120 seconds.
    The command requests transfer in unencrypted form.</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create  -server fs4.abc.com -instance upclientbin -type simple \
                 -cmd "/usr/afs/bin/upclient fs1.abc.com -clear \
                 -t 120 /usr/afs/bin"

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="upserver8">upserver(8)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
