<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="uss8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>uss</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>uss</refname>
    <refpurpose>Introduction to the uss command suite</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The commands in the <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> command suite help administrators to create AFS
    user accounts more easily and efficiently. If <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> commands are not
    used, creating an account requires issuing at least six separate commands
    to five different AFS servers.</para>

    <para>There are three main commands in the suite:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">uss add</emphasis> command creates a single complete user account, based on
        command line arguments and instructions in a template file.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">uss bulk</emphasis> command creates multiple complete accounts at once, based
        on command line arguments, instructions in a template file and a bulk
        input file.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">uss delete</emphasis> command removes most parts of a user account.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>To obtain help, issue the <emphasis role="bold">uss apropos</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">uss help</emphasis> commands.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <para>The following arguments and flags are available on many commands in the
    <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> suite. The reference page for each command also lists them, but
    they are described here in greater detail.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-admin</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>administrator to authenticate</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the AFS user name under which to establish a connection to the
          AFS server processes that administer the various parts of a user
          account. If it is omitted, the connection is established under the
          issuer's effective user ID (his or her identity in the local file
          system). Even when this argument is included, UNIX commands that run
          during the <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> operation (for instance, the UNIX <replaceable>/etc/chown</replaceable> command)
          run under the effective user ID.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>cell name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names the cell in which to run the command. It is acceptable to abbreviate
          the cell name to the shortest form that distinguishes it from the other
          entries in the <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc/CellServDB</replaceable> file on the local machine. If
          the <emphasis role="bold">-cell</emphasis> argument is omitted, the command interpreter determines the
          name of the local cell by reading the following in order:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The value of the AFSCELL environment variable.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The local <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc/ThisCell</replaceable> file.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-dryrun</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reports actions that the command interpreter needs to perform when
          executing the <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> operation, without actually performing them. Include
          this flag to verify that the command produces the desired account
          configuration. Combine it with the <emphasis role="bold">-verbose</emphasis> flag to yield even more
          detailed information. Note that the output does not necessarily reveal all
          possible problems that can prevent successful execution of the command,
          especially those that result from transient server or network outages.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints a command's online help message on the standard output stream. Do
          not combine this flag with any of the command's other options; when it is
          provided, the command interpreter ignores all other options, and only
          prints the help message.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-skipauth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Bypasses mutual authentication with the AFS Authentication Server,
          allowing a site that uses Kerberos instead of the AFS Authentication
          Server to substitute that form of authentication.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Privilege Required</title>
    <para>The issuer of a <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> command must have all the rights required for
    performing the equivalent actions individually. See each <emphasis role="bold">uss</emphasis> command's
    reference page.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="uss5">uss(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_bulk5">uss_bulk(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_add8">uss_add(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_apropos8">uss_apropos(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_bulk8">uss_bulk(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_delete8">uss_delete(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="uss_help8">uss_help(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
