<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="vlserver8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>vlserver</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>vlserver</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the Volume Location Server</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">vlserver</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>lwp processes</emphasis>&gt;] [<emphasis role="bold">-nojumbo</emphasis>]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">vlserver</emphasis> command initializes the Volume Location (VL) Server, which
    runs on every database server machine. In the conventional configuration,
    its binary file is located in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file
    server machine.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">vlserver</emphasis> command is not normally issued at the command shell prompt
    but rather placed into a file server machine's <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable>
    file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is ever issued at the command
    shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a database server machine as
    the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>As it initializes, the VL Server process creates the two files that
    constitute the Volume Location Database (VLDB), <replaceable>vldb.DB0</replaceable> and
    <replaceable>vldb.DBSYS1</replaceable>, in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory if they do not already
    exist. Use the commands in the <emphasis role="bold">vos</emphasis> suite to administer the database.</para>

    <para>The VL Server maintains the record of volume locations in the Volume
    Location Database (VLDB). When the Cache Manager fills a file request from
    an application program, it first contacts the VL Server to learn which
    file server machine currently houses the volume that contains the file.
    The Cache Manager then requests the file from the File Server process
    running on that file server machine.</para>

    <para>The VL Server records a trace of its activity in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/logs/VLLog</replaceable> file. Use the <emphasis role="bold">bos getlog</emphasis> command to display the
    contents of the file. By default, it records on a minimal number of
    messages. For instructions on increasing the amount of logging, see
    <link linkend="VLLog5">VLLog(5)</link>.</para>

    <para>By default, the VL Server runs nine lightweight processes (LWPs). To
    change the number, use the <emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> argument.</para>

    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>lwp processes</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the number of server lightweight processes (LWPs) to run.  Provide an
          integer between <computeroutput>4</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>16</computeroutput>. The default is <computeroutput>9</computeroutput>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-nojumbo</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prohibits the server from sending or receiving jumbograms. A jumbogram is
          a large-size packet composed of 2 to 4 normal Rx data packets that share
          the same header. The VL Server uses jumbograms by default, but some
          routers are not capable of properly breaking the jumbogram into smaller
          packets and reassembling them.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. For each connection with a specific UDP port on another machine,
          a separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile, GetStatus, and
          so on) sent or received. To display or otherwise access the records, use
          the Rx Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. A separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile,
          GetStatus, and so on) sent or received, aggregated over all connections to
          other machines. To display or otherwise access the records, use the Rx
          Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command creates a vlserver process on the
    machine <computeroutput>fs2.abc.com</computeroutput> that uses six lightweight processes. Type the
    command on a single line:</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create -server fs2.abc.com -instance vlserver -type simple \
                -cmd "/usr/afs/bin/vlserver -p 6"

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="VLLog5">VLLog(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="vldb_DB05">vldb.DB0(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
