<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="volserver8">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>volserver</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>volserver</refname>
    <refpurpose>Initializes the Volume Server component of the fs process</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Synopsis</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">volserver</emphasis> [<emphasis role="bold">-log</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number of processes</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-udpsize</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>size of socket buffer in bytes</emphasis>&gt;]
        [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis>] [<emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis>]</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">volserver</emphasis> command initializes the Volume Server component of the
    <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> process. In the conventional configuration, its binary file is
    located in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/bin</replaceable> directory on a file server machine.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">volserver</emphasis> command is not normally issued at the command shell
    prompt but rather placed into a file server machine's
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/BosConfig</replaceable> file with the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command. If it is
    ever issued at the command shell prompt, the issuer must be logged onto a
    database server machine as the local superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>The Volume Server records a trace of its activity in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/logs/VolserLog</replaceable> file. Use the <emphasis role="bold">bos getlog</emphasis> command to display
    the contents of the file.</para>

    <para>The Volume Server processes the <emphasis role="bold">vos</emphasis> commands that administrators use to
    create, delete, move, and replicate volumes, as well as prepare them for
    archiving to tape or other media.</para>

    <para>By default, the VL Server runs nine lightweight processes (LWPs). To
    change the number, use the <emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> argument.</para>

    <para>This command does not use the syntax conventions of the AFS command
    suites. Provide the command name and all option names in full.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-log</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Records in the /usr/afs/logs/VolserLog file the names of all users who
          successfully initiate a <emphasis role="bold">vos</emphasis> command. The Volume Server also records any
          file removals that result from issuing the <emphasis role="bold">vos release</emphasis> command with the
          <emphasis role="bold">-f</emphasis> flag.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-p</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>number of processes</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the number of server lightweight processes (LWPs) to run.  Provide an
          integer between <computeroutput>4</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>16</computeroutput>. The default is <computeroutput>9</computeroutput>.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-udpsize</emphasis> &lt;<emphasis>size of socket buffer</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the size of the UDP buffer in bytes, which is 64 KB by
          default. Provide a positive integer, preferably larger than the default.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_peer_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. For each connection with a specific UDP port on another machine,
          a separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile, GetStatus, and
          so on) sent or received. To display or otherwise access the records, use
          the Rx Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-enable_process_stats</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Activates the collection of Rx statistics and allocates memory for their
          storage. A separate record is kept for each type of RPC (FetchFile,
          GetStatus, and so on) sent or received, aggregated over all connections to
          other machines. To display or otherwise access the records, use the Rx
          Monitoring API.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">-help</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prints the online help for this command. All other valid options are
          ignored.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis> command creates a <computeroutput>volserver</computeroutput> process on the
    machine <computeroutput>fs2.abc.com</computeroutput>:</para>

<programlisting>
   % bos create -server fs2.abc.com -instance volserver -type simple \
                 -cmd /usr/afs/bin/volserver

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Privilege Required</title>
      <para>The issuer must be logged in as the superuser <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> on a file server
      machine to issue the command at a command shell prompt. It is conventional
      instead to create and start the process by issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos create</emphasis>
      command.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="BosConfig5">BosConfig(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="VolserLog5">VolserLog(5)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_create8">bos_create(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="vos1">vos(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
