<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="afsmonitor5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>afsmonitor</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>afsmonitor</refname>
    <refpurpose>Provides instructions for the afsmonitor command</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The afsmonitor configuration file determines which machines the
    <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> command probes for File Server or Cache Manager statistics
    and which statistics it gathers. Use the <emphasis role="bold">-config</emphasis> argument to the
    <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> command to identify the configuration file to use.</para>

    <para>The instructions that can appear in the configuration file are as follows:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>cm &lt;<emphasis>host name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names a client machine for which to display Cache Manager statistics. The
          order of <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> lines in the file determines the order in which client
          machines appear from top to bottom on the <computeroutput>System Overview</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>Cache
          Managers</computeroutput> output screens.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>fs &lt;<emphasis>host name</emphasis>&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Names a file server machine for which to display File Server
          statistics. The order of <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> lines in the file determines the order in
          which file server machines appear from top to bottom on the <computeroutput>System
          Overview</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> output screens.</para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>thresh (fs | cm) &lt;<emphasis>field</emphasis>&gt; &lt;<emphasis>thresh</emphasis>&gt; [&lt;<emphasis>cmd</emphasis>&gt;] [&lt;<emphasis>arg</emphasis>&gt; ...]</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigns the threshold value <emphasis>thresh</emphasis> to the statistic <emphasis>field</emphasis>, for
          either a File Server statistic (<computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>) or a Cache Manager statistic
          (<computeroutput>cm</computeroutput>). The optional <emphasis>cmd</emphasis> field names a binary or script to execute
          each time the value of the statistic changes from being below <emphasis>thresh</emphasis> to
          being at or above <emphasis>thresh</emphasis>. A change between two values that both exceed
          <emphasis>thresh</emphasis> does not retrigger the binary or script. The optional <emphasis>arg</emphasis>
          fields are additional values that the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program passes as
          arguments to the <emphasis>cmd</emphasis> command. If any of them include one or more
          spaces, enclose the entire field in double quotes.</para>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> program passes the following parameters to the <emphasis>cmd</emphasis>:</para>

<programlisting>
    &amp;lt;hostname&amp;gt; (fs|cm) &amp;lt;field&amp;gt; &amp;lt;thresh&amp;gt; &amp;lt;actual&amp;gt; [&amp;lt;arg&amp;gt; ...]

</programlisting>
            <para>The parameters <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput>, &lt;field&gt;, &lt;thresh&gt;, and &lt;arg&gt; correspond to
            the values with the same name on the thresh line. The &lt;hostname&gt; parameter
            identifies the file server or client machine where the statistic has
            crossed the threshold, and the &lt;actual&gt; parameter is the actual value of
            &lt;field&gt; that exceeds the threshold value.</para>

            <para>Use the <computeroutput>thresh</computeroutput> line to set either a global threshold, which applies to
            all file server machines listed on <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> lines or client machines listed
            on <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> lines in the configuration file, or a machine-specific threshold,
            which applies to only one file server or client machine.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>To set a global threshold, place the thresh line before any of the <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>
                or <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> lines in the file.</para>

              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>To set a machine-specific threshold, place the thresh line below the
                corresponding <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> line, and above any other <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput>
                lines. A machine-specific threshold value always overrides the
                corresponding global threshold, if set. Do not place a <computeroutput>thresh fs</computeroutput> line
                directly after a <computeroutput>cm</computeroutput> line or a <computeroutput>thresh cm</computeroutput> line directly after a <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>
                line.</para>

              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>show (fs | cm) <emphasis>field/group/section</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies which individual statistic, group of statistics, or section of
            statistics to display on the <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput> screen (<computeroutput>fs</computeroutput>) or <computeroutput>Cache
            Managers</computeroutput> screen (<computeroutput>cm</computeroutput>) and the order in which to display them. The
            appendix of <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> statistics in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration
            Guide</emphasis> specifies the group and section to which each statistic
            belongs. Include as many <computeroutput>show</computeroutput> lines as necessary to customize the
            screen display as desired, and place them anywhere in the file. The
            top-to-bottom order of the <computeroutput>show</computeroutput> lines in the configuration file
            determines the left-to-right order in which the statistics appear on the
            corresponding screen.</para>

            <para>If there are no <computeroutput>show</computeroutput> lines in the configuration file, then the screens
            display all statistics for both Cache Managers and File
            Servers. Similarly, if there are no <computeroutput>show fs</computeroutput> lines, the <computeroutput>File Servers</computeroutput>
            screen displays all file server statistics, and if there are no <computeroutput>show cm</computeroutput>
            lines, the <computeroutput>Cache Managers</computeroutput> screen displays all client statistics.</para>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term># <emphasis>comments</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Precedes a line of text that the afsmonitor program ignores because of the
            initial number (<computeroutput>#</computeroutput>) sign, which must appear in the very first column of
            the line.</para>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>For a list of the values that can appear in the <emphasis>field/group/section</emphasis>
      field of a <computeroutput>show</computeroutput> instruction, see the <emphasis role="bold">afsmonitor</emphasis> statistics appendix
      to the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis>.</para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="afsmonitor1">afsmonitor(1)</link></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
