<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="bdb_DB05">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>bdb.DB0, bdb.DBSYS1</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>bdb.DB0, bdb.DBSYS1</refname>
    <refpurpose>Contain the Backup Database and associated log</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>bdb.DB0</replaceable> file contains the Backup Database, which records
    configuration information used by the AFS Backup System along with
    cross-indexed records of the tapes created and volumes dumped using the
    Backup System commands.</para>

    <para>The <replaceable>bdb.DBSYS1</replaceable> file is a log file in which the Backup Server
    (<emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis> process) logs each database operation before performing
    it. When an operation is interrupted, the Backup Server replays the log to
    complete the operation.</para>

    <para>Both files are in binary format and reside in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory
    on each database server machine that runs the Backup Server.  When the
    Backup Server starts or restarts on a given machine, it establishes a
    connection with its peers and verifies that its copy of the <replaceable>bdb.DB0</replaceable>
    file matches the copy on the other database server machines. If not, the
    Backup Servers use AFS's distributed database technology, Ubik, to
    distribute to all of the machines the copy of the database with the
    highest version number.</para>

    <para>Use the commands in the backup suite to administer the Backup Database. It
    is advisable to create a backup copy of the <replaceable>bdb.DB0</replaceable> file on tape on a
    regular basis, using the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">tar</emphasis> command or another local disk backup
    utility.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="backup8">backup(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="backup_savedb8">backup_savedb(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="buserver8">buserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
