<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="BosLog5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>BosLog</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>BosLog</refname>
    <refpurpose>Traces BOS Server operations</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>BosLog</replaceable> file records a trace of Basic OverSeer (BOS) Server
    (<emphasis role="bold">bosserver</emphasis> process) operations on the local machine and describes any
    error conditions it encounters.</para>

    <para>If the <replaceable>BosLog</replaceable> file does not already exist in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/logs</replaceable>
    directory when the BOS Server starts, the server process creates it and
    writes initial start-up messages to it. If there is an existing file, the
    BOS server renames it to <replaceable>BosLog.old</replaceable>, overwriting the existing
    <replaceable>BosLog.old</replaceable> file if it exists.</para>

    <para>The file is in ASCII format. Administrators listed in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc/UserList</replaceable> file can use the <emphasis role="bold">bos getlog</emphasis> command to display
    its contents. Alternatively, log onto the server machine and use a text
    editor or a file display command such as the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">cat</emphasis> command. By
    default, the mode bits on the <replaceable>BosLog</replaceable> file grant the required <computeroutput>r</computeroutput>
    (read) permission to all users.</para>

    <para>The BOS Server records operations only as it completes them, and cannot
    recover from failures by reviewing the file. The log contents are useful
    for administrative evaluation of process failures and other problems.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="UserList5">UserList(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="bos_getlog8">bos_getlog(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="bosserver8">bosserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
