<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="cacheinfo5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>cacheinfo</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>cacheinfo</refname>
    <refpurpose>Defines configuration parameters for the Cache Manager</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>cacheinfo</replaceable> file defines configuration parameters for the Cache
    Manager, which reads the file as it initializes.</para>

    <para>The file contains a single line of ASCII text and must reside in the
    <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc</replaceable> directory. Use a text editor to create it during initial
    configuration of the client machine; the required format is as follows:</para>

<programlisting>
   &amp;lt;mount&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;cache&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;size&amp;gt;

</programlisting>
      <para>where</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;mount&gt;</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Names the local disk directory at which the Cache Manager mounts the AFS
            namespace. It must exist before the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> program runs. The conventional
            value is <replaceable>/afs</replaceable>. Using any other value prevents traversal of pathnames
            that begin with <replaceable>/afs</replaceable> (such as pathnames to files in foreign cells that
            do use the conventional name).  The <emphasis role="bold">-mountdir</emphasis> argument to the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis>
            command overrides this value.</para>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;cache&gt;</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Names the local disk directory to use as a cache. It must exist before the
            <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> program runs. The standard value is <replaceable>/usr/vice/cache</replaceable>, but it is
            acceptable to substitute a directory on a partition with more available
            space. Although the Cache Manager ignores this field when configuring a
            memory cache, a value must always appear in it. The <emphasis role="bold">-cachedir</emphasis> argument
            to the <emphasis role="bold">afsd</emphasis> command overrides this value.</para>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;size&gt;</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the cache size as a number of 1-kilobyte blocks. Larger caches
            generally yield better performance, but a disk cache must not exceed 90%
            of the space available on the cache partition (85% for AIX systems), and a
            memory cache must use no more than 25% of available machine memory.</para>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">-blocks</emphasis> argument to the afsd command overrides this value. To reset
            cache size without rebooting on a machine that uses disk caching, use the
            <emphasis role="bold">fs setcachesize</emphasis> command. To display the current size of a disk or
            memory cache between reboots, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs getcacheparms</emphasis> command.</para>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <para>The following example cacheinfo file mounts the AFS namespace at <replaceable>/afs</replaceable>,
      establishes a disk cache in the <replaceable>/usr/vice/cache</replaceable> directory, and defines
      cache size as 50,000 1-kilobyte blocks.</para>

<programlisting>
   /afs:/usr/vice/cache:50000

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para><link linkend="afsd8">afsd(8)</link>,
        <link linkend="fs_getcacheparms1">fs_getcacheparms(1)</link>,
        <link linkend="fs_setcachesize1">fs_setcachesize(1)</link></para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Copyright</title>
        <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
        converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
        Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
