<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="CellServDB5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>CellServDB</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>CellServDB</refname>
    <refpurpose>Lists the database server machines in AFS cells</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>There are two versions of the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file, both of which have the
    same format.  One version is used by an AFS client and lists all of the
    database server machines in the local cell and any foreign cell that is to
    be accessible from the local client machine.  The other version is used on
    servers and lists only the database servers in the local cell.</para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Client CellServDB</title>
      <para>The client version of the CellServDB file lists the database server
      machines in the local cell and any foreign cell that is to be accessible
      from the local client machine. Database server machines run the
      Authentication Server, Backup Server, Protection Server, and Volume
      Location (VL) Server (the <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">ptserver</emphasis>, and
      <emphasis role="bold">vlserver</emphasis>) processes, which maintain the cell's administrative AFS
      databases.</para>

      <para>The Cache Manager and other processes running on a client machine use the
      list of a cell's database server machines when performing several common
      functions, including:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Fetching files. The Cache Manager contacts the VL Server to learn
          the location of the volume containing a requested file or directory.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Authenticating users. Client-side authentication programs (such as an
          AFS-modified login utility or the <emphasis role="bold">klog</emphasis> command interpreter) contact the
          Authentication Server to obtain a server ticket, which the AFS server
          processes accept as proof that the user is authenticated.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Creating protection groups. The <emphasis role="bold">pts</emphasis> command interpreter contacts the
          Protection Server when users create protection groups or request
          information from the Protection Database.</para>

        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The Cache Manager reads the CellServDB file into kernel memory as it
      initializes, and not again until the machine next reboots. To enable users
      on the local machine to continue accessing the cell correctly, update the
      file whenever a database server machine is added to or removed from a
      cell. To update the kernel-resident list of database server machines
      without rebooting, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs newcell</emphasis> command.</para>

      <para>The <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file is in ASCII format and must reside in the
      <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc</replaceable> directory on each AFS client machine. Use a text editor
      to create and maintain it.</para>

      <para>The client version of the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file is distinct from the server
      version, which resides in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory on each AFS server
      machine. The client version lists the database server machines in every
      AFS cell that the cell administrator wants the machine's users to be able
      to access, whereas the server version lists only the local cell's database
      server machines.</para>

    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Server CellServDB</title>
      <para>The server version of the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file lists the local cell's
      database server machines. These machines run the Authentication Server,
      Backup Server, Protection Server, and Volume Location (VL) Server (the
      <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">buserver</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">ptserver</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">vlserver</emphasis>) processes, which
      maintain the cell's administrative AFS databases. The initial version of
      the file is created with the <emphasis role="bold">bos setcellname</emphasis> command during the
      installation of the cell's server machine, which is automatically recorded
      as the cell's first database server machine. When adding or removing
      database server machines, be sure to update this file appropriately. It
      must reside in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory on each AFS server machine.</para>

      <para>The database server processes consult the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file to learn
      about their peers, with which they must maintain constant connections in
      order to coordinate replication of changes across the multiple copies of
      each database. The other AFS server processes consult the file to learn
      which machines to contact for information from the databases when they
      need it.</para>

      <para>Although the server <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file is in ASCII format, do not use a
      text editor to alter it. Instead always use the appropriate commands from
      the <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis> command suite:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos addhost</emphasis> command to add a machine to the file.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos listhosts</emphasis> command to display the list of machines from the
          file.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos removehost</emphasis> command to remove a machine from the file.</para>

        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In cells that use the Update Server to distribute the contents of the
      <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory, it is customary to edit only the copy of the
      file stored on the system control machine. Otherwise, edit the file on
      each server machine individually. For instructions on adding and removing
      database server machine, see the <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis> chapter on
      installing additional server machines.</para>

    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>CellServDB Format</title>
      <para>Both <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> files have the same format:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The first line begins at the left margin with the greater-than character
          (<computeroutput>&gt;</computeroutput>), followed immediately by the cell's name without an intervening
          space. Optionally, a comment can follow any number of spaces and a number
          sign (<computeroutput>#</computeroutput>), perhaps to identify the organization associated with the
          cell.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each subsequent line in the entry identifies one of the cell's database
          server machines, with the indicated information in order:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The database server machine's IP address in dotted-decimal format.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>One or more spaces.</para>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A number sign (#), followed by the machine's fully qualified hostname
              without an intervening space. This number sign does not indicate that the
              hostname is a comment. It is a required field.</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>No extra blank lines or newline characters are allowed in the file, even
      after the last entry. Their presence can prevent the Cache Manager from
      reading the file into kernel memory, resulting in an error message.</para>

      <para>grand.central.org maintains a list of the database server machines in all
      cells that have registered themselves as receptive to access from foreign
      cells. When a cell's administrators change its database server machines,
      it is customary to register the change with grand.central.org for
      inclusion in this file. The file conforms to the required <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable>
      format, and so is a suitable basis for the <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file on a client
      machine.  You can download this file from http://grand.central.org/.</para>

    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following example shows entries for two cells in a client
    <replaceable>CellServDB</replaceable> file and illustrates the required format.</para>

<programlisting>
   &amp;gt;abc.com        # ABC Corporation
   192.12.105.2	        #db1.abc.com
   192.12.105.3	        #db2.abc.com
   192.12.107.3	        #db3.abc.com
   &amp;gt;test.abc.com   # ABC Corporation Test Cell
   192.12.108.57        #testdb1.abc.com
   192.12.108.55        #testdb2.abc.com

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para><link linkend="bos_addhost8">bos_addhost(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_listhosts8">bos_listhosts(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_removehost8">bos_removehost(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="bos_setcellname8">bos_setcellname(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="buserver8">buserver(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="fs_newcell1">fs_newcell(1)</link>,
      <link linkend="kaserver8">kaserver(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="klog1">klog(1)</link>,
      <link linkend="ptserver8">ptserver(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="vlserver8">vlserver(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="upclient8">upclient(8)</link>,
      <link linkend="upserver8">upserver(8)</link></para>

      <para><emphasis>IBM AFS Quick Beginnings</emphasis></para>

    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Copyright</title>
      <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

      <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
      converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
      Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

    </refsect1>
  </refentry>
