<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="fms_log5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>fms.log</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>fms.log</refname>
    <refpurpose>Records output from the fms command</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>fms.log</replaceable> file records the output generated by the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis>
    command. The output includes two numbers that can appear in a tape
    device's entry in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/backup/tapeconfig</replaceable> file on the Tape
    Coordinator machine to which the tape device is attached:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The capacity in bytes of the tape in the device.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The size in bytes of the end-of-file (EOF) marks (often referred to simply
        as <emphasis>filemarks</emphasis>) that the tape device writes.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>When transferring the numbers recorded in this file to the <replaceable>tapeconfig</replaceable>
    file, adjust them as specified in <link linkend="tapeconfig5">tapeconfig(5)</link>, to improve Tape
    Coordinator performance during dump operations.</para>

    <para>If the <replaceable>fms.log</replaceable> file does not already exist in the current working
    directory, the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command interpreter creates it.  In this case, the
    directory's mode bits must grant the <computeroutput>rwx</computeroutput> (read, write, and execute)
    permissions to the issuer of the command. If there is an existing file,
    the command interpreter overwrites it, so the file's mode bits need to
    grant only the <emphasis role="bold">w</emphasis> permission to the issuer of the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command.  The
    <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command interpreter also writes similar information to the standard
    output stream as it runs.</para>

    <para>The file is in ASCII format. To display its contents, log onto the client
    machine and use a text editor or a file display command such as the UNIX
    <emphasis role="bold">cat</emphasis> command. By default, the mode bits on the <replaceable>fms.log</replaceable> file grant the
    required <computeroutput>r</computeroutput> permission only to the owner (which is the local superuser
    <computeroutput>root</computeroutput> by default).</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>The first few lines of the file provide a simple trace of the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis>
    command interpreter's actions, specifying (for example) how many blocks it
    wrote on the tape. The final two lines in the file specify tape capacity
    and filemark size in bytes, using the following format:</para>

<programlisting>
   Tape capacity is &amp;lt;tape_size&amp;gt; bytes
   File marks are &amp;lt;filemark_size&amp;gt; bytes

</programlisting>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <para>The following example of the fms.log file specifies that the tape used
      during the execution of the <emphasis role="bold">fms</emphasis> command had a capacity of 2,136,604,672
      bytes, and that the tape device writes filemarks of size 1,910,220 bytes.</para>

<programlisting>
   fms test started
   wrote 130408 blocks
   Tape capacity is 2136604672 bytes
   File marks are 1910220 bytes

</programlisting>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>See Also</title>
        <para><link linkend="tapeconfig5">tapeconfig(5)</link>,
        <link linkend="fms8">fms(8)</link></para>

      </refsect1>
      <refsect1>
        <title>Copyright</title>
        <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

        <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
        converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
        Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
