<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="kaserverauxdb5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kaserverauxdb</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kaserverauxdb</refname>
    <refpurpose>Records failed authentication attempts</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The file <replaceable>kaserverauxdb</replaceable> records failed authentication attempts for the
    local Authentication Server. The server creates it automatically in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/local</replaceable> directory by default; use the <emphasis role="bold">-localfiles</emphasis> argument to
    the <emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> command to specify an alternate directory.</para>

    <para>The <replaceable>kaserverauxdb</replaceable> file is an internal database used by the
    Authentication Server to prevent access by users who have exceeded the
    limit on failed authentication attempts defined in their Authentication
    Database entry. The Authentication Server refuses further attempts to
    authenticate to an account listed in the database until either an AFS
    system administrator issues the <emphasis role="bold">kas unlock</emphasis> command to unlock the
    account, or the timeout period defined in the user's Authentication
    Database entry passes.</para>

    <para>The <replaceable>kaserverauxdb</replaceable> file is in binary format, so its contents are not
    directly accessible. However, the output from the <emphasis role="bold">kas examine</emphasis> command
    reports an account's maximum number of failed attempts, the lockout time,
    and whether the account is currently locked.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="kaserver_DB05">kaserver.DB0(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="kas_examine8">kas_examine(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="kas_unlock8">kas_unlock(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="kaserver8">kaserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
