<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="kaserver_DB05">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>kaserver.DB0, kaserver.DBSYS1</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>kaserver.DB0, kaserver.DBSYS1</refname>
    <refpurpose>The Authentication Database and associated log</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>kaserver.DB0</replaceable> file contains the Authentication Database, which
    records server encryption keys and an encrypted form of all user
    passwords. The Authentication Server (<emphasis role="bold">kaserver</emphasis> process) uses the
    information in the database to enable secured communications between AFS
    server and client processes.</para>

    <para>The <replaceable>kaserver.DBSYS1</replaceable> file is a log file in which the Authentication
    Server logs each database operation before performing it. When an
    operation is interrupted, the Authentication Server replays the log to
    complete the operation.</para>

    <para>Both files are in binary format and reside in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/db</replaceable> directory
    on each of the cell's database server machines. When the Authentication
    Server starts or restarts on a given machine, it establishes a connection
    with its peers and verifies that its copy of the database matches the copy
    on the other database server machines. If not, the Authentication Servers
    call on AFS's distributed database technology, Ubik, to distribute to all
    of the machines the copy of the database with the highest version number.</para>

    <para>Always use the commands in the kas suite to administer the Authentication
    Database. It is advisable to create an archive copy of the database on a
    regular basis, using a tool such as the UNIX <emphasis role="bold">tar</emphasis> command.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="kadb_check8">kadb_check(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="kas8">kas(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="kaserver8">kaserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
