<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="NetInfo5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>NetInfo</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>NetInfo</refname>
    <refpurpose>Defines machine interfaces to register with AFS servers</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>There are two <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> files, one for an AFS client and one for an AFS
    File Server or database server.  The AFS client <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file specifies
    the IP addresses that the client should register with the File Servers it
    connects to.  The server <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file specifies what interfaces should
    be registered with AFS Database Servers or used to talk to other database
    servers.</para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Client NetInfo</title>
      <para>The client <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file lists the IP addresses of one or more of the
      local machine's network interfaces. If it exists in the <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc</replaceable>
      directory when the Cache Manager initializes, the Cache Manager uses its
      contents as the basis for a list of local interfaces. Otherwise, the Cache
      Manager uses the list of interfaces configured with the operating
      system. It then removes from the list any addresses that appear in the
      <replaceable>/usr/vice/etc/NetRestrict</replaceable> file, if it exists. The Cache Manager records
      the resulting list in kernel memory. The first time it establishes a
      connection to a File Server, it registers the list with the File Server.</para>

      <para>The File Server uses the addresses when it initiates a remote procedure
      call (RPC) to the Cache Manager (as opposed to responding to an RPC sent
      by the Cache Manager). There are two common circumstances in which the
      File Server initiates RPCs: when it breaks callbacks and when it pings the
      client machine to verify that the Cache Manager is still accessible.</para>

      <para>The <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file is in ASCII format. One of the machine's IP addresses
      appears on each line, in dotted decimal format. The File Server initially
      uses the address that appears first in the list. The order of the
      remaining addresses is not significant: if an RPC to the first interface
      fails, the File Server simultaneously sends RPCs to all of the other
      interfaces in the list.  Whichever interface replies first is the one to
      which the File Server then sends pings and RPCs to break callbacks.</para>

      <para>To prohibit the Cache Manager absolutely from using one or more addresses,
      list them in the <replaceable>NetRestrict</replaceable> file. To display the addresses the Cache
      Manager is currently registering with File Servers, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      getclientaddrs</emphasis> command. To replace the current list of interfaces with a
      new one between reboots of the client machine, use the <emphasis role="bold">fs
      setclientaddrs</emphasis> command.</para>

    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Server NetInfo</title>
      <para>The server <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file, if present in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local</replaceable> directory,
      defines the following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On a file server machine, the local interfaces that the File Server
          (<emphasis role="bold">fileserver</emphasis> process) can register in the Volume Location Database
          (VLDB) at initialization time.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>On a database server machine, the local interfaces that the Ubik database
          synchronization library uses when communicating with the database server
          processes running on other database server machines.</para>

        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If the <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file exists when the File Server initializes, the File
      Server uses its contents as the basis for a list of interfaces to register
      in the VLDB. Otherwise, it uses the list of network interfaces configured
      with the operating system. It then removes from the list any addresses
      that appear in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/NetRestrict</replaceable> file, if it exists. The
      File Server records the resulting list in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/sysid</replaceable> file
      and registers the interfaces in the VLDB. The database server processes
      use a similar procedure when initializing, to determine which interfaces
      to use for communication with the peer processes on other database
      machines in the cell.</para>

      <para>The <replaceable>NetInfo</replaceable> file is in ASCII format. One of the machine's IP addresses
      appears on each line, in dotted decimal format. The order of the addresses
      is not significant.</para>

      <para>To display the File Server interface addresses registered in the VLDB, use
      the <emphasis role="bold">vos listaddrs</emphasis> command.</para>

    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="sysid5">sysid(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="vldb_DB05">vldb.DB0(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="fileserver8">fileserver(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="fs_getclientaddrs1">fs_getclientaddrs(1)</link>,
    <link linkend="fs_setclientaddrs1">fs_setclientaddrs(1)</link>,
    <link linkend="vos_listaddrs1">vos_listaddrs(1)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
