<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="NoAuth5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>NoAuth</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>NoAuth</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disables authorization checking</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>NoAuth</replaceable> file, if present in a server machine's <replaceable>/usr/afs/local</replaceable>
    directory, indicates to the AFS server processes running on the machine
    that it is not necessary to perform authorization checking. They perform
    any action for any user who logs into the machine's local file system or
    issues a remote command that affects the machine's AFS server functioning,
    such as commands from the AFS command suites. Because failure to check
    authorization exposes the machine's AFS server functionality to attack,
    there are normally only two circumstances in which the file is present:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>During installation of the machine, as instructed in the <emphasis>IBM AFS Quick
        Beginnings</emphasis>.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>During correction of a server encryption key emergency, as discussed in
        the <emphasis>IBM AFS Administration Guide</emphasis>.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In all other circumstances, the absence of the file means that the AFS
    server processes perform authorization checking, verifying that the issuer
    of a command has the required privilege.</para>

    <para>Create the file in one of the following ways:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>By issuing the bosserver initialization command with the <emphasis role="bold">-noauth</emphasis> flag,
        if the Basic OverSeer (BOS) Server is not already running.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>By issuing the <emphasis role="bold">bos setauth</emphasis> command with off as the value for the
        <emphasis role="bold">-authrequired</emphasis> argument, if the BOS Server is already running.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>To remove the file, issue the <emphasis role="bold">bos setauth</emphasis> command with <computeroutput>on</computeroutput> as the
    value for the <emphasis role="bold">-authrequired</emphasis> argument.</para>

    <para>The file's contents, if any, are ignored; an empty (zero-length) file is
    effective.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="bos_setauth8">bos_setauth(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="bosserver8">bosserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
