<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="sysid5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>sysid</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>sysid</refname>
    <refpurpose>Lists file server machine interface addresses registered in VLDB</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>sysid</replaceable> file records the network interface addresses that the File
    Server (<emphasis role="bold">fileserver</emphasis> process) registers in the Volume Location Database
    (VLDB) for the local file server machine.</para>

    <para>Each time the File Server restarts, it builds a list of interfaces on the
    local machine by reading the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/NetInfo</replaceable> file, if it
    exists. If the file does not exist, the File Server uses the list of
    network interfaces configured with the operating system. It then removes
    from the list any addresses that appear in the
    <replaceable>/usr/afs/local/NetRestrict</replaceable> file, if it exists. The File Server records
    the resulting list in the binary-format <replaceable>sysid</replaceable> file and registers the
    interfaces in the VLDB.</para>

    <para>When the Cache Manager requests volume location information, the Volume
    Location (VL) Server provides all of the interfaces registered for each
    server machine that houses the volume. This enables the Cache Manager to
    make use of multiple addresses when accessing AFS data stored on a
    multihomed file server machine.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Cautions</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>sysid</replaceable> file is unique to each file server machine, and must not be
    copied from one machine to another. If it is a common practice in the cell
    to copy the contents of the <replaceable>/usr/afs/local</replaceable> directory from an existing
    file server machine to a newly installed one, be sure to remove the
    <replaceable>sysid</replaceable> file from the new machine before starting the <computeroutput>fs</computeroutput> trio of
    processes, which includes the <emphasis role="bold">fileserver</emphasis> process.</para>

    <para>Some versions of AFS limit how many of a file server machine's interface
    addresses that can be registered. Consult the <emphasis>IBM AFS Release Notes</emphasis>.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="NetInfo5">NetInfo(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="NetRestrict5">NetRestrict(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="vldb_DB05">vldb.DB0(5)</link>,
    <link linkend="fileserver8">fileserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
