<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="UserList5">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>UserList</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>UserList</refname>
    <refpurpose>Defines privileged administrators</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The <replaceable>UserList</replaceable> file lists the AFS usernames of the system administrators
    authorized to issue privileged <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">vos</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> commands that
    affect the local server machine or the volumes housed on it. It must
    reside in the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable> directory on every server machine.</para>

    <para>Although the <replaceable>UserList</replaceable> file is in ASCII format, do not use a text editor
    to alter it. Instead always use the appropriate commands from the <emphasis role="bold">bos</emphasis>
    command suite:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos adduser</emphasis> command to add a user to the file.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos listusers</emphasis> command to display the contents of the file.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">bos removeuser</emphasis> command to remove a user from the file.</para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Although it is theoretically possible to list different administrators in
    the <replaceable>UserList</replaceable> files on different server machines, doing so can cause
    unanticipated authorization failures and is not recommended. In cells that
    use the Update Server to distribute the contents of the <replaceable>/usr/afs/etc</replaceable>
    directory, it is customary to edit only the copy of the file stored on the
    system control machine. Otherwise, edit the file on each server machine
    individually.</para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="bos_adduser8">bos_adduser(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="bos_listusers8">bos_listusers(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="bos_removeuser8">bos_removeuser(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="upclient8">upclient(8)</link>,
    <link linkend="upserver8">upserver(8)</link></para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <para>IBM Corporation 2000. &lt;http://www.ibm.com/&gt; All Rights Reserved.</para>

    <para>This documentation is covered by the IBM Public License Version 1.0.  It was
    converted from HTML to POD by software written by Chas Williams and Russ
    Allbery, based on work by Alf Wachsmann and Elizabeth Cassell.</para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
